<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glass for George Fox the Quaker, and other Quakers; wherein they may see themselves to be right devils. In answer to George Fox his book, called, Something in answer to Lodowick Muggletons book, which he calls The Quakers neck broken. Wherein is set forth the ignorance and blindness of the Quakers doctrine of Christ within them; and that they cannot, nor doth not know the true meaning of the Scriptures, neither have they the gift of interpretation of Scripture. As will appear in those several heads set down in the next page following. / Written by Lodowick Muggleton ...</title>
            <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09558</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 13111686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10137</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13111686</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13111686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192297</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192297)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 746:12, 1641-1700 , 2913:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glass for George Fox the Quaker, and other Quakers; wherein they may see themselves to be right devils. In answer to George Fox his book, called, Something in answer to Lodowick Muggletons book, which he calls The Quakers neck broken. Wherein is set forth the ignorance and blindness of the Quakers doctrine of Christ within them; and that they cannot, nor doth not know the true meaning of the Scriptures, neither have they the gift of interpretation of Scripture. As will appear in those several heads set down in the next page following. / Written by Lodowick Muggleton ...</title>
                  <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In these copies the "7" in the imprint date has been changed in ms. to "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (746:12) and the Haverford College Library (2913:6).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fox, George, 1624-1691. --  Something in answer to Lodowick Muggleton's book, which he calls The Quaker's neck broken.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Looking-Glaſs FOR GEORGE FOX THE QUAKER, And other QUAKERS; Wherein they may ſee themſelves to be Right Devils.</p>
            <p>In ANSWER to <hi>George Fox</hi> his Book, CALLED, <hi>Something in Anſwer to</hi> Lodowick Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gletons <hi>Book, which he calls</hi> The <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AKERS</hi> Neck broken.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſet forth the Ignorance and blindneſs of the Quakers Doctrine of Chriſt within them; and that they cannot, nor doth not know the true meaning of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, neither have they the Gift of Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture.</p>
            <p>As will appear in thoſe ſeveral Heads ſet down in the next Page following.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> one of the two laſt Prophets and Witneſſes unto the High and Mighty God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHap. 1.</hi> Of a Catalogue of damned Quakers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2.</hi> Sheweth the ignorance and fooliſhneſs of <hi>George Fox.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3</hi> How the Quaker people are altogether ignorant of Heavenly Secrets, ſo become the greateſt deſpiſers of them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> A diſcovery of the Quakers blindneſs which cannot diſcern whether a man that preaches the Goſpel ought to have his Commiſſion from Chriſt without him, or from a Chriſt within him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Sheweth how ignorant and dark the Quakers people are in the knowledge of the right devil, and of the ſerpents ſeed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> How the ſoul of man is mortal, and doth die, yet <hi>Fox</hi> thinks it impoſſible to prove by Scripture.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap 7.</hi> How it was no lie to accuſe the Quakers of ſin and blaſphemy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> The right devil proved.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> How the Quakers are miſtaken in the fleſh and bone of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> How God hath made the Witneſſes of the Spirit Judge in his ſtead.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Sheweth that the body of Chriſts fleſh and bone is diſtinct of it ſelf, and not in the Quakers bodies, neither are they members of his body.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Sheweth by Scripture how Chriſt dwelleth in his Saints, and how it may be ſaid they are fleſh of his fl ſh, and bone of his bone.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> How <hi>Fox</hi> is proved a devil, becauſe he cannot give a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he is no reprobate.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> An Explanation how <hi>George Fox</hi> and other Quakers, may be ſaid to appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> A further Interpretation concerning the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> How the Sentence and Curſe hath ſubdued thoſe Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft-fits in the Quakers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> How ſpirits cannot aſſume what ſhapes they pleaſe, neither can there appear any ſpirit without a body.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> How the true God is no bigger than the compaſs of a man, and no ſpirit without a body, as the Quakers doth vainly imagine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap 19.</hi> How the Quakers may ſee themſelves to be right devils.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:192297:5"/>
                  <hi>Chap 20.</hi> How the Quakers are more Antichriſtian in their doctrine, than the Pope.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 21.</hi> How the body of Chriſts fleſh and bone is diſtinct from the Quakers bodies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 22.</hi> That which killed the righteous and juſt, it was the ſpirit of reaſon the devil in man that always did it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 23.</hi> A difference between reaſonable and unreaſonable men, and a further diſcovery that reaſon is the devil.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 24.</hi> How the ſoul of Chriſt died, and the ignorance of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers diſcovered in the death of their own ſouls.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 25.</hi> It is proved that Chriſt the onely God is not in this world at all, in his perſon or eſſence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 26.</hi> How men cannot worſhip God in ſpirit and truth without bodies, and how <hi>Muggleton</hi> never was in the ſpirit of <hi>Solomon,</hi> nor never ſhall be.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 27.</hi> A great ſtir the Prophet <hi>Muggleton</hi> hath to keep the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſpirits out of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 28.</hi> How <hi>Fox</hi> juſtifies the Magiſtrates perſecuting of me in <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſhire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 29.</hi> How the Curſe of <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſhall remain upon <hi>Fox</hi> to eternity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 30.</hi> How the Curſe and Sentence of <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſhall be over, and upon the ſpirits of the Quakers to eternity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 31.</hi> How the Law written in the Quakers herats, is that Chriſt they could have ſpoken in had they never ſeen letter of Scripture, nor man that profeſſeth it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 32.</hi> How their confidence will fail them in the day of trouble.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 33.</hi> How <hi>Fox</hi> ſhall ſee no other God or Judge, but that Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <hi>Reeve</hi> and <hi>Muggleton</hi> hath paſſed upon him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 34.</hi> A reproof the Quakers for rejoycing in my ſufferings, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſorry the Magiſtrates did not puniſh me more than impriſonment.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 35.</hi> How it doth belong unto mortal men that are choſen of God to interpret Scripture, and not unto Chriſt himſelf.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 36.</hi> How every true Prophet and Miniſter of Chriſt, hath power to open the Book of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>In the laſt place I ſhall ſay ſomething as to the Quakers Principle and Practice.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192297:5"/>
            <head>A Looking-Glaſs for <hi>George Fox</hi> the Quaker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Eorge Fox,</hi> I ſaw a Pamphlet of yours, Entituled, <hi>Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Anſwer to</hi> Lodowick Muggletons <hi>Book, which he calls</hi> The Quakers Neck broken.</p>
               <p>You ſaid well in that you ſaid, ſomething in Anſwer to that Book of the <hi>Quakers Neck broken,</hi> for it is a very little ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing indeed; it is ſo little a ſomething, that wiſe men will hardly diſcern any thing in it as a direct Anſwer: but how comes it to paſs that you make no mention of your own damnation in your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; you know <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf gave you the Sentence of Damnation a matter of fourteen years ago; when we were priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in <hi>Old Bridewel,</hi> there was you, <hi>Edward Borroughs,</hi> and <hi>Francis Howgel,</hi> you three were counted the Chief Speakers of the Quakers at that time, and you three were the firſt Speakers of the Quakers that were damn'd by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, but ſince that there hath fallen a many more of your brethren under this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; but you have been <hi>Fox</hi>-like, as is your name, ſo is your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, you have lain ſtill, and kept your damnation to your ſelf from the knowledge of others, becauſe you would not be upon pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Record as a damn'd Devil, and yet a Speaker of the Quakers.</p>
               <p>Alſo you read of your name in that Book, you ſay you have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſomething, but you take no notice of your ſelf, but take o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther folks parts; and if your brethren <hi>William Smith, Samuel Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Edward Bourn, Richard Farnſworth,</hi> had not written to me, there would have been no occaſion for the <hi>Fox</hi> to come out of his hole, and now the <hi>Fox</hi> is come out, he will be catcht and made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to Generations to come, who pretended to be a means of ſalvation to others, and yet he himſelf a caſt-away, a reprobate, a ſon of the Devil, one that ſhall be recorded amongſt the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Crew to the worlds end, and I am ſure your Damnation is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192297:6"/>
written in the Tables of Heaven, even as the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was written in the Tables of Stone, that is, theſe men were written the ſeed of the Serpent in Heaven in the Reprobate Angel his nature, before he deceived <hi>Evah;</hi> for you Speakers of the Quakers doth act forth the Serpent Angel his nature, thinking your ſelves wiſer than God, as he did; he thought if he had been God, he could have made all thoſe glorious Creatures above the ſtars of nothing; even ſo be you Quakers here in mortality, you teach your diſciples to believe that God made this vaſt Earth and Waters of nothing, witneſs that <hi>Thomas Taylor</hi> Speaker of the Quakers, in his Letters to me, which I have given Anſwer to, and joyn'd it to the Book called <hi>The Quakers Neck broken;</hi> and you <hi>Fox</hi> and others of your Speakers doth the ſame, for you ſay you were in Chriſt before the world was, here you are quite miſtaken, for you were in the Reprobate Angel his ſeed and nature, who is called a <hi>Serpent,</hi> and in this Serpent Angel you and others were in before the world was, and ſo you and others were recorded in the Table of Heaven for the Reprobate ſeed, and to be damned to eternity.</p>
               <p>And as I know from whence you came, even from the Serpent aforeſaid, and that you were in him before the world was, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you ſhall be recorded for damned devils here while the world is, as long as time doth laſt, therefore I ſhall ſet you down as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, you being one of the grand Devils, you ſhall be firſt:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox, Edward Borroughs, Francis Howgel, Edward Bourn, William Smith, Samuel Hooton, Richard Farnſworth, Thomas Taylor, John Parrat, Richard Whitpane, John Harwood, Richard Hubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn, Fox</hi> the younger, and that great lubbardly fellow ſpoken of in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> theſe were generally all, or moſt of them Speakers of the Quakers, and exerciſed the Miniſterial prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching without a Commiſſion from God, and not onely ſo, but they have been the greateſt fighters againſt a perſonal God in Heaven above the ſtars of any, and have ſinned againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent us, and ſo have procured the Sentence of eternal Damnation upon them, and this Record is true, and it ſhall be recorded in the hearts of the Saints to the worlds end.</p>
               <p>Now I ſhall give you an Anſwer to what is needful in <hi>George Fox</hi> his Book, if there be any thing in it that is not ſufficiently An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered already in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> I am willing to do it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192297:6"/>
for the ſakes of ſome that deſire it, becauſe I hear the Quakers are very brag of this Book <hi>George Fox</hi> hath writ againſt me, ſo they were when <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> printed his Rage and Malice againſt me, but did he proſper afterwards when I had printed an Anſwer to it? For that printed Pamphlet was the occaſion of <hi>The Quakers Neck broken</hi> being printed; and doth <hi>George Fox</hi> think to proſper now he hath manifeſted himſelf what he is? and his great wiſdom which ſome thought he had, will be found but meer fooliſhneſs.</p>
               <p>But to the matter in hand. The firſt Accuſation that I am ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed with, is as followeth, <hi>That I ſay in</hi> The Quakers Neck bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>that the Quakers will not beſtow a penny in any Writings but their own, let it coſt them never ſo much pains the writing, and charge in printing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>George Fox</hi> ſaith is a lye, known to the Printers and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, and Book-ſellers at <hi>London:</hi> and <hi>George Fox</hi> hath called me a Lier ſeven times for this one lye, as he calls it, yet I ſhall make it appear I told no lye in thoſe words, to ſay the Quakers will not beſtow a penny in any Writings but their own, let them coſt ever ſo much pains the writing, and charge the printing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Lodowick Muggleton's</hi> Anſwer.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, I would have the Reader to minde the ignorance and fooliſhneſs of this <hi>George Fox,</hi> he undertakes to anſwer ſome things in my Book called <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> and the firſt thing he begins to anſwer is the laſt thing in my Book, for it is the laſt page of my Book, and it is a point of the leaſt concernment to a mans eternal happineſs of any in that Book, but <hi>George Fox</hi> hath made it of the greateſt concernment of all the reſt; therefore he begins with that firſt, and ſets it in the Fore-front of his Pamphlet, to ſhew his Maſter-piece; for he hath ſet the Cart before the horſe, for he begins at the latter end of the Book and ſo goes backwards towards the beginning, and charges me with a lying ſpirit ſeven times in this one thing, as if this was the moſt hainous ſin of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins, that to ſay the Quakers would not beſtow a penny up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Writings but their own, this is counted a ſeven-fold worſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:192297:7"/>
ſin, than any other ſin whatſoever: Let the Reader but minde theſe things aforeſaid, and what I ſhall ſay in anſwer to <hi>George Fox</hi> his printed Pamphlet.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>George Fox</hi> hath gone on like an unwiſe, ſimple, fooliſh man, no ways in order, but confuſed, to begin at the latter end of a Book, and end at the beginning, and catch a bit here, and ſnap at a bit in another place, and wrong the words, and write ſome part of a ſentence that ſerves his turn, and leaves the other part out that would make againſt him, or clear the matter, this he leaves out. Now I do commend <hi>William Smith</hi> and <hi>Richard Farnſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> though they are damned Devils, yet they went orderly to work, they named my words right as they were ſet down, and they rayled againſt me in order, and ſo went on from point to point in order: but you <hi>George Fox,</hi> your Anſwer is confuſed, for the aforeſaid Quakers had a great deal more wiſdom in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings againſt me than you have. Becauſe I ſpeak of order, you Quakers may think I mean good order, and ſo the aforeſaid men were good men, [no] but they went in the method and order of Reaſon the Devil; in the wiſdom of Reaſon did they write to me, and I was well pleaſed with it, becauſe I knew well enough how to anſwer Reaſon the Devil in his beſt and orderlieſt wiſdom he hath, as is now extant in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken;</hi> but you, if you have not attained that wiſdom of Reaſon the aforeſaid Quakers your brethren have attained, for you that are the old Fox is become more ignorant and fooliſh in ſpiritual matters than the aforeſaid that are younger.</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying of mine, that you make the greateſt ſin of all, in that I belye the Quakers, to ſay they will not beſtow a penny in any Writings but their own, that ſaying of mine is very true; for my meaning was, the Quakers would not beſtow a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon any of my Writings, though they coſt never ſo much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor the writing, and charge the printing; and ſo the following words doth clear my meaning; but <hi>George Fox</hi> hath catcht at that word of mine <hi>[of any other Writings but their own]</hi> here was a word out of joynt, and that the Fox was glad of; for if I had made a diſtinction between my Writings and others, as my meaning was, and as my words following did imply, then the Fox would have had no hole to have crept out at, nor to have called me a Liar
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:192297:7"/>
ſeven times for one: but as for the Quakers not beſtowing a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon any Writings, though they coſt ever ſo much pains the writing, and coſt the printing, that is very true; for I do not know any Quaker, that is an abſolute Quaker, that ever did buy any: Alſo it is credibly reported to me by ſome that have been Quakers, but fallen from them, that ſeveral of the Quakers have given a charge to others of their acquaintance that had a minde to buy, to ſee what was in them, the rumour was ſo great; but the Quakers charged thoſe that had a minde to buy, not to buy any, not to beſtow a penny on them, except it were to burn them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if they had any of my Writings they would burn them, and theſe were Qakers that ſaid this; ſo that this proves my ſayings to be true, both by experience and witneſs. But <hi>George Fox</hi> hath got the Printers, and Stationers, and Book-ſellers in <hi>London</hi> to prove me a Liar, as if the Quakers had been great Cuſtomers to the Book-ſellers: I ſuppoſe <hi>Jacob Behmont</hi>'s Books were the chief Books that the Quakers bought, for there is the Principle or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their Religion; for they cannot go beyond that, but there they build, this I know by <hi>William Smiths</hi> Lettters to me: And you <hi>George Fox</hi> are far below <hi>William Smith</hi> in the knowledge of <hi>Jacob Behmonts</hi> Writings; and as for what Books elſe that you Quakers have beſtowed money upon ſince you were Quakers, I think the Stationers will neither juſtifie, neither can you ſhew none of any value: but it is not much matter whether you did or did not, I am ſure that ſaying of mine is true, that you will not beſtow a penny upon my Writings, though they coſt much pains the writing, and much charge the printing: this you <hi>Fox</hi> doth not deny, ſo that part of my words are true by your own acknowledgement, ſo that it is but half a Lie that you charge me with, in caſe the words be taken in your ſenſe, yet you charge this half Lie to be ſeven Lies. So much for that.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>L. Muggleton</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is a vain thing to talk of any Heavenly Secrets to Quakers, for they will not beſtow a penny of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi> calls this a Lie alſo, and ſaith, Heavenly Secrets are eſteemed of by them, ſcornfully called <hi>Quakers,</hi> and ſaith that <hi>Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gletons</hi> Heavenly Secrets are money worth, and may be bought with a price, and complains againſt me, becauſe ſome of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers of this Commiſſion would not lend <hi>George Fox</hi> a Book of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:192297:8"/>
ten ſhillings price, to peruſe, to rayl againſt, and ſaith the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, as I call them, are free with their Books to give them to any one to read: but ſaith, <hi>It is a hard thing to get any of my Books;</hi> and ſaith, <hi>that I would not let them be brought forth unto light, left my Deeds, Curſes, and Lies,</hi> as he calls them, <hi>ſhould be made manifeſt; for the Quakers,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in the divine light, power, and ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus do comprehend thy ſpirit and ſcoffs, at the divine light of Chriſt Jeſus within.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> THis I do know, it is a vain thing to talk of any Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Secrets to Quakers, neither do the Quakers eſteem of Heavenly Secrets at all, but doth altogether deſpiſe and hate them; for what need the Quakers and I conteſt ſo one againſt the other? or why ſhould I have curſed ſo many Quakers as I have? If the Quakers had eſteemed Heavenly Secrets, then ſhould we the Witneſſes of the Spirit never have been ſo contrary to them, as now we are; for the Quakers have deſpiſed Heavenly Secrets more than any other Sect whatſoever. Is not this a Heavenly Secret to declare what the true God is in his Form and Nature; Alſo this is a Heavenly Secret to ſhew what the Right Devil is in his Form and Nature. It is a Heavenly Secret to know the place of Hell, and the manner of Torment. It is a Heavenly Seeret to know the Reſidence of Heaven, and the Aſſurance to poſſeſs the Joys there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to eternity. It is a Heavenly Secret to know really that the Soul or Life of Chriſt did dye, and that a mans own ſoul or ſpirit muſt, and doth dye. It is alſo a Heavenly Secret to know the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and nature of Angels. Theſe all are great Heavenly Secrets, with many more Heavenly Secrets declared in our Writings, which dependeth upon theſe aforeſaid; but the Quakers deſpiſeth every one of theſe Heavenly Secrets; ſo that you Quakers cannot eſteem of any Heavenly Secrets; ſo that I know it is a vain thing to talk of Heavenly Secrets to Quakers. For I will appeal to the greateſt enemies I have of another Opinion that differs from the Quakers, that if all their Writings which they have all writ ever ſince they were Quakers, if they were brought together, there is not one Heavenly Secret in them all; nay, if it were poſſible, that all the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:192297:8"/>
Quakers ſpeakings were bound in a bundle together, I know there would not be one Heavenly Secret, or true Principle to be found amongſt them all: they are worſe as to that than <hi>Sodom</hi> was, for there was one righteous perſon found in thoſe two Cities, and but one, even righteous <hi>Lot;</hi> but let our Writings and Speakings be put in a balance, and yours in another, and let mine enemies judge, though I know people will be more angry at my Heavenly Secrets I have written, than they will of thoſe Heavenly Secrets you Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers eſteem of; for thoſe Heavenly Secrets the Quakers do eſteem of, they are ſo groundleſs, that a man can diſcern no heavenlineſs in them at all. And as for thoſe Books my diſciples, as you call them, would not lend you, I will give the Fox a reaſon for it. The reaſon is, I did deſire thoſe that had thoſe Books, who believed the matter contained in them, I would not have them lend them to Quakers; for one <hi>Thomas Barnet</hi> formerly a Quaker, but afterwards believed theſe Writings, and he bought one bound together, and he out of love to <hi>Thomas Taylor</hi> Quaker, this ſaid <hi>Thomas Barnet</hi> did lend him his Book, thinking he might receive it as he did; but this <hi>Thomas Taylor</hi> deſpiſed it, and not onely ſo, but did abuſe the Book very baſely by writing upon the Margent, which thing procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Thomas Taylors</hi> Curſe; ſo others of our friends have lent Books to Prieſts, and they have abuſed them in like manner, ſo that I was not willing that friends ſhould lend Books to Quakers or others, onely <hi>The Quakers Neck broken</hi> I was alwayes free they ſhould be lent to Quakers or others: but it was a Book all bound together, where the Heavenly Secrets are declared, that you ſent your friend to borrow, and becauſe the Believers would not lend them, you upbraid me, as if I were unwilling my Curſes and Lies, as you call them, ſhould be brought to light. But if you Quakers would have made my Curſes and Lies, as you call them, manifeſt, and that you Quakers could comprehend me, you ſhould have bought one of them, and have made it your Church-Bible, and taken your Text out of it every time you meet, your Hearers would have edified more by your reading a Chapter in that when you meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, than by all the Speakings that ever they heard in their lives, it would have coſt you but ten ſhillings; you might have had it out of the Church Stock, and have let it to have been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to all Quakers and others to ſee, and ſo you might have made
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:192297:9"/>
me manifeſt indeed; but if you ſhould do ſo, what would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of you Speakers of the Quakers? then your light within, and your Chriſt within you, would come to nothing, and ſo you would cheat the people no longer with your ninny-nonies &amp; ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs words, to ſtand pratling every week, of words over and over forty times together, <hi>The word of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>Hearken to the light within you,</hi> or <hi>The light within you.</hi> Cannot you when the people meet, ſpeak theſe words forty times over and ſo diſmiſs them, then they would underſtand what you mean; but you deliver a great deal of non-ſenſe over and over again, ſo when the people are diſmiſt, they go away with their hearts full of non-ſence, and by the next week they will be emptied again; and theſe are the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Secrets the Quakers feed the people with.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Muggleton, <hi>thou ſayeſt thou haſt a Commiſſion from without thee to preach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>Fox</hi> hath belied my words, and left out ſome part; for theſe are my words, I do ſay that I have a Commiſſion from God without me to preach: this I own to be true.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have manifeſted darkneſs: and,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is there any Commiſſion from God, but the underſtanding of it is given to man by the divine light within?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Fox</hi> calls every thing darkneſs, though it be as clear a light as the Sun at noon-day; for who ever ſhall read the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words in that Book, may clearly ſee that the light of Chriſt within a man is not a ſufficient Commiſſion to authorize a man to be a Preacher of the Goſpel, though a man may have underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him to do it, yet for want of Authority from a God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, he will be puniſhed for going to preach before he is ſent: This may be experienced by all men in temporals, we ſee a Petty-Conſtable and other Officers more inferior, dares not execute their office upon any man, if it be but to whip beggars, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Commiſſion from ſome perſon, one or more without him; and ſo it is in all places both high and low upon the face of this earth.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192297:9"/>
It is not the underſtanding within that will authorize men to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſuch and ſuch places, but it muſt be Authority without a man; for many men that are in great and honorable places, have leſs wiſdom and underſtanding to manage their places than other men, yet he that hath a Commiſſion from others without him, will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him that hath a better underſtanding within than himſelf; yet you Quakers will undertake to be Preachers of the Goſpel without a Commiſſion from God without you, or without a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from Man without you: And becauſe I durſt not preach without a Commiſſion from God without me, and not by the light of Chriſt within me, though I had the light of Chriſt within me more than any Quaker in the world hath at this day, before I had a Commiſſion from God without me; and if God without me had not forc'd me to take this Commiſſion upon me, I had remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned quiet and ſtill, and had let Quakers and all other Opinions in Religion alone; for I was of <hi>Jonas</hi> his minde, willing to ſit ſtill and be quiet, for I minded no bodies happineſs but my own: for I was willing to go to <hi>Tarſhiſh</hi> to ſit down in quiet, but I was forced by the Lord God to go to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> amongſt all Opinions of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that I might be envied, hated, and perſecuted of Quakers, and all other Opinions whatſoever; and this I have found true by experience, and all this came upon me from a Commiſſion of the true God without me, and this you Quakers calls <hi>manifeſted darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle might truly ſay when it pleaſed the Father to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal his Son in him, <hi>he preached him;</hi> but what is this to <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker? The Father hath not revealed the Son in him; for <hi>Fox</hi> doth not know what the Son is: but the Apoſtle that had the Son revealed in him, had a Commiſſion from that Son without him: For ſure you Quakers will not be ſo wicked as to ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his Commiſſion to preach within him, when he breathed out threatnings againſt the Church of Chriſt, and went with Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Commiſſion from the High-prieſts to perſecute thoſe that believed in Jeſus that was put to death, and riſen again, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up to Heaven.</p>
               <p>Now this Jeſus met <hi>Saul</hi> in the way as he went to perſecute the Saints, and ſaid, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me? Saul</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Lord, who art thou?</hi> The Anſwer was, <hi>I am Jeſus of Nazareth.</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:192297:10"/>
Will you <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker ſay that this Jeſus was within <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſpake theſe words, or without him? Sure you will not be ſo wicked to ſay Jeſus was within <hi>Paul,</hi> what ever you think: and if you grant that Jeſus was without him, then <hi>Paul</hi> received his Commiſſion to preach from Jeſus Chriſt the onely Wiſe God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him: For this ſame Jeſus ſaid to <hi>Paul, Thou art a choſen Veſſel, and thou ſhalt bear,</hi> or preach, <hi>my Name before the Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I ask, did <hi>Paul</hi> receive his Commiſſion to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Jeſus Chriſt to the Gentiles, from Jeſus Chriſt without him, or from Chriſt within him? Again, who was that which ſpake to <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>My grace is ſufficient?</hi> Was it not Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? Was this Chriſt within <hi>Paul</hi> then? Was he not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Paul</hi> in that ſame fleſh and bone he ſuffered death in? This fleſh and bone was ſpiritual after it riſe again, but ſtill it kept it ſelf an entire body to its ſelf: And are you Quakers ſo void of ſenſe as to believe that the body of Chriſt is in you, and ſo reveals things to you? So you may ſee that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> received his Commiſſion to preach from a Chriſt without him, and not from a Chriſt within him: And I received my Commiſſion from Chriſt without me, and not from Chriſt within me. And <hi>Fox</hi> the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker ſaith, I have manifeſted my darkneſs: But this power I have received from the perſon of Chriſt without me, will be too hard for all the Quakers Chriſt within them in the world.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Muggleton, <hi>Thou ſayeſt the Right Devil became fleſh, and the Soul is mortal; and thou ſpeakeſt of thy knowledge of the Lord, and the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fox his words.</hi> Where do the Scriptures ſay that the Right De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil became fleſh, and the Soul is mortal? for God breathed into man the breath of life, through which he became a living Soul, and this breath of life by which man became a living Soul, is this mortal? is this thy knowledge? Make this good by Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have proved theſe two things abundantly by Scripture in my other Writings, in <hi>The Mortality of the Soul,</hi> and <hi>The Divine
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192297:10"/>
Looking-Glaſs,</hi> and in <hi>The Interpretation of the Eleventh of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and in <hi>The Interpretation of the whole Book of the Revelation;</hi> theſe ſeveral Books written by us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, hath clearly opened thoſe two points as much as any one thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: but I perceive this <hi>Fox</hi> hath ſeen none of our Books, not as to read them, but this book onely of the <hi>Quakers Neck broken,</hi> which makes him ſo ignorant of the Scriptures, and of what we have written; alſo its proves my words true, that the Quakers will not beſtow a penny in any of my Writings, but their own. But becauſe ſome may ſee this Anſwer to <hi>Fox,</hi> that hath not ſeen the other books afore-mentioned, I ſhall prove by the Scriptures again that the Right Devil became fleſh, and the Soul of man to be mortal.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall prove the Devil became fleſh. Let the Reader minde the Interpretation of Scripture. In the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> chap. 3. verſe 8. it is thus written, <hi>He that committeth ſin is of the Devil; for the Devil ſinneth from the beginning.</hi> Mark theſe words, <hi>The Devil ſinneth from the beginning:</hi> I think there is no man ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly ignorant to ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> was this Devil that ſinned from the beginning, for <hi>Adam</hi> was never called a Devil not throughout the Scriptures; for <hi>Adam</hi> is called the Father of Chriſt, and there is none will dare to ſay the Devil was the Father of Chriſt; which I ſhall open more clear hereafter: but then of neceſſity there muſt be ſome other Devil in the beginning which all men are ignorant of in theſe our days, but this Commiſſion of the Spirit onely. Now this Devil that committeth ſin from the beginning, muſt needs be that Serpent that was called <hi>A Tree of knowledge of good and evil,</hi> this I declare was the Devil: now this Devil became fleſh, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he became fleſh, then the devil committed ſin, and this was in the beginning of the world; for the faith of the Scriptures goeth no further than the beginning of the Creation of <hi>Adam.</hi> Now minde the twelfth verſe, that proves that <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt devil in fleſh. <hi>John</hi> exhorting the Believers <hi>that they ſhould love one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which Commandment was from the beginning, not as</hi> Cain, <hi>who was of that wicked one, and ſlew his brother.</hi> Here it is clear that <hi>Cain</hi> was none of <hi>Adams</hi> ſon; for <hi>Adam</hi> was never counted a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked one by any that writ Scripture, ſo that <hi>Cains</hi> father was the devil, that is, he was that Serpent Angel that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192297:11"/>
                  <hi>Cain</hi> was the devil manifeſt in fleſh; and that act of murther which <hi>Cain</hi> did when he ſlew his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> is that ſin which the devil committed from the beginning; for what the devil did before he became fleſh, was not counted by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to be ſin; for ſin was not imputed to ſpiritual bodies, but to natural bodies onely: for ſpiritual bodies are either to receive the fruit of happineſs, or the puniſhment of what they do in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural body of fleſh.</p>
               <p>Again, that I may give the Reader a further proof of this, minde the Scripture ſaith there are two Seeds, the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed of the Serpent, now God hath put emnity between theſe two Seeds: now I would fain know of <hi>Fox</hi> from whence this Seed of the Serpent came. If he ſhall ſay, it came from <hi>Adam,</hi> as moſt Quakers do, they blaſpheme againſt God that made <hi>Adam</hi> in his own image and likeneſs, both ſpirit and body, onely <hi>Adam</hi> was earthly, and God was heavenly; but <hi>Adam</hi> had but one Seed in his Creation, but as men are generated they come to have two Seeds in them; ſo that this Seed of the Serpent muſt needs be from the fallen Angel that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> who was called <hi>A Tree of Knowledge of good and evil;</hi> and this Seed of the Serpent that ſhould be at enmity with the Seed of the Woman, it is the devil in fleſh; for God owns the Seed of the Woman to be his own Seed, ſo that <hi>Cain</hi> was the devil became fleſh, blood, and bone: and that ſeed of Reaſon in <hi>Cain</hi> being now become mortal, which was immortal before <hi>Eve</hi> ate of the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, it comes to commit ſin from the beginning, and to generate and bring forth millions of devils of his own ſeed and nature, and ſo the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the two Seeds continues from generation to generation to the worlds end.</p>
               <p>For we read in Scripture that <hi>Cain</hi> is the Father of all wicked men and women, and that wicked men and women are his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as the Reader may ſee in <hi>Matthew</hi> how the devil tempted Chriſt, that devil that tempted Chriſt was a man, yet called a <hi>Devil,</hi> as you may ſee <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> the ſixth, and the ſixteenth verſe, that the Jewes that tempted God are called <hi>Devils:</hi> and when Chriſt anſwered the devil, and ſaid, <hi>It is written, thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God, but him onely ſhalt thou ſerve:</hi> ſo that rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious men are called the <hi>Devil</hi> that tempt God. And where was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192297:11"/>
there ever given any Law to any other devil but to man, to ſerve the Lord his God? So that it may be clear to the Seed of Faith that man is a devil, and that there is no other devil that can, or doth tempt God, but man.</p>
               <p>Again, it is clear that men are the children of the devil: now they cannot be children of the devil, except they be of his ſeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of him, and this is clear by Scripture, as may be read, <hi>John</hi> 8. verſe 44. Chriſt ſaith to the Jews that were men, who ſaid they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> children, and ſaid they were Gods children; but Chriſt ſaith theſe men were the devils children: <hi>Ye are,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of your father the devil, and the luſts of your father you will do, he was a murtherer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth, becauſe there is no truth in him; when he ſpeaketh a lie, he ſpeaketh of his own; for he is a Liar, and the father of it.</hi> Now minde, there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was no liar, nor murderer but man, and <hi>Cain</hi> being the firſt murderer and liar from the beginning; for when <hi>Cain</hi> killed <hi>Abel,</hi> and lied unto God, and ſaid, <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi> this was the firſt murder and lie the devil <hi>Cain</hi> committed upon earth after the devil became fleſh; therefore called by the Spirit of Revelation of Faith, <hi>A murderer and a liar from the beginning;</hi> for then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in fleſh began to murder and lie, and ſo this ſin hath run in the line of all his poſterity from generation to generation, ſo that the Reader may ſee that men are the children of the devil, and that the devil their father was a man, even <hi>Cain.</hi> This is the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Scriptures, and from this <hi>Cain</hi> did <hi>Feorge Fox</hi> come, and this <hi>Cain</hi> is his father, this I know for a certain truth.</p>
               <p>And to ſtop the mouth of that Objection which Quakers and all others do make, in that <hi>Adam</hi> knew his wife <hi>Eve,</hi> and ſhe concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and bare <hi>Cain,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>I have gotten a man from the Lord:</hi> To this I ſay, ſhe was with childe by the Angel before: but after <hi>Adam</hi> and ſhe were put forth of the Garden, that was from the preſence of God, then it is ſaid, <hi>Adam knew his wife, and ſhe conceived and bare</hi> Cain, <hi>and ſhe ſaid he had received a man from the Lord,</hi> and yet that <hi>Cain</hi> was none of <hi>Adams</hi> begetting; for we never read in Scripture that ever <hi>Adam</hi> begot <hi>Cain,</hi> neither is <hi>Adam</hi> called <hi>Cains</hi> father; but ſhe was with childe by that Serpent Angel before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> knew her, but he was but a cloak to cover her ſin; as many adulterous women have been with childe by other men that were
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192297:12"/>
not their husbands, yet their husbands have been a cloak to cover their ſhame, and the childe hath been counted her husbands, which was nothing ſo. This many can experience if they would, and that many of the Quakers too, when they were Ranters, if not ſince; ſo that <hi>Cain</hi> was none of <hi>Adams</hi> begetting, though he knew his wife <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſome may ſay, Why did not <hi>Moſes</hi> tell us theſe things? To that I ſay, it was not made known to him, nor to no other till now, but to the Witneſſes of the Spirit onely. The condition of <hi>Eve</hi> was much like the condition of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, ſhe was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed to <hi>Joſeph</hi> before ſhe was with childe by the Holy Ghoſt; but <hi>Joſeph</hi> never knew her before, nor after ſhe was with childe by the Holy Ghoſt, till that Childe Jeſus was born; therefore Jeſus is called <hi>Emanuel, that is God with us;</hi> that is, God was born of a Virgin. Alſo <hi>Mary</hi> is ſaid to conceive with childe by the Holy Ghoſt, yet if <hi>Joſeph</hi> had known <hi>Mary</hi> his eſpouſed wife in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim of her Conception by the Holy Ghoſt, it is like that <hi>Mary</hi> would have ſaid that ſhe had received her Childe Jeſus from <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> her husband, for ſhe could not tell which got it, if ſuch a thing ſhould have been: but it was otherwiſe ordered with her than it was with <hi>Eve;</hi> for <hi>Adam</hi> knew <hi>Eve</hi> as ſoon as the Angel had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into her womb, and then <hi>Adam</hi> knew his wife after they were put forth from the preſence of God; ſo that <hi>Eva</hi> did not know which ſhe was with childe by, the Serpent Angel, or her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo that ſhe might well ſay, <hi>ſhe had received a man from the Lord:</hi> but if <hi>Eve</hi> had not enticed her husband to know her, that was, eating of the forbidden fruit, ſhe would have brought forth according to the time of life that very ſame devil <hi>Cain,</hi> fleſh, blood, and bone, as ſhe did, if <hi>Adam</hi> had never known her in that time; even as the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> did the bleſſed Jeſus, the God and Savior of the Seed of <hi>Adam,</hi> with fleſh, blood, and bone; So that the Reader may ſee clearly that <hi>Adam</hi> was not <hi>Cains</hi> father, neither did he beget him, for <hi>Cain</hi> was the devil became fleſh; and this is the Right devil, and you <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker are one of his ſons begotten by him.</p>
               <p>But to make it more clear that <hi>Adam</hi> was not <hi>Cains</hi> father: He could not be <hi>Cains</hi> father, and Chriſts father alſo. Now we finde by the Scriptures that Chriſt doth own <hi>Adam</hi> to be his father, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:192297:12"/>
the Scriptures doth own <hi>Cain</hi> to be the Right Devil, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all other devils, as I have ſhewed before, and that <hi>Adam</hi> is called the <hi>Father of Chriſt,</hi> read <hi>Luke</hi> the third, to the laſt verſe in the Genealogy, <hi>Which was the ſon of Enos, which was the ſon of Seth, which was the ſon of Adam, which was the ſon of God:</hi> So that God was <hi>Adams</hi> Father as he was God, and <hi>Adam</hi> was Chriſts Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he was Man; therefore calls himſelf <hi>The Son of Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What do you Quakers think the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil was, and that Serpent that beguiled <hi>Eve?</hi> Do you look upon it to be ſome Apple-tree, and the Serpent to be an ugly Snake? and ſo this Snake crept up the Tree, and got an Apple in his mouth, and the Woman took the Apple out of the Snakes mouth, and ſo ate of it, and gave her husband to eat, and ſo brought themſelves into this miſery, and all mankinde? Do you teach your Hearers this? What is it you teach, that your Hearers are ſo ignorant of the knowledge of the true God, and the right Devil, and of the Scriptures? This is the Faith that other religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men do believe concerning the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, and of the Serpent: but you Quakers carries it in an Allegory, ſo that nothing can be made of it, neither one way nor other. But all Profeſſors of the Scriptures do own that the Tree of Life was Chriſt, and I ſuppoſe you Quakers do ſo too.</p>
               <p>If you grant that the Tree of Life was Chriſt, then this Tree of Life could ſpeak: Now if the Tree of Life did ſpeak, why ſhould not the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil ſpeak alſo? If Chriſt the Tree of Life, becauſe he gave life to every thing in Creation, ſo why pray not the Angel be called A Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and evil? or a Serpent which brought death and miſery upon the whole Creation?</p>
               <p>And we read that the Serpent ſpake wiſe words, who ſaid to the woman, <hi>They ſhould become as Gods knowing good and evil:</hi> did ever any Snake we call Serpents, ſpeak ſuch a language? Surely no. I marvel people are ſo unwilling to believe that the Tree of Knowledge of good and evil ſhould be an Angel, and yet ſpeak ſuch God-like wiſdom, and hath brought ſuch woful miſery upon all the earth! and very many men and women do eat of the ſame forbidden fruit now, as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> did then.</p>
               <p>And as the Tree was pleaſant to the eye, and good to make one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192297:13"/>
wiſe, is it not ſo now with luſtful men and women? doth not their fancy to one another ſeem pleaſant to the eye? and acting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath been pleaſant to the taſte: this makes many to know good and evil by woful experience, for this ſweetneſs of ſin is but for a ſeaſon; for I have known many in my days that have eaten of the forbidden fruit, men and women both, that have waſted their eſtates, which was good and comfortable to them; but now the want is evil to them: they have ſpoiled their bodies with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of luſt, they have made their good healthful bodies rotten with the Pox, ſo that their good healthful bodies are become evil and loathſom to their friends; and that which is worſt of all, the eating of this forbidden fruit, they have loſt the peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which was very good, and in ſtead thereof they have had an evil Conſcience, as King <hi>Saul, Cain,</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had, alwayes tormenting of them with fear, horror, and the torments of hell, and thus men and women have known good and evil, by eating of the forbidden fruit of luſt.</p>
               <p>This many Ranters were guilty of to my knowledge, neither is your Quakers people free; for I know of thoſe that have fallen to the Quakers, thinking to finde eaſe there, but they will finde the Quakers Principle but a broken Reed. Theſe things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Tree of Life, and Tree of Knowledge of good and evil, are opened more at large in <hi>The Interpretation of the Eleventh of the Revelation,</hi> ſo I ſhall conclude this point.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I am to make good by Scripture that the Soul of man is mortal. This is one of the eaſieſt points that is to prove by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and experience. Theſe are the words that <hi>George Fox</hi> doth ground the Immortality of the Soul upon, as followeth. Saith he, <hi>For God breathed into man the breath of life, through which he became a living Soul.</hi> And then <hi>George Fox</hi> asketh, <hi>Is this breath of life by which man became a living Soul, mortal?</hi> And ſaith, <hi>Is this thy knowledge?</hi> as if it were impoſſible for me to anſwer, or to make good by Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis point hath been proved by Scripture in all our other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings as aforeſaid, and that Book of the <hi>Mortality of the Soul,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:192297:13"/>
the chief ſubject it treats upon is to prove the Soul mortal; but all theſe things will do <hi>Fox</hi> no good, nor convince him of his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in this point. <hi>Fox</hi> had hard luck that he could ſee none of theſe Writings, for nothing might have better informed him in theſe things, but the Book of <hi>The Quakers Neck broken</hi> onely, that makes <hi>Fox</hi> ſo ignorant of all things, for that Book doth but name the Heads of theſe things, but in the other Writings aforeſaid they are more largely expounded. But to give a little further anſwer to this point here.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall prove that breath of Life God breathed into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to be mortal, and doth die. Let the Reader minde. I do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that Breath of Life God breathed into <hi>Adam</hi> which made him become a living Soul, it was immortal when it came from God, but it was breathed into an earthen veſſel; <hi>Adam</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the earth, he was earthly, and ſo capable to be overcome by temptation from a heavenly body, <hi>viz.</hi> the Serpent Angel: now Chriſt being the Lord from heaven, therefore he was not capable to be overcome by the temptations of earthly bodies, <hi>viz.</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent Angel his ſeed in mortality.</p>
               <p>Minde alſo, this Breath of Life which God breathed into <hi>Adam,</hi> wherein he became a living Soul, it was immortal ſo long as he ſtood in obedience to God, and no death could have touched him: but this I muſt tell the Reader, <hi>Adam</hi> could have had no other heaven than this world, he being made of this earth, he ſhould never have gone higher to the place where God is, the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and all ſpiritual Bodies are, there <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould not have come.</p>
               <p>But this I ſay, <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have been freed from all ſickneſs, diſeaſes, and death, and ſhould have lived a Paradiſical life of peace upon this earth for ever, if he had kept that ſtate he was created in. I confeſs this was a ſtate that I was always deſirous to get into, and I did endeavor much after it, but could not attain unto it; but when the Revelation of Faith did ariſe in me, the Spirit of Faith, which I call the Spirit of Chriſt, or God, ſhewed me what the ſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> was in the ſtate of innocency, and the Paradiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal heaven here upon this earth: but when the Spirit ſhewed me the Form of God, Angels, and other Creatures in a Celeſtial ſtate in the Celeſtial Heavens in all glory, I thought then that this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:192297:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
earthly Paradiſe, though it had been for ever, very inferior and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that which I am ſure I ſhall poſſeſs.</p>
               <p>But to the matter in hand. I ſhall make it appear that <hi>Adams</hi> Soul did die, though it was the breath of God made it live, yet by diſobeying the command of God, this Life muſt die, as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. and verſe 17. <hi>For in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die:</hi> Is not this plain that <hi>Adams</hi> Soul did die, notwithſtanding the breath of Life God breathed into him? this became mortal, and did die If you <hi>Fox</hi> ſhall ſay the ſoul departed from the body, and the body died, this is the opinion of moſt people, but it is an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant dark opinion, contrary to Sence, Reaſon, or Faith; for if the Soul ſlip out of the body, or depart from it, that cannot be ſaid to die, but to part one from another for a ſeaſon; beſides the body is a dead lump fit for no uſe without a ſoul. Alſo the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The ſoul that ſins ſhall die:</hi> The Scriptures doth not ſay, the ſoul ſhall ſlip out of the body that ſins, but <hi>ſhall die:</hi> it is that which ſins that muſt die; And did you <hi>Fox</hi> ever know a body commit ſin without a ſoul? if you did not, methinks you might be convinced of your ignorance, and teach the people no more that lie.</p>
               <p>Where do you read in Scripture, that ever any bodies were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to die? We read in Scripture in many places of ſouls that ſhall die, and ſouls that ſhall be cut off from the land of the living, but never of bodies.</p>
               <p>Again, it is ſaid, <hi>that Chriſt poured out his ſoul unto death:</hi> Will you <hi>Fox</hi> be ſo wicked to ſay that Chriſt did not die? <hi>He poured out his ſoul unto death:</hi> Death took Chriſts ſoul into it ſelf, that is, death ſwallowed up his ſoul. It is not ſaid he gave his body for a Ranſom for ſin, but <hi>he gave his ſoul a Ranſom for ſin:</hi> How ſhould any man be ſaved from eternal death, if Chriſts ſoul did not die?</p>
               <p>But I know the Quakers look for no benefit from the blood of Chriſt, all their happineſs it muſt come from the Law written in their hearts, that they call <hi>the light of Chriſt in them;</hi> for they know no other Chriſt neither within them, nor without them. For this I ſay they that cannot believe that their own ſouls ſhall die, cannot believe that the ſoul of Chriſt did die, and ſo they can receive no benefit by the death of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Reader may ſee the innocence in the Quakers Writings. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>He doth believe in Chriſt that ſuffered, roſe again, and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:192297:14"/>
and yet Chriſts ſoul did not die, according to the Quakers faith: for if they do acknowledge that Chriſts ſoul did die, they muſt needs acknowledge their own ſouls muſt the alſo. And if <hi>Fox</hi> had believed the one, he would have believed the other, and never have put me to this trouble to anſwer that difficult point, as <hi>Fox</hi> thinks, to prove from Scripture that the ſoul of man is mortal; if there were no Scripture at all, experience would prove that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day we ſee it with our eyes.</p>
               <p>Alſo I would ask <hi>Fox,</hi> or any other, where the ſoul of <hi>Lazarus</hi> was thoſe four days his body was in the grave? I believe <hi>Fox</hi> will ſay it was in heaven. To this I ſay, that <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſoul was in the grave where his body was; his ſoul was dead, elſe Chriſt did not raiſe him from the dead if his ſoul were not dead. Minde, if his ſoul departed out of his body, as moſt people imagine, and went to Heaven or hell, then I ſay Chriſt would have called to Heaven for his ſoul to come down, and go into the body again: if it ſhould be ſo, then Chriſt did not raiſe the dead, but brought two friends together that were ſeparated one from the other.</p>
               <p>This is the Quakers Faith, and many others beſides, but the Faith of Gods Elect doth ſtedfaſtly believe that <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſoul was dead, and there in the grave, and that by the power of Chriſts words and groans they entred in to that dead ſoul in the grave, and made it quick and live again.</p>
               <p>Here you ſee, <hi>Fox,</hi> that the ſoul of <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt man did die; And alſo you may ſee that the ſoul of Chriſt did die, and that <hi>Lazarus</hi> his ſoul was dead, and all mens ſouls elſe ſince that are dead, becauſe they were mortal. This the Scriptures prove as much or more than any one thing whatſoever, and this is my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Scripture.</p>
               <p>And are you, <hi>George Fox,</hi> convinced yet that your ſoul muſt die? For die you muſt, even two deaths, a death mortal, and a death eternal: for you that count it a Lie to ſay the ſoul is mortal, and muſt die, you ſhall taſte of two deaths, but I ſhall taſte but of one: this I know to be true, and you ſhall finde my words to be true alſo.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Muggleton, <hi>Thou ſayeſt thou accuſeſt no man of ſin, yet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, in a few lines after, thou accuſeſt the Quakers of ſin and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192297:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu told a Lie, to ſay I accuſe the Quakers of ſin and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my a few lines after; for I do accuſe the Quakers of ſin and blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt a few lines before. I ſaid, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe no man of ſin, but becauſe you began to write againſt me back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, you began at the laſt ſide of my Book, and ſo anſwered this backward. I ſhall bear with that Lie, and look upon it as no hainous crime in you: but if you had found ſuch a miſtake in me, you would have triumphed as if it had been the greateſt ſin in me to tell ſuch a Lie: you would have thought it worſe than the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which you Quakers do commit.</p>
               <p>But who ever reads that Book may ſee that I have ſaid nothing but truth, in what I have written of the Quakers.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Page 5. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Scriptures ſpeak of the wicked one, and wicked men, but where,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth the Scriptures ſpeak of a right devil?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DOth the Scriptures ſpeak of a wrong Devil? there muſt needs be either a right devil, or a wrong devil, elſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures would never have ſpoken ſo much of a devil, if there had been no devil at all: For you <hi>Fox</hi> neither declares what the right devil is, nor what the wrong devil is; ſo that no man can tell where, nor what the devil is.</p>
               <p>It ſeems <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker thinks it a hard thing to prove by the Scriptures a right devil: Do you not read in Scripture that <hi>Cain</hi> is called a <hi>devil, who was a murderer and a liar from the beginning?</hi> and the devil was thoſe Phariſees that diſputed with Chriſt, the devil was their father, Chriſt ſaid. And was not <hi>Cain</hi> their father a right devil? Is there any ſin committed, but it is the devil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it? As <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that committeth ſin is of the devil;</hi> and if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192297:15"/>
he that commits ſin be of the devil, then his father that begat him muſt needs be a right devil. Was not <hi>Judas</hi> that betrayed his Lord, was not he a right devil? Sure if he had not been a right devil, he would never have done that wickedneſs: And you <hi>George Fox,</hi> had not you been a right devil, you would never have bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemed againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent me, as you have; but you being ignorant who was your father, even <hi>Cain,</hi> you know not what your ſelf is: and that you are the ſon of a right devil, and ſo in proceſs of time you your ſelf are become a right devil, and you ſhall be recorded ſo by the Commiſſion of the Spirit of Truth to the worlds end.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Page 7. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Quakers do not deny Chriſts fleſh and bones, who remain in the Heavens until the Reſtitution of all things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre people may ſee the confuſion of the Quakers Principles, who ſay Chriſt is in them, and yet <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith the Quakers own the fleſh of Chriſt that ſuffered.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Quakers doth not deny Chriſts fleſh and bones, who remain in the Heavens until the reſtitution of all things.</hi> But this the Reader may mind, that the Quakers do not believe that Chriſts fleſh and bone is now in the Heavens, though <hi>Fox</hi> doth not deny it, becauſe the Scriptures are ſo full to prove the ſame. For if the Quakers ſhould really believe it, their Principle of Chriſt within them would quickly fail and vaniſh: for I never knew none that would avouch that Chriſts fleſh and bone was in them, neither wil any of the Quakers avouch that they do believe Chriſt to be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon now in Heaven above the ſtars in that ſame fleſh and bone he ſuffered death in; if they ſhould do ſo, how then would all the Quakers do to get Chriſt within them? there could but one Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker get Chriſt in him at a time, and when Chriſt comes out of one, he muſt go into another.</p>
               <p>But the Quakers Chriſt is nothing elſe but an Allegory, and ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:192297:16"/>
                  <hi>Fox</hi> ſhews in his following words; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we are fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone:</hi> ſo that fleſh and bone of Chriſt that was reſerved in the Heavens, which <hi>Fox</hi> doth not deny in the words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but in the latter words, the Quakers fleſh and bones are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſts fleſh and bone; ſo that Chriſt hath no fleſh and bone of his own, but what fleſh and bone Chriſt hath of the Quakers. But I ſhall ſpeak of this more in another page; but the Reader may a little ſee <hi>Fox</hi> his Allegorical Juggle.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Page 6. <hi>Fox</hi> calls me a lying ſpirit, becauſe I curſed ſome Quakers for the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and ſaith, <hi>Chriſt ſaid, Bleſs, and curſe not, who is the Chief Judge.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Do acknowledge that Chriſt is Chief Judge both of quick and dead: but Chriſt hath choſen me to be chief Judge in his ſtead here upon earth in ſpiritual matters, and I had my Authority from Chriſt the onely God without me, and not from Chriſt within me, and by this Authority from Chriſt without me, who is now in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above the ſtars, in that ſame fleſh and bone he ſuffered death in, onely that fleſh and bone is ſpiritualized and glorified, have I power over you Quakers, and that light of Chriſt within you alſo, and look what Judgement I have given upon you Quakers and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it will ſurely come to paſs upon you; neither can you, nor your Chriſt within you, deliver you from it.</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying of Chriſt who ſaid to his diſciples, <hi>Bleſs, and curſe not,</hi> this will not deliver you Quakers at all from what I have ſaid. But for the Readers ſatisfaction I ſhall open thoſe words of Chriſt more plain hereafter.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Page 7. <hi>Fox</hi> is very angry with me, becauſe I ſay that <hi>Cain</hi> was not begotten of <hi>Adam,</hi> but was begotten by the Reprobate Angel; but I have ſufficiently opened and proved this thing by the Scripture before, ſo I ſhall ſay no more of it here.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Page 10. <hi>Fox</hi> after he hath railed at me, becauſe I ſay the Quakers Chriſt hath never a body; and <hi>Fox</hi> knowing it to be true,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192297:16"/>
thought he ſhould bring himſelf into a premunire, if he ſhould deny Chriſts body without him, the Scriptures being ſo clear for it, <hi>Fox</hi> doth confeſs Chriſt hath a body, <hi>for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that which deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, aſcended; And,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Quakers are of his body: and as the Scriptures ſaith, A body haſt thou prepared.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Fox</hi> ſhews himſelf a meer Juggler, for he confeſſes Chriſt hath a body, but never confeſſes that this body of Chriſt is at a diſtance from the Quakers, neither doth <hi>Fox</hi> acknowledge that Chriſts body is in a diſtinct place by himſelf; <hi>for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that which deſcended, aſcended: And,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Quakers are of his body, as the Scriptures ſaith, A body haſt thou prepared me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Minde: <hi>Fox</hi> doth not ſay, that which deſcended was a body, nor that which aſcended neither; for <hi>Fox</hi> his meaning is myſtical, and ſo he thinkes the Quakers are fleſh of Chriſts fleſh, and bone of Chriſts bone, of Chriſts myſtical body as they conceive; ſo <hi>Fox</hi> owns Chriſt to have a myſtical body, and ſo the Quakers comes, as they ſay, to be bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh; and ſo that body which was prepared for Chriſt, the Quakers believe their fleſh and bones is that body which the Spirit of Chriſt doth dwell in, and that is that body the Scriptures ſaith is prepared.</p>
               <p>So that the Quakers do deny that Chriſt hath a body of fleſh and bone diſtinct of his own, at a diſtance from them; for if they ſhould acknowledge, as I ſaid in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken,</hi> that Chriſt hath the ſame fleſh and bone that ſuffered, ſtill diſtinct of himſelf, though glorified fleſh and bone, yet it is a diſtinct thing of it ſelf, even the perſon of a man, and cannot, nor is not within any man whatſoever; I ſay, if the Quakers ſhould own this indeed, their Principle of Chriſt within them would vaniſh like ſmoke.</p>
               <p>For this fleſh and bone of Chriſt his own perſon, was that body prepared for the God-head life to dwell in, as the Prophet ſpeaks, and that which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>the fulneſs of the God-head dwelt bodily in Chriſt:</hi> And this fleſh and bone of Chriſt was that body prepared for the God-head to dwell in.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:192297:17"/>Now will any man be ſo ſenſleſs to think this body of Chriſt to be within a man? for he that can get Chriſts body of fleſh and bone into him, he will get the fulneſs of the God-head alſo into him; ſo that he that can do this will be a God, and not a man: ſo that I have told no lie, but truth, when I ſaid the Quakers Chriſt hath never a body, for which <hi>Fox</hi> is very angry with me, and calls me Liar.</p>
               <p>Yet let the Reader but minde <hi>Fox</hi> his words, when he doth ſeem to own a body of Chriſt, his words are ſo dubious, and ſo dark, that none but the Spirit of Truth could finde out the cheat of theſe Quakers: what could any man that hath not the true knowledge of the true God, and the right Devil, and the knowledge of the Scriptures, ſay to theſe things, this Allegorical Cheat and Deceit, it being ſo coucht under the words of the Scriptures? For this is to be minded by the Reader, that the Quakers never gives no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scriptures, neither in writings nor ſpeakings. This <hi>Fox</hi> hath ſpoken of ſeveral places of Scripture to prove me a Liar, but hath given the Interpretation of none.</p>
               <p>Onely he hath named the words, and rayled againſt me, and ſo he hath left the Scriptures, and the Apoſtles words, and me to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to diſpute out the Quakers Principle of Chriſt within them. And becauſe <hi>Fox</hi> hath not opened thoſe Scriptures he quotes to prove Chriſt within, and that the Quakers are of Chriſts body, I ſhall unfold thoſe places of Scriptures which the Quakers ground upon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. It is thus written, <hi>To whom God would make known what is the riches of the glory of this myſtery among the Gentiles, which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory.</hi> This is one of the Quakers chief Scriptures to prove Chriſt within them. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. &amp; 10. <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin.</hi> So 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Examine your ſelves whether you be in the faith, approve your ſelves how that Chriſt is in you except ye be reprobates.</hi> So <hi>Galatians</hi> 2. &amp; 20. <hi>I live, yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me and gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the chiefeſt places of Scripture the Quakers have to prove that Chriſt is in them. Let the Reader minde the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as followeth, and you may ſee that the Quakers are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192297:17"/>
both in the thing it ſelf, and in the perſon and perſons to whom theſe words were ſpoken. Firſt, the perſon that ſpake theſe words, it was <hi>Paul</hi> who had a Commiſſion to preach Chriſt unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and this Commiſſion to preach Chriſt was from Chriſt without him, as I ſhewed before: and the perſons he directs theſe ſpeeches or words unto, they were to ſuch men and women that did ſeem to receive <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine, and doubtleſs many of them did truely believe that Chriſt which ſuffered, riſe again, and was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up to Heaven, according to the preaching of <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, was the Chriſt the Savior of the world; and that this Chriſt was without them in his perſon, though by faith Chriſt may be ſaid to dwell, or be in a man.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Paul</hi> and theſe Believers he preached unto, did believe the blood of Chriſt which was poured out unto death, that the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of this would purge their conſciences from dead works, to ſerve the living God; for <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth as much in the ſame verſe: <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himſelf for me.</hi> So that it may be clear to thoſe that have any true faith in them, that <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Believers had Chriſt in them no otherwiſe than by faith in the Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and Aſcenſion of that Chriſt without them, and ſo Chriſt dwells in true Believers hearts by faith, according to that ſaying, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.20. <hi>that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith;</hi> And ſo when men have true faith in Chriſts Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion without them, they may be ſaid to have Chriſt in them the hope of glory; for the faith of Chriſt, or faith in Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, gives hope to the minde that they ſhall behold that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſt without them is in; and ſo by faith a man comes to know that he is no reprobate.</p>
               <p>For a man that hath true faith in Chriſt without him, may be ſaid to know that Chriſt is in him, and that he is no reprobate: And this is that great Myſtery, Chriſt in you the hope of glory; for it is a great Myſtery to underſtand God manifeſt in fleſh, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very man in one ſingle perſon, even the Man Chriſt Jeſus, and he to die, riſe again, and aſcend from whence he came; this is a great Myſtery indeed, and few can comprehend it, but Faith doth ſee it, and underſtand it, and where ever it is truly believed, that man may be ſaid to have Chriſt in him the hope of glory, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192297:18"/>
to know that he is no reprobate, becauſe the Seed of Faith, which is Chriſts Seed, is in him, and that Seed acts it ſelf forth to lay hold of that perſon of Chriſt without him, and ſo gives aſſurance of everlaſting life in a man, and ſo Chriſt may be ſaid to be in a man.</p>
               <p>For the Seed is counted ſometimes for the thing it ſelf, ſo that if a man doth not really know in himſelf that he hath the Seed of Chriſt in him, and that is known by actual believing him that is ſent, that man is a reprobate to himſelf, and hath not the hope of glory in him, and ſo Chriſt is not in his heart by faith. This is the true Interpretation of thoſe Scriptures, and of the Apoſtles minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p n="2">2. I Shall open the Quakers Cheat concerning their bodies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fleſh of Chriſts fleſh, and bone of his bone, and thoſe Scriptures interpreted they ground that Conceit upon. Firſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. and 5. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>So we being many, are one body in Chriſt.</hi> So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>For as the body is one, and hath many members of that one body, ſo alſo is Chriſt.</hi> So <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. <hi>For we are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bone.</hi> So <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>And you that were ſometimes alienated and enemies in your minde by wicked works, yet now hath he reconciled in the body of his fleſh, through death.</hi> Theſe be the chief places of Scriptures the Quakers do prove themſelves to be fleſh of Chriſts fleſh, and bone of his bone: and for want of explaining theſe words, making no diſtinction, they cheat many ignorant people of the peace of their minds, and of the knowledge of the true body of Chriſt without them.</p>
               <p>Let the Reader but minde the words of <hi>Paul</hi> before, and they may eaſily ſee that <hi>Pauls</hi> minde was quite contrary to the Quakers; for the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Believers being Chriſts body, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts body, no otherwiſe than he did of Chriſts being within the Saints, as I ſaid before, that is, by the union the Saints have with Chriſt by faith in the true Preachers of the Goſpel, they come to be members of Chriſts body, and ſo called the body of Chriſt the Head, as you may ſee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. and <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. and <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. Theſe places all prove that the Saints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:192297:18"/>
true Believers are counted the members and body of Chriſt, in reſpect of that union they have with Chriſt by faith in his Death, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, knowing that Chriſts body lives for ever, and that his blood hath redeemed their ſouls from eternal death, and knowing he is aſcended to poſſeſs a perſonal glory, and to prepare Manſions of perſonal glory for his Saints, and thoſe that are truely united to him by faith, may be ſaid by <hi>Paul</hi> to be members of Chriſts body, and to be Chriſts body: but this body is but by the union of faith in Chriſt, and by the way of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; for this body hath never a head, but the whole Body and Perſon of Chriſt without the Saints, is the Head of this Body; ſo that if Chriſt had never a body of his own, but the Saints bodies, as the Quakers do vainly imagine, he would be but a ſad Chriſt. And becauſe you may ſee that the Apoſtle did mean no otherwiſe than I have ſaid; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.4, 5. <hi>as we have many members in one body, and all members have not the ſame office; ſo,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we being many, are one body in Chriſt, and every one members one of another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that all true Believers, though ſome be Prophets, Apoſtles, or any other gifts of the Spirit that any man hath, it is given for the good of others, who are members of the ſame faith with him, and ſo all that are partakers of the ſame faith with him, if they be ever ſo many, they all make up but one body of Chriſt, even as all the members of a mans body makes up but one body.</p>
               <p>But all this while theſe members that makes up one body, what will this body ſignifie without a head? Now thoſe natural mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that makes up a natural body, what will this body ſignifie if it hath never a head? So it is with true Believers, if there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Head of this Body of Faith without men, even Chriſt Jeſus, where then ſhould the motions and acts of Faith in a man repair to have union and communion with their Head Chriſt Jeſus? Muſt they go into themſelves to finde Chriſt their Head there? Surely no: but the motions and acts of Faith that doth ariſe from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Seed of Faith, which is the Seed of Chriſt in every true Believer, whereby he comes to have union with Chriſt their Head, and ſo he is made a member of Chriſt; and ſo all the Believers that have been from the beginning, and ſhall truly believe, to the latter end of the world, they make up but one body of Chriſt, and this body is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192297:19"/>
                  <hi>Chriſts Body,</hi> but by vertue of union of Faith, and not by Chriſts being eſſentially in men, as the Quakers do vainly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. The Apoſtle ſufficiently clears this thing in thoſe places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, ſo that I need ſpeak no more of it here.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall give the Reader to underſtand the difference between that body, that is called a body by union, and that body that is ſo in it ſelf. As for example: A woman is ſaid to be fleſh of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands fleſh, and bone of his bone, as <hi>Adam</hi> ſaid concerning <hi>Eve</hi> his wife; So <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.31. <hi>For this cauſe ſhall a man leave his father and mother, and ſhall be joyned to his wife, and they two ſhall be one fleſh.</hi> Here the Reader may ſee that a man and his wife are made one fleſh, by vertue of union and inſtitution: now they are not really one fleſh, but they are made one fleſh by union and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as aforeſaid; for when a man lieth with a harlot, he makes himſelf a member of a harlot, by that union, and ſo the harlot is made one fleſh with this man. Now this man is none of her fleſh, nor ſhe his not really ſo; for ſome men do abhor it ſhould be ſo, yet by union with a harlot many times men come to be fleſh of her fleſh, and ſo are become diſeaſed with her diſeaſe, even with the Pox, ſo that theſe are become double fleſh of one anothers fleſh by that union they had with each other; theſe things I have known by Ranters and others.</p>
               <p>Now minde the diſtinction: a childe that a man begets of his wife, is more fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, than his wife is: why? becauſe the childe is indeed fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, becauſe children came out of the mans loyns, as the twelve Patriarchs came forth of <hi>Jacobs</hi> loyns: now theſe were really fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone naturally ſo, and not by union, as a man and his wife that were two, are by union made one fleſh.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe the Scriptures ſpeaks of two ſorts of bodies, as that in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44. <hi>there is a natural body, and a ſpiritual body;</hi> a cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial body, and a terreſtrial body: now theſe bodies cannot go one into another, but mortal bodies may be made ſpiritual bodies, and ſpiritual bodies may be made mortal bodies by the power of the Creator, as it were by the Serpent Angel, he was a ſpiritual body when he deceived <hi>Eve,</hi> but when he was made mortal, he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Curſed Cain:</hi> So the Lord from heaven was a ſpiritual body
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192297:19"/>
before he over-ſhadowed the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but afterwards this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit al body was a pure mortal body, and that mortal body was caned <hi>A Bleſſed Jeſus.</hi> This is the great Myſtery to the world! and this Jeſus is that God that prepared a pure mortal body for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he might be capable to be put to death in this body, to redeem the loſt Seed of <hi>Adam:</hi> And this is that body I ſay is not in the Quakers, neither are the Quakers of Chriſts body by union, nor fleſh of his fleſh, nor bone of his bone not by union, and thoſe Believers were the Apoſtle writ unto; for the Apoſtle was choſen of Chriſt without him, and had a Commiſſion to preach Chriſt to others, and thoſe that did believe his Commiſſion were one in faith with him, and ſo they by faith might know that Chriſt was in them, except they were reprobates; that is, except they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing: for if they had faith in the true Chriſt which he had taught them, then Chriſt did dwell in their hearts by faith, and they ſhould know by faith in themſelves that they were not repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates; and by the union they ſhould have with Chriſt by faith, they ſhould become members of Chriſt, yea, they ſhould be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone; This is the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>But the Speakers of the Quakers have no Commiſſion from Chriſt to preach, as the Apoſtles had, neither have the Believers of the Quakers any true faith in Chriſts perſon, or body, without them, and ſo the Speakers and Hearers are both in the ſtate of reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither doth Chriſt dwell in their hearts by faith; for true faith they have none, but the faith of devils: And that which they call the <hi>Light of Chriſt in them,</hi> is nothing elſe but the Light of the Law written in their hearts, for true faith in Chriſts perſon they have none; ſo they call the Light of the Law in them, the Light of Chriſt, becauſe the Law convinces them of ſin.</p>
               <p>Now this Law written in the Quakers hearts, is the light of Chriſts Creation, and this light of the Law that Chriſt hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart of man, it is written in the heart of every devil, and ſo in the heart of the Speakers of the Quakers, and they teach their diſciples to harken to the light within them, and ſaith Chriſt is in them; but this is no ſaving light, neither is Chriſt within them, neither are the Quakers members of Chriſts body, nor bone of his bone, nor fleſh of his fleſh; for they have no faith in his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:192297:20"/>
perſon without them, ſo that <hi>Fox</hi> his Cheat and Deceit is made manifeſt by the Scriptures being interpreted.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Page 11. <hi>Fox</hi> is very angry with me for ſaying, Reaſon is the Devil, <hi>and yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou giveſt a reaſon for what thou doeſt:</hi> and becauſe I give a reaſon of my doings, <hi>therefore,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I am judged out of my own mouth to be the Devil, Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker hath ſhewed himſelf an ignorant devil, that cannot give a reaſon of the hope that is in him, but for fear he ſhould be counted a devil, takes up other mens words, and the Scriptures muſt give a reaſon for <hi>Fox,</hi> how that he is no reprobate, becauſe the Scriptures ſaith to Believers in that time, <hi>Know ye not that Chriſt is in you, except ye be reprobates? And be ready to render a reaſon of the hope within you:</hi> But <hi>Fox</hi> himſelf hath no knowledge but that he is a reprobate, but I perfectly know that <hi>Fox</hi> is a reprobate, and I can give a reaſon why he ſhould, and will be damned to eternity, though <hi>Fox</hi> can give no reaſon for it. What would <hi>Fox</hi> have done if he had not had other mens words to prove Chriſt within, and to give a reaſon of the hope they had in Chriſt? for <hi>Fox</hi> hath no intereſt in the Scriptures. But I ſhall open this point ſomething more hereafter, where he ſpeaketh of Reaſon, in the 19th page of his Pamphlet.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Page 11. <hi>And</hi> Muggleton <hi>ſaith, he rejoyceth in his Curſings, and them that he doth Curſe and Sentence, ſhall never ſee any other God, or Judge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, how now</hi> Muggleton, <hi>art thou become God, and Judge? Muſt not all appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, to have their ſentence and reward from him, whether they have done good or evil?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DO you <hi>Fox,</hi> and the Speakers of the Quakers, indeed believe that you ſhall appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:192297:20"/>
to receive the reward of deeds done in your bodies, whether good or evil? If you do, I ſhall ſay this unto you, that when you do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf ſhall be there alſo, and look what Sentence and Judgement we have given upon you and others here upon earth, the ſame Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence will Chriſt give when you appear before his Judgement-ſeat; and look what blaſphemy againſt the Holy Spirit you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this natural body you now have, you ſhall have the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of that blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt that ſent us, puniſhed in that ſpiritual dark body you ſhall have, when Chriſt doth raiſe you again, and then you ſhall know that you did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, when you appeared to reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt in us the Witneſſes of the Spirit; and look what Judgement and Sentence we the Witneſſes of the Spirit have given you here in this world, the ſame Judgement and Sentence ſhall be upon you in the world to come, even to eternity. And when you <hi>Fox</hi> appeared before us, to reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt in us, then did you appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, and look what Judgement I have given you and others, it may be ſaid to be the Judgement and Sentence of Chriſt, and that you appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>As it is in all Courts of natural Juſtice, when men are condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Judge for the breach of the Law, doth not ſuch an one appear before the Judgment-ſeat of the King? What are all Courts of Juſtice, but the Judgment-ſeat of the King? and whoſoever is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified or condemned by the Judges of theſe Courts, they may be ſaid to be juſtified, or acquitted; or judged, or condemned before the Judgement-ſeat of the King.</p>
               <p>In like manner it is with the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, Chriſt is the chief Judge and King of Heaven and Earth, yet he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven power to his Prophets, Apoſtles, and Witneſſes of the Spirit, to be Embaſſadors and Judges in his ſtead, as it is with Earthly Kings, ſo that who ever appears before the true Embaſſadors of Chriſt, they do appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, and look what Judgement the Embaſſadors, who are Judges, do give upon a man; if juſtified, then Chriſt juſtifies; if condemned, then condemned, and there is no appealing to any other; So that you <hi>Fox,</hi> you have appeared before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192297:21"/>
and have received your Judgement and Sentence already, but the execution of it is not yet come: and when you appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt as you mean, and I ſhall be there alſo, and look what Sentence I have paſſed upon you and others here, the ſame ſhall I paſs upon you. When Chriſt which is my Life, doth appear, then ſhall I appear with him in glory, and ſhall ſit upon a Throne of glory, and ſhall judge you wicked deſpiſers of a perſonal God, with the ſame Sentence of eternal Damnation, as I did when I was here in mortality; and then ſhall you <hi>Fox</hi> know to your endleſs miſery, that God gave power to a mortal man like your ſelf, to give Judgement and Sentence of eternal Damnation upon you, though you deſpiſe and ſcorn that a mortal man ſhould give Sentence upon you Speakers of the Quakers and others, but you ſhall finde the Sentence of a mortal man as really true upon you, as if the Immortal God himſelf had paſſed it upon you. But the Reader may finde this more largely opened in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to make it appear more plain to the Reader, that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſeat of Chriſt is in this world, as well as hereafter, and that all Prophets, Apoſtles, and true Meſſengers and Miniſters of Chriſt, if they be choſen by him, they are Judges; and thoſe that do appear before them, or any of them, they may be ſaid to appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, and look what Judgement Chriſts Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which he hath choſen and given them a Commiſſion, doth give Sentence either of Juſtification or Condemnation, they received this Sentence before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, becauſe theſe Judges are choſen by him, as it is with other Judges in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>This I ſhall make more appear by Scripture, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.29. where Chriſt ſaith to his twelve Apoſtles, <hi>You,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> Now let the Reader minde: Theſe twelve Apoſtles had the Keyes of Heaven and Hell given them here, and they had power to remit ſins, and to retain mens ſins, that is, they had power to forgive ſins, and power to retain ſins; that is, they had power to juſtifie that man or woman that believed their doctrine, and they had power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe that deſpiſed, and did not believe their doctrine: now theſe people ſo juſtified and condemned by theſe Apoſtles and true
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192297:21"/>
Preachers, they did appear before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, for they were appointed Judges in his ſtead; and that the Reader may underſtand how theſe Apoſtles ſhould judge the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> I declare unto you thus.</p>
               <p>That theſe Twelve had their Commiſſion from Chriſt to preach the Goſpel of Chriſt, unto the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> though ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gentiles believed alſo, yet <hi>Paul</hi> was chiefly ſent unto the Gentiles, and choſen of Chriſt to preach him unto the Gentiles; but the other twelve Apoſtles their Meſſage was chiefly to preach Chriſt unto the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which were the Jewes in their time, and as many of thoſe Jewes as did believe in theſe twelve Apoſtles Doctrine, concerning Chriſts Death, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Aſcenſion, and other things belonging thereunto, which they preached, I ſay the Apoſtles had power to give Sentence of Bleſſedneſs upon thoſe which did truly believe their Doctrine, and that their ſins were forgiven them, and ſo they came to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in their own conſciences, juſtified before God, and ſo had peace with God.</p>
               <p>So on the contrary, thoſe that did not believe the Apoſtles Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, but rather deſpiſed it, ſpoke evil of it, and perſecuted it, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it Blaſphemy, Hereſie, Deceit, and Lies, which many of thoſe Jews did, the Apoſtles had power to pronounce and condemn thoſe unbelieving Jewes who deſpiſed and ſpake evil of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt: Alſo they had power to retain their ſins, ſo that God ſhould never forgive them, ſo that they ſhould never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given in the conſcience, nor forgiven of God: So that theſe twelve Apoſtles doth judge the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> here in this world; ſome they have judged eternally happy, becauſe they believed their report; others they judged eternally damned for their unbelief and deſpiſings, as aforeſaid; ſo that the Apoſtles did judge the Twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their time, as aforeſaid; and this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theirs is the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, and theſe twelve Tribes were before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt ſo long as the Apoſtles Commiſſion laſted, which was a matter of three hundred and fifty years after Chriſts death; So that theſe twelve Apoſtles may be ſaid to judge the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> here in this life, by their Doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Alſo it may be ſaid that the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did appear
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192297:22"/>
before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, for many of them were ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith in Chriſt, and many were condemned by unbelief in Chriſt, ſo that every one had the Sentence in themſelves by the Apoſtles judging, whether happy or unhappy; and for this faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervice the twelve Apoſtles have done in this life, in judging according to their Commiſſion, they ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones of Glory in the Reſurrection, and ſhall give the ſame Judgement upon the twelve Tribes there, as they did here: that is, they will juſtifie the ſame Sentence of Salvation and Damnation upon the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as they gave here in mortality; they will juſtifie the ſame before Chriſt their King, when they do ſit upon twelve Thrones of immortal Glory, and many that believed them here, ſhall ſee them in that glory; and many that were condemned here, ſhall ſee in their own conſciences that their Sentence was true, even as the Rich man did that was in hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <p>SO likewiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets were Judges, and did judge thoſe that believed their Report, to be happy; and thoſe which did not, unhappy; as you may ſee <hi>John</hi> 5.25. In that Chapter the Jews do upbraid Chriſt, as if he did accuſe the Jews worthy of condemnation, for not believing in him; <hi>But,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>do not you think that I will accuſe you to the Father, there is one,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that accuſeth you, even</hi> Moſes <hi>in whom you truſt; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>had you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> Moſes, <hi>you would have believed me, for he wrote of me.</hi> The meaning is this, That ſeeing their Fathers did not believe <hi>Moſes,</hi> neither obeyed they him, but murmured againſt him, and tempted God at the Waters of <hi>Meribah,</hi> and at ſeveral other times, whereby their carcaſes fell in the wilderneſs, by their provoking the Lord to anger, in murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> and theſe Jews in Chriſts time being the children of thoſe that tempted God, when they tempted <hi>Moſes,</hi> they being devils that tempted <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet he being dead, theſe their children put their truſt in his Writings, and condemns their own Fathers, ſaying, <hi>Had we lived and ſeen thoſe things, and great wonders our Fathers ſaw</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets did, we would never have murmured againſt</hi> Moſes, <hi>nor have perſecuted the Prophets, as our Fathers did:</hi> But when the greateſt wonder of all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192297:22"/>
that ever God did for the ſatisfaction of mans minde, was done upon earth, that is, God manifeſt in fleſh; the God and Savior of the world become very man, ſo that men might talk with God in fleſh, as a man talketh with his friend.</p>
               <p>Even that Prophet that ſhould be raiſed up like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom <hi>Moſes</hi> adviſed the Generations to come to hear him, and all the Prophets foretold of him, yet when he was come, theſe Jews did not believe him no more than their Fathers did believe <hi>Moſes,</hi> but they tempted him as their Fathers tempted <hi>Moſes:</hi> Neither did Chriſt accuſe, nor judge theſe Jews, nor their Fathers for unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, but leaves them to <hi>Moſes</hi> in whom they truſted; ſo that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets ſhall be the Judges of all thoſe that put their truſt in their Writings; and who ever did, or doth truely believe their Writings concerning Chriſt to come, or truely believe when he was come, they are all juſtified, and ſhall be ſaved by the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets.</p>
               <p>So on the contrary, all thoſe Jews that read <hi>Moſes</hi> Writings, and the Prophets, and profeſſed obedience unto them, yet did not truely believe them, but rather deſpiſed and perſecuted thoſe that foretold of a Chriſt the Savior; and the children of thoſe Jews perſecuted the Savior himſelf: theſe, I ſay, are all to be accuſed and judged by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, for they made a profeſſion of their Writings, but underſtood, nor believed nothing of them; ſo theſe Jews have appeared before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt, and they will have no other Accuſer or Judge but <hi>Moſes,</hi> in whoſe Letter men put their truſt: So that <hi>Moſes</hi> will be always ſpeaking in the conſcience, as the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> did in <hi>Cains</hi> conſcience, fear and horror: And this is the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt that theſe men aforeſaid ſhall, and hath appeared before; for <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets were Judges in Chriſts ſtead.</p>
               <p>So that all Commiſſionated men whom God hath choſen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the Myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven to mankinde, they are all Judges, and are in Chriſts ſtead, and what Judgement they give in ſpiritual matters, Chriſt doth own as his own Judgement; ſo that who ever is judged by any of theſe Judges, they may be ſaid to be judged, whether it be the Sentence of Juſtification, or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Condemnation, to eternity; and that they received this Sentence before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:192297:23"/>Alſo theſe Judges ſhall all ſit upon Thrones of Immortal Glory, in the Celeſtial Heavens, being faithful here upon earth, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was in his houſe, that was in his Commiſſion of the Law, and the Apoſtles in the Goſpel, and we the Witneſſes of the Spirit, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the tenor of our Commiſſion have been faithful alſo; ſo that <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, and Apoſtles, and we the Witneſſes of the Spirit, ſhall ſit upon Thrones of Glory as Judges in the preſence of Chriſt, our God, our King, and our Redeemer in the higheſt Heavens. So much concerning the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The ſame page <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, Becauſe he hath paſſed Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence upon the Quakers, they ſhall never grow to have more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience in Viſions, and Revelations, but ſhall wither.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, are more of</hi> Muggleton's <hi>Lies, for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the truth ſpreads, yea and will ſpread over the whole world more and more.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Do know and affirm, that thoſe Speakers of the Quakers, and others whom I have paſſed the Sentence of eternal Damnation upon, that they have not, nor do grow in any Experience nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation ſince the Sentence of damnation was paſſed on them, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doth plainly manifeſt, and many will witneſs unto it. And as for <hi>Fox</hi> himſelf, what Experience and new Revelation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have you had ſince you were damned a matter of fourteen years ago? Have you publiſhed any other things but what you did at the firſt? no not ſo much as you did at the firſt; for then it was your Principle of Zeal to fall into Witchcraft-fits, ſuppoſing it was the Spirit of Chriſt that moved you to foam at the mouth, and ſigh, and groan, and ſwell with ſpiritual Witchcraft, and howl and groan as if hell were like to burſt in you; and perhaps a while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your ſpirit would break forth into a many non-ſenſical words, as if the devil had broke forth out of hell: was not this your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice? and were not theſe the moſt eminent Quakers counted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, who had thoſe Witchcraft-fits? for the Quakers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation doth ariſe in them onely when the Witchcraft-fit is upon them; nay, I have known ſome that have followed the Quakers,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:192297:23"/>
deſiring to be of them, and earneſtly deſiring in their Meetings to have thoſe Fits as other Quakers had; for they thought ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who had thoſe Witchcraft-fits to be much in the favor of God, and that thoſe Fits had been wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt, and that he had revealed great things unto them; and becauſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties aforeſaid could not produce thoſe Fits in themſelves, as they ſaw others have, notwithſtanding their melancholy life, their fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their outward aparrel, and obſerving every motion in the minde, according to the Quakers doctrine, they left no ſtone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned, nor no endeavor neglected in the Quakers way, that they might attain thoſe Witchcraft-fits, but could not attain them do what they could: They got the Quakers language of <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou,</hi> but could not attain the Fits; neither would ſome of thoſe Quakers own one of theſe perſons becauſe ſhe had not ſuch Fits as they had, ſo ſhe was forc'd to leave them. And the cauſe why theſe perſons aforeſaid could have no ſuch Fits, it was becauſe they had talked with me before they fell to the Quakers Principles, ſo that no Witchcraft-Fit could be produced in them, though their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors were great.</p>
               <p>Alſo I have drove the Witchcraft-power out of Quakers that have been ſtrongly poſſeſt, ſo that they have never had Fit more. And as for you, <hi>Fox,</hi> have you ever had any Witchcraft-fit ſince you were damned? did you ever fall into a ſwoon, and lye as one dumb? and hath the ſpirit of Reaſon the devil, which you call the Light of Chriſt in you? I ask, hath he revealed any myſteries of the Scriptures in the time of your Fit, ſince you were damned fourteen years ago? Is your revelation of Reaſon to be ſeen in writing, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>Again, hath <hi>Samuel Hooton, William Smith, Edward Bourn, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Farnſworth,</hi> and many others that were damned of late years, have they had any Witchcraft-fits ſince? or any new revelation? if they have, let them be brought forth to the light. Do you <hi>George Fox</hi> know any Quaker that I have paſſed the Sentence upon, that can produce a Witchcraft-fit afterwards? If no Fit can be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as formerly, then I ſay no true revelation nor experience can ariſe in the Quake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s hearts: Nay, this Sentence it puts a ſtop to the revelation of Reaſon alſo, elſe why ſhould Quakers fall ſo, as you do, from your firſt Principle? for you are not like the people
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192297:24"/>
you were ſixteen years ago, there were few Quakers then but they had Witchcraft-fits, but now of late I do not hear of any Quaker that hath any Fits, no not ſo much as to buzz or hum before the Fit comes. But if you <hi>Fox</hi> doth know any of you Quakers that have any of thoſe Witchcraft-fits as formerly, bring them to me, or let me hear of it, and I ſhall caſt out that devil which cauſed thoſe Fits, ſo that they ſhall never have more, but ſhall be ſenſible and in their right mind. So <hi>Fox,</hi> you ſhall finde my words to be truth, and no lie, that the Quakers after the Sentence is paſt upon them, ſhall never grow to have more experience in Viſions and Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but ſhall wither. Do not you, <hi>Fox,</hi> finde this to be true? if you do not, others will witneſs unto it to be truth.</p>
               <p>But you ſay, <hi>The truth ſpreads:</hi> I know the truth ſpreads, but not the Quakers Witchcraft-fits which produced Viſions, Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Revelations which the Quakers thought had been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by the Spirit of Chriſt, but they were produced by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Reaſon the Devil, in themſelves; and theſe Fits, Viſions, Apparitions, and Revelations in the Quakers are greatly withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red away of late by that Sentence I have paſſed upon the Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Quakers, and others of that opinion, ſo that thoſe Fits of theirs makes moſt people aſhamed to own them, which formerly people thought them the moſt knowingſt that was poſſeſt with a Witchcraft-fit; ſo that it is plain and clear, and many that were lovers of the Quakers way of Worſhip that can, and will witneſs that their experience in Viſions and Revelation are withered, and come to nothing.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Fox</hi> thinks becauſe a many ignorant people comes to hear the Quakers ſpeak their ninny-nonies over and over again, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Truth,</hi> as he calls it, <hi>ſpreads,</hi> but when it was at the beſt, it was but a lie that ſpreads; indeed a lie will ſpread very faſt, but truth ſpreads very ſlowly; for truth was ten years in the world, and there was not much above forty perſons that owned it, but the Quakers at that time had many thouſands that were Quakers, as was expreſt by thoſe five damned Quakers in <hi>Eaſtcheap,</hi> mentioned in that Book called <hi>The Quakers Neck broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Page 14. <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, He could never finde any Quaker that would own God to be a perſon in form of a man, which ſhews the Quakers darkneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:192297:24"/>
                  <hi>Here,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox,</hi> Muggleton <hi>hath ſhewed his ignorance of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Scriptures ſaith, That God is a Spirit: And Chriſt ſaith, that a Spirit hath not fleſh and bone as I have. And,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, God fills heaven and earth; and herein,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou haſt ſhewed thy ignorance and darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO this I ſhall make it appear to the Reader, that my words are truth, and that <hi>Fox</hi> hath ſhewed his ignorance and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both of Gods filling Heaven and earth, and that <hi>Fox</hi> nor the Quakers doth not believe that Chriſt hath fleſh and bone of his own diſtinct of himſelf, and that this fleſh and bone of Chriſt is now in heaven above the ſtars.</p>
               <p>Let the Reader minde the words of Chriſt: His diſciples ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they had ſeen a Spirit, theſe diſciples were ignorant at that time as moſt people, thinking that Spirits might walk without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or that Spirits might aſſume bodies, and appear to men: this ignorant opinion was in the diſciples of Chriſt before they were endued with power from on high, and this is the general opinion of all men, but thoſe that have a Commiſſion from God; for if God had never choſen Prophets and Apoſtles, and Witneſſes, to enlighten the underſtanding of people, all people in the world would have believed ſo; therefore it was that Prophets cauſed Kings to put to death all Witches and Wizards that dealt with familiar ſpirits, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did, and King <hi>Saul,</hi> out of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth beſides did practice Witchcraft, and dealing with familiar ſpirits, and did believe that ſpirits might, and did walk without bodies, and could aſſume what ſhapes they pleaſe. The ſame opinion is now all the world over, and in the Quakers alſo; and the diſciples of Chriſt at that time had a ſmatch of the Heathen opinion in them, which made them through their ignorance to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they had ſeen a Spirit without a body to walk before them: but Chriſt willing to convince them of that vain and lying opinion ſaith to his diſciples, <hi>Feel me, and handle me, for a Spirit hath not fleſh and bone as I have;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, No Spirit can appear without a body, for a Spirit without a body is a meer ſhadow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192297:25"/>
to your fantaſie through your ignorance, as if Chriſt ſhould ſay, do not believe that Spirits can walk without bodies, there is no ſuch thing, it is but a meer ſhadow you ſuppoſe to be a Spirit, but come to me, and feel me, and handle me, for a ſhadow as you take or think to be a Spirit, hath not fleſh and bone, nor is of no ſubſtance as I am. This was after Chriſt was riſen from the dead, and before the Apoſtles had received power from on high, ſo that the Reader may ſee that Chriſt had fleſh and bone after he was riſen from the dead: now I would fain know of the Quakers what became of this fleſh and bone of Chriſt, where it went, or where it is now? Sure you Quakers will not ſay this fleſh and bone of Chriſt is within you, neither will you acknowledge that the fleſh and bone which is the body of Chriſt riſen from the dead, to be now in Heaven above the ſtars diſtinct of himſelf: for that body of Chriſt which was felt and handled by his diſciples, was that body that was prepared for the God-head Life to dwell in, and to ſuffer, and when that body of Chriſt aſcended to Heaven, the God-head Spirit aſcended with it alſo.</p>
               <p>So that there is but one God, and one body of God, ſo that Chriſt is God embodyed with fleſh and bone in all things like unto man, ſin excepted, as the Scriptures ſaith; ſo that Chriſt cannot be in the Quakers, neither in his body nor his ſpirit; neither are they members of his body not by union of faith as true Believers are; for then Chriſt hath never a body, neither within them, nor without them; for if they ſhould believe that Chriſt hath a body diſtinct of his own, at ſuch a diſtance &amp; reſidence above the ſtars, then I ſay the Quakers Principle of Chriſt within them would vaniſh like ſmoak indeed, as it doth with many true Believers that were of the Quakers faith, before they came to know the true God, and the right devil: but the Quakers are in black, pitchy darkneſs, ſo that it is a vain thing to talk to them of Heavenly Myſteries, as the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the true God, and the myſtery of the right devil, and how they became fleſh; for the Quakers have got, as they imagine, God and devil, hell and Heaven, Reſurrection, and all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, ſo they cannot tell where to finde any God without them, but an Infinite Spirit without a body; alſo their devil is a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſs ſpirit, they know not from whence he came, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192297:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <p>ALſo <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>God fills heaven and earth.</hi> Here he repeats Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture words, but never gives any Interpretation: he hath repeated many words of the Prophets, Apoſtles, and the words of Chriſt, he hath named their words to prove me a liar, but he gives no interpretation, no not one Text that he hath brought againſt me: I do think he never did interpret any Scripture words in his life. I marvel how the people called Quakers are ſatisfied with their bibble-babble, that never tells what the ſenſe of ſuch words of Scripture are as they ſo much talk of, but I cannot expect no other from Quakers, for they are all alike.</p>
               <p>So <hi>William Smith, Samuel Hooton, Richard Farnſworth,</hi> they named many places of Scriptures, which were other mens words, againſt me, as <hi>Fox</hi> doth, but never did interpret any. But <hi>Fox,</hi> do you conceive that God is ſo big a bulk, that he fills heaven and earth with his bigneſs? how comes it to paſs then that the Quakers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and others are ſo empty? for if God be ſo big to fill Heaven and Earth, me thinks the Quakers bodies are but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle veſſels in compariſon of Heaven and Earth, they are great veſſels, and doth certainly hold God, and yet many vaſt places in the earth where God is not at all, and I know many Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and others that God is not in them at all, how is it then that God fills heaven and earth? Oh this blind <hi>Fox!</hi> it is the nature of Foxes to be cunning and ſubtile, but this <hi>Fox</hi> is ignorant and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to repeat Scripture words and give no diſtinction, that is the cauſe of ſuch groſs errors concerning God and devil; for <hi>Fox</hi> takes God to be an Infinite Spirit without a body, and this Spirit without a body fills heaven and earth without diſtinction, and ſo <hi>Fox</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is a bodileſs Spirit, ſo that he can give no diſtinction what the devil is, though I know he is one himſelf: but for the Readers ſake I ſhall interpret a little how God may be ſaid to fill heaven and earth, as thus: God is a ſingle perſon in form of a man, a ſpiritual perſon, and no bigger in compaſs than a man, and he was ſo from eternity, even of the ſame ſtature as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was, therefore ſaid to be <hi>made ni the image and likeneſs of God.</hi> Alſo Chriſt is ſaid to be <hi>the expreſs image of his Fathers perſon;</hi> the meaning is this, that Chriſt was the expreſs Image of God the Father, as he was God in Immortality and Glory; and as Chriſt was in mortality and ſhame
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192297:26"/>
he was the expreſs image of his Father <hi>Adam,</hi> for the Scriptures calls <hi>Adam</hi> his Father, and <hi>David</hi> is called Chriſts Father as he was man; ſo that Chriſt being God and man, ſo that God is of no big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bulk or bigneſs, nor never was, than the compaſs of a man, and the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was of the ſame bigneſs for compaſs of perſon as God was that made him, and the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> Chriſt, which was God and man, was of the ſame compaſs when upon earth, as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in the beginning of the world was, the Scriptures are full to prove this. But it would be too tedious to ſpeak of them in this place, neither was it my intention to ſpeak of this point now, onely that the Reader may ſee the darkneſs of the Quakers, to think God ſo big a bulk to fill heaven and earth, and give no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction how.</p>
               <p>This being a ground-work to know what God is in himſelf, ſo it may eaſily be underſtood how God fills heaven and earth: he fills heaven and earth by his wiſdom and power, in that he created all things by the power of his word: alſo by the power of his word he hath planted a Law in every creature according to its kinde, he hath by the power of his word written his Law in the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and all other celeſtial creatures in heaven, and every creature in heaven in their kinde obeys his Law written in their natures by the power of his word, ſo that all the creatures in heaven obey him, and ſets forth the praiſe, wiſdom, power, and glory of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, their God, and King, ſo that heaven is filled with his glory.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe God hath written by his wiſdom and power of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Law in every creature here upon earth, he hath written by the power of his word a Law in mans heart who is the Image of himſelf, whom God made lord of all other creatures; he by the power of his word hath placed a Law in the beaſts of the fields, in the fowls of the air, in all ſenſible creatures hath he planted a Law, and they all obey him in their kinde, and ſets forth his glory.</p>
               <p>Yea, he hath by the power of his word placed a ſecret Law in the Vegetables, as Trees, Plants, Herbs, and all things of that kind, nay, by the power of his word he hath put a Law in the Sun and Moon, to run their courſe in their ſeaſon appointed.</p>
               <p>Alſo he hath placed by the power of his word a Law in the Stars, and Planets, and in all the Hoſt of Heaven on this ſide the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nay, he hath ſet the Law of bounds to the Sea, and great
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192297:26"/>
Waters; all theſe things, and a thouſand times more hath he done by his wiſdom and power, and all theſe things which he hath made by the power of his word here below upon this earth, they declare his handy-works, and doth ſhew forth the wiſdom, power, and glory of God their Creator, every thing in its kinde ſhews forth the glory of God, and ſo God hath filled the earth with his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, power, and glory, in that he hath placed a Law in every thing according to his pleaſure, to ſet forth his praiſe here on earth</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe God may be ſaid to fill the heaven and earth, and yet his perſon but the bigneſs of a man as aforeſaid; and he may be called the <hi>Great God,</hi> in reſpect of his great power, but not in reſpect of his perſon; for a King may be called a great King in reſpect of his great power; as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babylon</hi> was of great power, as in <hi>Daniel</hi> 4.20. <hi>He was as a Tree which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched up to heaven.</hi> So likewiſe his <hi>dominion is ſaid to reach to the ends of the earth,</hi> as in verſe 22. So that it was the greatneſs of his power that reached up to heaven, and to the end of the earth, that is, as far in the earth as his Power, Decrees, and Laws would reach, yet the perſon of this great King was no bigger in ſtature and compaſs than another man.</p>
               <p>So it is with God, though his power, wiſdom, and glory fills heaven and earth, in that he hath given Laws, and placed Bounds to all his Creation, as I ſaid before, yet he himſelf is no bigger in bulk, nor in compaſs than a man, as the Scriptures doth in many places prove, and as I have ſaid before; and in this ſenſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures doth mean that God fills heaven and earth.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Fox</hi> and the Quakers looks upon God to be ſo big in his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Spirit without any body, that he fills heaven and earth, the Air, and all things elſe with his great big Spirit without a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, this is the Quakers God, and Chriſt; ſo they can get God in to them, as they think, and then when they part out of the body they now have, then their ſpirits goes into God again, ſo that the Quakers God and their Spirits doth ſo whip into one another, ſo that no body can tell where to finde either of them.</p>
               <p>This is the Quakers Principle, and their imaginary God &amp; Chriſt, and this is that Spirit they call the Spirit of Chriſt in them; this is that Chriſt they are members of, and bone of this Spirits bone, and fleſh of this Spirits fleſh; for they abhor ſuch a God that is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192297:27"/>
and can be confined to one place of reſidence, but they muſt have a great infinite Spirit who fills all places, and all things, which cannot be known nor underſtood what he is, ſuch a God as this muſt the Quakers have, that their ſpirits may ſlip into him, when death doth approach; for Quakers thinks their ſouls cannot die, they look upon that to come from God, therefore immortal; ſo they think to ſlip out of thoſe bodies they have, and ſo creep into that infinite Spirit again from whence they came, as they ſuppoſe, for they are of <hi>Solomons</hi> opinion, <hi>the body to the duſt and the ſpirit returns to God that gave it;</hi> but <hi>Solomon</hi> was ignorant in this point, though he was a wiſe Man in things of nature, and you Quakers will find your thoughts and conceit in this thing fruſtrated, and that your ſouls ſhall die, neither ſhall your ſouls ſlip out of your bodies, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it go into God again, as you doe vainly imagine; but as your ſouls doth die a natural death here, even in the ſight of others, ſo many of you ſhall die an eternal death hereafter, in your own bodies; ſo that God ſhall be no hiding place for you, but he will ſay, <hi>Depart from me ye workers of iniquity;</hi> for you have been the greateſt deſpiſers and blaſphemers againſt a perſonal God, and them whom I ſent, of any.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIX.</head>
               <p>AGain it will be neceſſary to give <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker a little to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the bigneſs of the right Devil. <hi>Fox</hi> may remember that I have ſhewed before that <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt Devil in fleſh, and the right Devil, and that the ſpirit of the Devil is not body leſs, as the Quakers doth vainly imagine; and this <hi>Cain</hi> the firſt and right Devil was a Man, and of the ſame ſtature and bigneſs as the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent Angel was who beguiled <hi>Eva,</hi> who was <hi>Cains</hi> Father.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Adam</hi> was none of his Father, as I have ſaid before, but I perceive that <hi>Fox</hi> and other Quakers are unacquainted with the right Devil; ſo that they wonderfully ſtrange at my words, to call the Devil a right Devil, they never heard the Devil called a right Devil before.</p>
               <p>I have received Letters from Quakers before, deſiring to have it proved by Scripture, but I perceive the Quakers are unacquainted with the right Devil, and altogether ignorant of the wrong Devil;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192297:27"/>
for they know neither right Devil nor wrong Devil: but if <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker will but follow my advice, he ſhall ſee a right devil; let <hi>George Fox</hi> but take a <hi>Looking-glaſs</hi> and look into it, and he ſhall ſee his own face, and then he will ſee a right devil, and he need go no further to ſee the right devil, and all other Quakers that are ignorant of the right devil, let them look into a glaſs and there they may ſee themſelves to be right devils, and not wrong devils.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The ſame page <hi>Muggelton</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt hath a diſtinct body of fleſh and bone of his own.</p>
               <p>To this <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Is Chriſt diſtinct from his Saints? then how come they, ſaith Fox, to be of his fleſh and bone?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre people may ſee <hi>Fox</hi> hath manifeſted his deceit, and how he carrieth the Principle of the Quakers in an Allegory to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people; for their Chriſt they ſo much talk of, is a meer Allegory; <hi>For</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox</hi> in another place of his Pamphlet, <hi>we own the Son of God, and his fleſh, and bone, and blood, who was Crucified, and laid in the grave and roſe again, and ſits at the right hand of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>Fox</hi> ſeems to owne Chriſts Body without him, but it is in a myſtery; for he doth not believe that God hath any right hand or left hand either; for infinite ſpirits hath no hands, there is no need of ſpirits without bodies to have hands: but the Reader may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee that <hi>Fox</hi> hath a myſtical meaning, or elſe he groſſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts himſelf:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, is Chriſt diſtinct from his Saints, then how came they to be of his fleſh and bone?</hi> ſo that <hi>Fox</hi> his words here are quite contrary to his words before; ſo that it may be clear to thoſe that are not ſtark blind, that the Quakers do not believe that Chriſts fleſh and bone is now in Heaven above the Star without them; <hi>for,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, can Chriſt be diſtinct from the Saints?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that <hi>Fox</hi> looks upon the Quakers bodies to be members of Chriſts body of fleſh and bone, and ſo all the Quakers bodies which they count members, they make up but one body of Chriſt, &amp; Chriſts Spirit in them they count the head, and the Quakers fleſh and bone to be Chriſts body of fleſh and bone; ſo that Chriſt can not be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192297:28"/>
diſtinct of himſelf, nor have fleſh and bone diſtinct both in body and ſpirit.</p>
               <p>This is the Quakers imaginary Chriſt, which is the abſolute ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Anti-chriſt, and this ſpirit of Anti-chriſt it doth reign more in the Quakers people, then in any people whatſoever. Here people may ſee what the Quakers Chriſt within them is, a meer allegory, a ſpirit without a body, and their fleſh and bone of their bodies they count Chriſts body, and ſo when their ſouls ſlips out of their bodies, and goes into God, as they imagine, their bodies goes to the Earth, and ſo Chriſts body goes to the Earth, and his ſpirit that is in them, goes into Gods vaſt ſpirit that taketh all things into its ſelf; And according to Squire <hi>Pennington's</hi> ſaying unto <hi>John Reeve,</hi> but it was when he was upon the Ranting Principle, but ſince that he is turned Quaker; for the Quakers principle is but the Ranters refined into a more civil kind of life.</p>
               <p>For the Ranters were ſo groſly rude in their lives, that ſpoyled their high language, and made people weary of them; but the Quakers that were upon the Rant are the beſt able to maintain the Quakers principle of Chriſt within them, than any other Quakers that were not upon the Rant, as <hi>William Smith,</hi> and Squire <hi>Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and others as I know: ſo that people may plainly ſee that the Quakers are led and guided by the ſpirit of Antichriſt, that will not allow Chriſts body of fleſh and bone to be diſtinct from his Saints, but would have the Quakers bodies to be Chriſts fleſh and bone; This is that ſpirit of Anti-chriſt that denied Chriſt come in the fleſh, as <hi>John</hi> in his Epiſtle ſaith; for who ever denies Chriſt come in the fleſh, and that fleſh he is come in to be diſtinct of it ſelf from all other fleſh, and from all other Creatures both in Heaven and in Earth, I ſay is the ſpirit of Anti-chriſt, which I am ſure the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are, and do more than the Pope, ſo that the ſpirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt reigns in the Quakers people more than in the Pope, and his people; the Pope indeed is more ſuperſtitious than the Quakers, but the Quakers are for more Anti-chriſtian than the Pope in their doctrine.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Page 15. <hi>Muggelton</hi> ſaith, this body of Chriſt is the only God.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Fox</hi> calls darkneſs, and ſaith God is a Spirit, and God is in Chriſt, who prepared Chriſt a body: there cannot be, ſaith he, Chriſt without God; and, ſaith <hi>Fox,</hi> the Quakers do know Chriſt in the fleſh, and ſaith he feels me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:192297:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat is as true a ſaying of mine, as ever was ſpoken with tongue, that the body of Chriſt is the onely God, and they are reprobates who dares denit, yet this devil <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker calls it <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>God is a Spirit, and God is in Chriſt:</hi> what igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God doth this <hi>Fox</hi> manifeſt? if God be in Chriſt and that body of Chriſt was Gods body which was prepared for the ſpirit of God to be in, then muſt Chriſts body needs be the only God.</p>
               <p>For if God was in Chriſt, and <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith there cannot be Chriſt without God, than that body of Chriſt had the Spirit of God in that body; then I ſay Chriſts body muſt needs be the onely God, for God and Chriſt, ſaith <hi>Fox,</hi> cannot be one without the other, then I ſay where Chriſts body is, there is Gods body.</p>
               <p>For if the ſpirit of Chriſt, and the ſpirit of God be all one ſpirit, as I think no man dares denie, then I ſay, if the ſpirit of Chriſt and the ſpirit of God be all one ſpirit, then I ſay one body was prepared for this one ſpirit, even the body of Chriſt his own fleſh and bone, ſo that this body of Chriſt and the ſpirit of God is in that body, ſo that body of Chriſt being God and Man, that body may be called, and is the onely God, and who ever prayeth to any other God, he prayeth to a God of his owne imagination, as all your Quakers do; yet <hi>Fox</hi> calls this darkneſs to ſay Chriſts perſon, body, and ſpirit is the onely God; yet he ſaith God and Chriſt cannot be one with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other; but he will not acknowledge Chriſts body of fleſh and bone to be ſo honored, as to be called the body of the onely God: how confuſed is this <hi>Fox</hi> in diſtinction concerning God and Chriſt, they muſt be both one, and they muſt not be both one; one of them muſt have a body prepared, but the other muſt be a ſpirit without a body; this is the Quakers confuſed non-ſence.</p>
               <p>But I know <hi>Fox</hi> his juggle; he means, as I ſaid before, that the Quakers bodies are Chriſts body, &amp; ſo Chriſts Spirit and Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit being all one, the ſpirit of Chriſt is in the Quakers bodies, whom he calls <hi>Saints,</hi> and the Saints bodies are called by the Quakers the body of Chriſt, that is prepared for the ſpirit of Chriſt and God, which is all one, to be in.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:192297:29"/>And this is the Chriſt the Quakers own to have within them, this is the Quakers myſtery of iniquity to ſhufle off the belief of the body of Chriſt without them diſtinct from them, even at ſuch a diſtance as Heaven and Earth, for his body of fleſh and bone is in Heaven above the Stars, but the Quakers bodies are hereon Earth, and muſt rot in the Earth; but Chriſts body doth live for ever and ever: So that the Quakers bodies are neither members of Chriſts body, nor the body it ſelf, which is prepared for the ſpirit of Chriſt, the ſpirit of the onely wiſe God, to dwell in; for in Chriſts own body of fleſh and bone did the fulneſs of the God-head dwell body<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in him, that is, all the fulneſs and ſpiritual ſubſtance, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and being of the Godhead ſpirit dwelt in Chriſts body of fleſh and bone when he was upon Earth, and in no mans body elſe; and this body who had the fulneſs of the Godhead in it, I call the Godhead Spirit, and that body together the only God, and this body and ſpirit of Chriſt is both diſtinct from the Quakers bodies, and all mens bodies elſe.</p>
               <p>So that the Quakers Chriſt within them is a meer imaginary Chriſt, which the ſpirit of reaſon the devil, the Anti-chriſtian ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath produced in them, and not the true Chriſt; So that the Quakers knoweth no other Chriſt in the fleſh but that Chriſt within them, and their bodies is this imaginary Chriſts body; this is the Quakers Chriſt ſpirit and body they ſo much talk of, this I know to be true, for as I ſaid before, and in <hi>the neck of the Quakers broken,</hi> that is the Quakers ſhould own that body of Chriſt, fleſh and bone without them, at ſuch a diſtance as above the Stars, to be the onely God; then I ſay the Quakers principle of Chriſt within them would vaniſh like ſmoak.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe have I paſſed the ſentence of eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon ſo many Quakers for denying that fleſh and bone of Chriſt without them to be the onely God; for the Quakers are the greateſt fighters againſt a perſonal God without them diſtinct of himſelf, of any that profeſſe the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith he feels me: that ſaying of <hi>Fox,</hi> is true I know you do feel me, and you ſhall feel me to eternity, and ſo ſhall more of you Quakers feel that ſentence of eternal damnation that I have paſſed upon you; ſo that your Chriſt within you cannot, nor God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out you will not, deliver you from that ſentence and curſe I have
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192297:29"/>
paſſed upon you; it will, and ſhall be written and ingraven upon, and in your hearts of ſtone, even as the Law that <hi>Moſes</hi> gave was written in Tables of ſtone to ſignifie the Law written in the ſeed and nature of reaſon in the reprobate Angel before his fall, from whom all men received that ſeed of reaſon, and ſo the Law written in it.</p>
               <p>So that as you feel the motions of that Law written in your hearts, your thoughts accuſing and excuſing, ſhewing the Law written in your hearts, ſo ſhall that ſentence I have paſſed upon you be printed in your memory, always judging and accuſing of you for your blaſphemie againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and deſpiſing the meſſengers of the holy Spirit, and you ſhall remember you were told ſo by a true Prophet:</p>
               <p>So that you ſhall feel me indeed to your endleſs miſery; and if you do not find this to be true as I have ſaid, then let the ſame evil I have judged upon you, let it be upon me, or if God will not own what I have ſaid unto you deſpiſing Quakers, or if I judge thus without a commiſſion and authority from the true God, let God judge me with the ſame judgment I have judged you and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with: this is as much as can be ſaid by man.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Page 19. <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, the devil ſo much ſpoken of in Scripture, is nothing but the ſpirit of reaſon in man that killed the righteous; alſo it was the ſpirit of reaſon the devil that kil'd the Juſt.</p>
               <p>Here <hi>Fox</hi> blames my judgment, and pleads for Reaſon, as if all reaſonable men had ſaith from thoſe words of <hi>Paul,</hi> who deſired to be delivred from unreaſonable men; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, all men have not faith;</hi> ſo that <hi>Fox</hi> looks upon the devil to be nothing elſe but unreaſonableneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Fox</hi> ſhews his ignorance and darkneſs both of the devil, and of the meaning of the Scriptures, and of the Apoſtles words; the want of diſtinction, and the want of the gift of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, is the cauſe the Quakers are ſo ignorant of every true Principle of Faith. For the ſpeakers are the worſt of all men in that, for they never gives meanings of Scripture, nor interprets any.</p>
               <p>Look into all the Quakers writings, and they give no meanings,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192297:30"/>
nor interpretations of any; for no interpretation can be given but there muſt be a meaning, as there was by <hi>Philip</hi> to the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but the Quaker names the Scripture words that are for his purpoſe, &amp; though there be three places againſt that he names to prove to the contrary, the Quaker will give no meanings nor diſtinctions, but ſay, <hi>it is the fleſh that asks queſtions:</hi> and this is the cauſe the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are ſo unable to diſpute, or to anſwer queſtions, or interpret Scripture, indeed I cannot ſee how they ſhould, their foundation is ſo ſandy, one puffe of wind from a true Meſſenger or Miniſter of Chriſt will blow down all the Quakers building; For they have none of the true Corner-ſtone to build upon, nor that Rock which is Chriſt without them, but a ſandy foundation of a Chriſt within them.</p>
               <p>Yet becauſe I would not have the Reader unſatisfied that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Reaſon in man is the devil, and that it was the ſpirit of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in man that always killed the righteous, and the Spirit of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that killed the Juſt, I ſhall prove it by Scripture, and ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain thoſe words of <hi>Paul, who deſired to be delivered from unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, for all men have not faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know it is a vain thing to interpret Scriptures to Quakers, or to give meanings of Prophets, or Apoſtles to Quakers; but for the ſake of others that ſhall read this Epiſtle, I ſhall open this point, and prove by Scripture that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it was the ſpirit of Reaſon in <hi>Cain</hi> that killed righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> for <hi>Cain</hi> reaſoned in himſelf, why ſhould God accept of <hi>Abel</hi> &amp; his offering, &amp; not of him and his offering: he reaſoned in himſelf why ſhould God ſend fire from Heaven to teſtifie his acceptance of <hi>Abels</hi> offering, &amp; ſend no fire from Heaven to conſume his offering: Alſo <hi>Cain</hi> reaſoned in himſelf, I am the firſt-born, and lo God hath had reſpect unto the younger, what reaſon is there that God ſhould reſpect the younger and reject the elder? Likewiſe <hi>Cain</hi> reaſoned in himſelf, that he would kill <hi>Abel,</hi> then thought he, God will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of me, there being none to offer up ſacrifice unto him, but himſelf; ſo theſe reaſonings and ſuch like paſſed through <hi>Cains</hi> ſoul before he was reſolved to kill righteous <hi>Abel;</hi> but this reaſoning being too ſtrong for <hi>Cain,</hi> it made him reſolve to kill his brother when he had an opportunity, which a while after he had an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, when he met <hi>Abel</hi> in the field, he talked with him and ſlew him. And this ſpirit of reaſon in <hi>Cain</hi> was the firſt devil in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192297:30"/>
man that killed righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> and this was the ſpirit of reaſon in <hi>Cain,</hi> and not any unreaſonableneſs in him.</p>
               <p>For he thought he had reaſon to kill <hi>Abel,</hi> ſeeing God had dealt ſo by him to accept the younger, and reject the elder. Alſo the like caſe was with <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> becauſe <hi>Jacob</hi> had got the bleſſing from <hi>Eſau,</hi> he reaſoned in himſelf to kill his brother <hi>Jacob;</hi> ſo he reaſoned in himſelf how he might do this murder, and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur his Father <hi>Iſaac's</hi> diſpleaſure, ſo he reaſoned in himſelf how he might have opportunity to do it, and not to be diſcovered that he did it, and this reaſoning in <hi>Eſau</hi> took place in his ſoul, and gave a reſolution to put it into execution to kill <hi>Jacob,</hi> becauſe he was bleſt, and <hi>Eſau</hi> was not bleſt with that bleſſed promiſe that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Seed ſhould come of him, as his brother <hi>Jacob</hi> was.</p>
               <p>For this is to be minded by the Reader, that the perſon that is accepted of God, of that perſon the righteous Seed muſt, and doth come of; &amp; look what perſon is rejected of God, of that perſon muſt, and doth come the reprobate and curſed Seed, as it was in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> alſo; <hi>Eſau</hi> would have put his reaſoning of his mind in practiſe, had not <hi>Rebecca</hi> his Mother by her revelation of Faith ſent <hi>Jacob</hi> away out of <hi>Eſaus</hi> reach; but <hi>Eſaus</hi> reſolution remained in his minde ſtill, and waited for an opportunity: now was not this reaſon in <hi>Eſau</hi> the devil? for if <hi>Eſau</hi> had had no reaſon to kill <hi>Jacob,</hi> he would never have reſolved to do ſuch wickedneſs, but <hi>Eſau</hi> thought he had good reaſon to kill <hi>Jacob,</hi> who had ſtoln away the bleſſing from him, whoſe birthright he thought in reaſon it was, ſo he thought it was but reaſon to kill his brother who had done him that injury or wrong: was not this the ſpirit of reaſon the devil in <hi>Eſau,</hi> that would have killed his brother <hi>Jacob</hi> of whom the righteous Seed came of?</p>
               <p>Again, were not thoſe reaſonable men that talked with Chriſt, to whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Why reaſon you in your ſelves, ſaying, you have A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham for your Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe up children unto Abraham,</hi> ſo thoſe Phariſees and Saducees that came to the baptiſm of <hi>John, Mat.</hi> 4. were they not wiſe rational men, and indued with a high meaſure of reaſon? did not they ask a reaſonable queſtion whether <hi>John</hi> was the Chriſt or no? yet <hi>John</hi> calls them <hi>a generation of vipers:</hi> and Chriſt calls thoſe wiſe rational men he talked with, Serpents, Devils, yea, and that the devil was their Father; yet theſe were wiſe, prudent men, indued with a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:192297:31"/>
great meaſure of reaſon: they were no diſtracted men, nor poſſeſt with any witchcraft-fits, as you Quakers are, but were ſober, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible men, and would ask a reaſonable queſtion, and required a reaſonable anſwer, yet this ſpirit of reaſon in theſe wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent men, it was but the devil reaſon in them.</p>
               <p>For <hi>John</hi> calls them <hi>a generation of vipers,</hi> and Chriſt calls them <hi>Serpents, Devils,</hi> and that they were the devils children, yet theſe were wiſe men, endued with reaſon, and it was that wiſdom of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in them, that would have intrapt Chriſt in his words that they might have had ſome reaſon to have put him to death; for Reaſon propounds queſtions to catch him in his words, that they might have had ſome reaſon to put him to death, therefore Reaſon layd many ſnares to catch him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So they reaſoned amongſt themſelves, if we let this man alone, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans will take away our place and nation,</hi> ſo when they had accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed their deſires by their reaſon, and brought him before the High-prieſt and Councel of the Jews, the Councel ſome of them reaſoned that it was fit Chriſt ſhould die for blaſphemy, in that he made himſelf the Son of God; others reaſoned again that he ought not to die by their Law, not being juſtly accuſed.</p>
               <p>So when he came into <hi>Pilates</hi> cuſtody, what reaſoning had <hi>Pilate</hi> in his ſpirit? his reaſon told him it was better to whip Chriſt, than to kill him; and <hi>Pilates</hi> wifes dream put him exceedingly to reaſon how he might deliver Chriſt, but the reaſon of the High-prieſts and Elders and thoſe that were below them, their reaſon was too ſtrong for <hi>Pilate,</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> thought it more reaſon to obey <hi>Ceſar</hi> then his wifes dream, or the reaſoning of his own heart.</p>
               <p>So that his reaſon was, he thought better to keep the favour of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and the honor of this world than the peace of his conſcience and favour with God; ſo his reaſon and their reaſon together deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up the Juſt One to be crucified by reaſonable men, for the Centurion and thoſe that guarded him were reaſonable men alſo, and thought it but reaſon to obey their Rulers command in this, as well as other things: ſo that it may be cleer to thoſe that are truely inlightned, that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil, and that the ſpirit of reaſon did kill the righteous in the beginning, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of reaſon did kill the Juſt perſon, even Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:192297:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <p>AGain, it may be cleer that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil, as may plainly appear by thoſe Chief-prieſts and Elders of the Jews, as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 21 23. theſe Chief-prieſts and Elders would know of Chriſt by what authority he did thoſe things? but Chriſts anſwer was, <hi>Is the Baptiſme of John from Heaven, or of men?</hi> and theſe Chief-prieſts and Elders of the Jews reaſoned in themſelves, if they ſhould ſay from Heaven; then their reaſon told them they fought againſt God; and if they ſhould ſay, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> had his commiſſion from men to baptiſe with water, then their reaſon told them that the people would ſtone them:</p>
               <p>So they reaſoned in themſelves it was better to ſay, they could not tell, which was a lye againſt the light of their own conſcience. Here the Reader may ſee that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; for theſe Chief-prieſts and Elders were wiſe, prudent men, endued with a great meaſure of reaſon, elſe they would not have bin choſen Governors and Expounders of the Law and Prophets to the people of the Jews; yet theſe reaſonable men were devils, even thoſe who Chriſt called <hi>Serpents, Devils;</hi> and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> called <hi>a generation of vipers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that it may be cleer to thoſe that are inlightned, that the reaſon in man is the devil, and not onely a devil, but a damned de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; for it was the ſpirit of reaſon in man that always blaſphemed and fought againſt God, and perſecuted and killed the Juſt and the righteous, becauſe God would not accept of the devil reaſons worſhip, as he did of the Juſt and innocent worſhip of the ſpirit of Faith: and as for that ſaying of <hi>Paul, who deſired to be delivered from unreaſonable men, for all men have not faith,</hi> I am of <hi>Pauls</hi> mind in that, for I have had experience in a meaſure of the bad dealings of unreaſonable men as <hi>Paul</hi> had: but I ſhall ſhew the cauſe and why <hi>Paul</hi> calls them <hi>unreaſonable men,</hi> it was becauſe the rude multitude, or ſome envious men upon the report of other envious people, would beat and abuſe <hi>Paul</hi> without any authority from the Rulers, or without the command of ſome officer, as is cleer in the <hi>Acts</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the Goddeſs <hi>Diana:</hi> how were ſome of <hi>Pauls</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:192297:32"/>
friends beaten by unreaſonable men, and <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf would have bin ſerved ſo and worſe, had he not bin reſcued by the Town-Clark's ſpeech; which ſpeech of his ſhewed that the people did that which was not lawful by their Law, therefore unreaſonable, and were in danger to be called to account by the Judges of their Law, as Deputies and ſuch, and to be puniſhed as offenders of the Law for their unreaſonable practice, to beat and kill men uncondemned by the Law, as you may ſee <hi>Acts the</hi> 19.18. <hi>and ſo in Acts</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>How <hi>Paul</hi> had like to have bin killed by unreaſonable men, forty of them had bound themſelves in an oath, neither to eat nor drink till they had killed <hi>Paul;</hi> yet by the power of the Centurion who had a commiſſion from the Magiſtrates to keep the peace, would not ſuffer theſe men to do ſuch unreaſonable deeds to kill a man, and not condemned by the Law of reaſon; for all Laws are made by the reaſon of man to govern people by.</p>
               <p>So in other places in the <hi>Acts</hi> you may read how <hi>Paul</hi> was abuſed by unreaſonable men, ſo that <hi>Paul</hi> had cauſe, and all Saints elſe, to deſire to be delivered from unreaſonable men; for all men have not ſaith; <hi>Paul</hi> knowing that thoſe men that have faith dares not perſecute men for conſciences, though he hath reaſon ſo to do, much leſs to perſecute men for conſcience againſt Law and reaſon, as the rude multitude doth, and envious men doth, having not Law of their ſide, but are puniſhed as evil doers by the law of reaſon for doing things contrary to the Law, therefore called <hi>unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this ſence <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to be delivered from unreaſonable men, for he knew men that had faith in their hearts would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute nor abuſe him, nor kill him, though he ſhould give them cauſe. This I my ſelf knoweth by experience to be true, for I have fallen ſometimes into the hands of unreaſonable men, for I have bin pull'd out of the houſe by head and ſhoulders, and beaten with their fiſts, and knocked down in the garden, and when they were affraid to do me more miſchief in another bodies houſe, they conſulted to lay in wait in all the Alleys to catch me as I came out, that they might do me ſome further miſchief, and no body know who did it: they thought to break my bones, if not kill me, but they were ſomewhat prevented, for we paſſed through a mans garden a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate way, ſo that the layers in wait could not catch us untill we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:192297:32"/>
came in the fields, but when they heard we were paſt the corners of the Alleys which were four, they run, and the boys run to ſee the men run, that the duſt and gravel did flye about with the ſound of their feet, to overtake us; ſo two of the men of the moſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateſt of them overtook us in the fields, and they both ſmote upon my head and neck with their fiſts a while, and then run to <hi>John Reeve,</hi> and ſtruck up his feet, and he fell upon the gravel which made his hands bleed, ſo he lay upon the ground, and people came thick about us to know what was the matter; but the woman came in whoſe houſe I was pulled out of, and ſhe knew theſe two men that purſued us in the fields, ſo they left off, and ſlank away, leſt ſhe ſhould have had the Law of them for abuſing us in her houſe: There was about a hundred of them in her houſe and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den when they pulled me out, theſe were unreaſonable men, ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> met withall which he deſired to be delivered from. Several times hath <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf been in danger to be abuſed and ſpoiled by unreaſonable men, and it was upon the ſame account, as <hi>Paul</hi> was.</p>
               <p>For he was ſerved ſo for declaring Jeſus Chriſt to be the Son of God, and that he was a meſſenger to declare it; and we for declaring Chriſt Jeſus to be the onely God, and our ſelves to be commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated from him, to bleſs the Seed of Faith, and curſe deſpiſiing ſpirits to eternity.</p>
               <p>So that I am not unacquainted, nor ignorant of <hi>Pauls</hi> words; For it hath been always my deſire ever ſince to be delivered from the rude multitude, who doth not go by the Law of reaſon, but doth act as bruit-beaſts, who have no reaſon in them, therefore called unreaſonable men. This is a true diſtinction and interpretation what the devil is, even the ſpirit of reaſon in man, and how reaſon always killed the juſt and righteous Seed of Faith, and what the Apoſtle meant when he deſired to be delivered from unreaſonable men, and who may be ſaid to be unreaſonable men. Much more might be ſaid in this point, but I ſuppoſe there is enough written to ſatisfie and inform any man that hath true light of faith in him, or hath but moderate reaſon.</p>
               <p>Onely this may be minded by the Reader, that the Scriptures never called diſtracted men, nor mad-men, nor fools; nor diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered brained men are never called <hi>Devils,</hi> though theſe men are
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192297:33"/>
poſſeſt with Devils; that is, with diſtempers of nature, theſe are Devils that are produced through accidents of nature, through ſome extraordinary grief, fright, or loſſes, and ſuch like, hath broke the brain, and ſo the ſeat of reaſon is quite out of order, and makes them more ſtrong then when their reaſon was in order, and ſo come to be poſſeſt with devils; theſe devils are produced by accidents in nature, as I ſaid before.</p>
               <p>So not thoſe devils the Scriptures ſpeake of: we never read that any Prophet, Apoſtle, or Chriſt himſelf did ever condemn or judge ſuch perſons, but rather pittied them, and healed them, and caſt thoſe devils out, as may be read in Scripture, nay the civil Magiſtrate doth not regard what a mad-man ſaith, whoſe reaſon is out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; therefore it may be clear that the moſt wiſe, prudent men, who have the greateſt meaſure of reaſon in them, are thoſe Devils the Scriptures calls devils, therefore more fit to be politicians both in Church and State, neither could unwiſe man in reaſon go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern this world as it is at this day.</p>
               <p>So that it may be clear to thoſe that are inlightned, that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil that killed the righteous and the Juſt, for <hi>Cain</hi> was a high pitch of reaſon when he killed righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> for <hi>Cain</hi> had the fulneſs of the reprobat Angels ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of reaſon, it dwelt in <hi>Cain</hi> bodily, and <hi>Eſau</hi> had much reaſon, and <hi>Judas,</hi> and that devil that tempted Chriſt was a man, &amp; had a great meaſure of the wiſdom of reaſon in him; and thoſe Chief-prieſts and Elders that Chriſt called <hi>Serpents, Devils,</hi> that tempted him, were indued with a great meaſure of reaſon; they were wiſe, ſenſible, ſober, learned men, yet devils, and the ſpirit of reaſon in them was the devil that tempted Chriſt, &amp; perſecuted him, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him that was the juſt One, even the Savior of the world, of the elect Seed, ſo that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures condemn, which commits murder for conſcience ſake, or other ways, and is that devil that is to be damned to eternity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that the Devil ſo much ſpoken of in Scripture, and condemned by Chriſt, it was ſenſible, wiſe, prudent men, indued with a high pitch of reaſon, and not unreaſonable men, nor mad, frantick, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted men, as people do vainly imagine, as <hi>Fox</hi> and moſt of the Quakers do.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, it was the Godhead life that ſuffered death.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:192297:33"/>
                  <hi>Fox</hi> calls this darkneſs alſo; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Chriſt he ſuffered in the fleſh; but he did not die as he was God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Fox</hi> hath diſcovered his Allegorical Cheat, as I have made appear before; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he in the fourteenth particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of this Book, <hi>the Quakers owns the Son of God who was crucified, and laid in the grave, and roſe again, and ſits at the right hand of God,</hi> yet <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>the Godhead life did not die.</hi> Here <hi>Fox</hi> hath manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his great ignorance of life that died; alſo he hath cut himſelf off from having any part or portion in the death of Chriſt, for God and Chriſt is all one undividual, or undivided Eſſence, Perſon, and Subſtance, ſo that when Chriſt died, God died; and when Chriſts blood, or ſoul was poured out unto death, the ſoul of God was poured out unto death alſo, Chriſt being God and Man.</p>
               <p>For no man can truly ſay Chriſt was God and Man, except he were God as well as Man; for if there be another God beſides Chriſt, or above Chriſt, then Chriſt is not God as well as man, as people do vainly imagine. Now we read that Chriſt poured out his ſoul unto death, and will any dare to ſay that the ſoul of Chriſt was not the ſoul of God? it is high blaſphemy to affirm the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; beſides it cuts a man off from all benefit of the death of Chriſt, for no blood but the blood of a God can ſpeak peace to the ſoul of man, therefore it is <hi>the blood of Chriſt ſpeaketh better things than the blood of Abel,</hi> becauſe <hi>Abel</hi> was but a faithful man.</p>
               <p>But Chriſt was God as well as man, yet this Godhead life did die, and quickened again by its own power, which <hi>Abels</hi> life could not do, being but a man. But what ſhould I talk to Quakers of theſe things, for they do not believe that any ſouls die, no not their own, they all ſlip away, and leave the body to ſuffer; ſo <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith Chriſt ſuffered in the fleſh, but his ſoul did not die, but ſlipt out of his body; for he doth not own that Chriſts ſoul died, neither as he was God, nor as he was man. But this is opened more large con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Godhead life dying, in <hi>The Interpretation of the whole Book of the Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what think you, <hi>Fox,</hi> did <hi>Cain</hi> kill the ſoul or life of <hi>Abel,</hi> or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192297:34"/>
no? or did he onely drive his ſoul or ſpirit out of his body? Surely if <hi>Cain</hi> had not killed <hi>Abels</hi> ſoul, his blood would never haye cryed for vengeance in Gods ears, and in his own conſcience as it did, if his life had not been killed.</p>
               <p>What do you think, <hi>Fox,</hi> that <hi>Judas</hi> did by his ſoul when he hang'd himſelf? did he onely hang the body that his ſoul might ſlip away, and leave his body to ſuffer? What, do you think the ſufferings that all Quakers of late, and others have undergone in impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and baniſhment, ſome have died by reaſon of thoſe ſufferings, but you Quakers do believe it was nothing but their bodies that ſuffered, their ſouls ſuffered nothing, they ſlipt out of their bodies, and went ſome where, you know not where.</p>
               <p>So your perſecutors did you no great hurt, onely turned your ſouls out of your bodies before the time, as a Landlord doth a bad Tenant, turns him out of his houſe for not paying his Rent, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kills him: So the Quakers ſouls are never killed, they are only ſeparated from the body, ſo that there is no great harm done by the perſecutors, they do but onely ſeparate ſoul and body one from the other, they do not kill life in the Quakers, for life cannot die; the body indeed may ſuffer, but life cannot die.</p>
               <p>This is <hi>Fox</hi> the Quakers faith, and all Quakers elſe that I have talked with, and were not the Quakers blinded and hardned, they would be aſhamed to own ſuch a Principle; for all true Believers are aſhamed of the Quakers faith in this point, nay, men that are meer moral men that have no light but the dictates of nature, do know by experience, that the ſpirit and ſoul of man doth die, for nothing can be capable of pain but life, nor nothing can be capable to die but life, yet theſe blinde Quakers cannot believe that life can die, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Page 21. <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, God the King of Heaven is not in this world at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fox</hi> calls this Lies alſo; <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou doſt confeſs that Chriſt is God; and</hi> John ſaith, <hi>he was in the world, but the world knew him not.</hi> Alſo <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>the true Prophet ſaith he fills heaven and earth: but,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, the falſe prophet ſaith God the King of Heaven is not in this world at all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:192297:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat ſaying of mine is truth, That God the King of Heaven is not in this world at all, not in his Perſon and Eſſence, or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as is clearly opened in <hi>The Neck of the Quakers broken,</hi> which whoſoever doth read that Book may ſee every one of thoſe ſayings of mine more clearly opened than in this Treatiſe; yet <hi>George Fox</hi> calls them all lies, and darkneſs, and ſuch like, though what I have written in that Book is as true as any Writings of the Prophets or Apoſtles, and are of as great Authority, and will prove as true in the end as theirs.</p>
               <p>But to give the Reader a little light to ſee the groſs darkneſs of this <hi>Fox</hi> and his ſubtilty: <hi>Fox</hi> brings the words of <hi>John,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>Chriſt was in the world, but the world knew him not.</hi> Minde! Did I ever deny in all my Writings that Chriſt never was in the world? I always in all my Writings juſtified more than any man living, that Chriſt the onely God was in this world in the ſtate of mortality, which the Apoſtles did witneſs unto; therefore it is that <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt was in the world, but the world knew him not,</hi> which doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that Chriſt was not in the world in his perſon at that time when <hi>John</hi> writ thoſe words; if he had, <hi>John</hi> would have ſaid, Chriſt is now in the world, but the world knows him not.</p>
               <p>So that it is clear to thoſe that know the Scriptures, that Chriſt the onely God was not in this world at all in the Apoſtles time: he was in the world before he ſuffered death, and the world knew him not; but after he was aſcended he hath not been in this world never ſince, and this <hi>John</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles knew very well, and they preached this Chriſt that was in the world, but the world knew him not, therefore they perſecuted him, and ſlew him, and would ſlay him again if he were in this world now, ſo <hi>John</hi> knew well enough, therefore he teſtified that Chriſt was in the world in his own perſon, but the wicked world put him to death, becauſe they knew him not; but he is not in the world now, for he is aſcended: for <hi>John</hi> knew if Chriſt had been in the world in his perſon at that time, they would have done unto him as they did before; and becauſe Chriſt was not in the world in his perſon in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:192297:35"/>
the Apoſtles time, therefore the world perſecuted them, and put them to death for witneſſing that Chriſt was in the world, and they with wicked hands had ſlain the Lord of Life, even Chriſt Jeſus, the onely God, the King of Heaven.</p>
               <p>So that <hi>John</hi> and I am both of one minde, and of one faith, that though Chriſt the only God and King of Heaven, was in this world before he ſuffered death, this <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle and I both do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and know, but ſince Chriſt roſe from the dead and aſcended up to heaven, <hi>John</hi> and I do believe and know, that Chriſt the only God and King of heaven is not in this world at all in his perſon and eſſence, yet <hi>Fox</hi> calls this Lies: But the Reader may ſee if he hath any light, who it is that lies, <hi>Fox</hi> or I.</p>
               <p>Alſo he ſaith, <hi>The true Prophet ſaith, God the King of Heaven fills heaven and earth; but,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the falſe prophet ſaith, God the King of Heaven is not in this world at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a ſmall thing to be called a falſe prophet by the Seed of the Serpent, eſpecially by a damned devil; for I know <hi>Fox</hi> would have ſaid ſo by thoſe prophets he calls true, had he lived in that time, and this <hi>John</hi> and Chriſt he ſo much talks of, would have been count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all falſe: a falſe Chriſt, a falſe Witneſs, what will any Quaker believe that to be a Chriſt, a Savior that comes in likeneſs of man, nay, is a man, ſin excepted? No, no, we will have a Chriſt that is a Spirit, that may creep into our ſpirits when he will, and whip out again when we commit ſin, and diſpleaſe his Spirit, ſuch a Chriſt we own that hath never a body of his own, but is all Spirit, that fills every Quakers body with his Spirit, and heaven and earth alſo. What, will you perſwade us to believe that Chriſt is a man, Chriſt is God, and admits of no form, ſo thou <hi>John</hi> art a falſe witneſs, to perſwade us to believe in a man to be Chriſt, or God the Savior of the world; this I know would <hi>Fox</hi> and the reſt of the Quakers have ſaid by thoſe he calls now true prophets they being dead, and by Chriſt and the Apoſtles, as he doth by me.</p>
               <p>For when they were alive on earth as I am now, they were coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſeed of the Serpent, ſuch as <hi>Fox</hi> is, Blaſphemers, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, Liers, and ſuch like, but now who ſo zealous for the dead letter of the Prophets, and Apoſtles, as the ſeed of the Serpent are, but when they were alive, they were hated and perſecuted for ſpeaking that which the ſeed of the Serpent doth now honor; ſo
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:192297:35"/>
is it with me now I am alive, I am hated and perſecuted by the ſeed of the Serpent, as well by Quakers as others, for my doctrine and commiſſion now while I am alive; but when I am dead many of the ſeed of the Serpent in the next generation ſhall have reſpect unto my Writings, and ſhall ſay, had we lived in thoſe days that <hi>Fox</hi> and other Quakers lived in, we would never have blaſphemed and ſpoken evil of ſo pure a truth as <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker hath done, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur eternal damnation upon our own heads, as <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker their father hath done: theſe things will come to paſs, as it hath done in the other two Commiſſions, namely the Law &amp; the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Page 22. <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, the Quakers hearken to the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but they deſpiſe the body and perſon of Chriſt without them, and ſo they are Antichriſt.</p>
               <p n="20">20. To this <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Here are more Lies of the falſe prophet; for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Chriſt that died at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>his perſon we own without us, who is manifeſt within us, the light of Chriſt Jeſus, by which we have ſeen of his glory, and ſpeak in his perſon.</hi> And <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Solomons Books in the Bible are good Scripture, though</hi> Muggleton <hi>ſaith they be not Scripture, he being not in the ſpirit of</hi> Solomon <hi>that gave them forth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Fox</hi> hath ſhewed his Allegorical Juggle, who dares not deny the perſon of Chriſt without them, not in plain terms, becauſe the Scriptures are ſo full to prove Chriſt a perſon, and it is the Faith of all Chriſtendom, as we call it; but any man that hath any true light in him, may ſee that <hi>Fox</hi> is a meer Juggler to deceive the ſimple and ignorant, whoſe doctrine makes the people more dark in their mindes, than they were by nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, we Quakers own the perſon of Chriſt without us, who is manifeſt within us.</hi> There is ſuch a great ſtir with Gods Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to part Chriſts perſon or body from the Quakers, and their bodies from him, that Chriſts body might ſtand ſingle of it ſelf, and the Quakers bodies might ſtand ſingle of themſelves, at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from Chriſts body; but the Quakers will either get into Chriſts body, or elſe Chriſt muſt get into the Quakers bodies, ſo that no man can tell how to part them one from another, but I know death will part them: And Chriſt will ſay to <hi>Fox</hi> and other
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:192297:36"/>
Quakers, Depart from me you workers of iniquity, you pretended that you were my Saints, and that I was in you, and you in me, but I know you not; neither did I ſend you to preach, for I never was in you by my Spirit to aſſiſt you in your preaching; you ſhould have let preaching and praying in my name alone, for you have done more hurt than good, in that your doctrine hath blinded the eyes of many people, and have led them as ſheep to the ſlaughter, and hath cauſed many to ſuffer extreamly in this life, even to the loſs of their natural life, beſides the puniſhment hereafter.</p>
               <p>For you ſhould have hearkened to my choſen Witneſſes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, who can declare the true Chriſt God and man in one ſingle perſon, in the form of a man, with the right devil, his form and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but your non-knowledge of the right devil is the cauſe of your groſs darkneſs in the knowledge of the true Chriſt.</p>
               <p>What are you Quakers the better for your Chriſt within you? he yields you no true peace: and what are you the better for being in Chriſt? for the true Chriſt denies you, and will not be in you by his Spirit, neither will he ſuffer you to be in him, becauſe you and a great part of you Quakers are of the reprobate Seed, which have no part nor portion in the true Chriſt; for you are, and the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers people, but the devil transformed into the likeneſs of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light, becauſe you are ſomething more preciſe in your life as to outward appearance, but your preciſeneſs is very much broken and withered of late years; your darkneſs and ignorance is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the light of this Commiſſion of the Spirit; for you are not like the people you were formerly, neither doth your Witchcraft-fits catch any now as it did heretofore. Your Witchcraft-fits can hardly be produced now of late not in any, I marvel how you Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers can have Chriſts perſon manifeſt in you, and how you can ſpeak in his perſon!</p>
               <p>Let the Reader mind the Quakers Cheat, they own Chriſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon without them, yet this perſon of Chriſt without them is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt within them. See the deceit of this <hi>Fox!</hi> I have read of Chriſt manifeſt in his Saints and Apoſtles, by his Spirit or Seed of Faith, but I never read that Chriſts perſon, fleſh and bone was ever mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt within any man, that was alwayes without man, and will be without man for ever, diſtinct of himſelf.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>the Quakers ſpeak in Chriſts perſon.</hi> Here is another
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:192297:36"/>
Allegorical ſpeech without any diſtinction: I have heard that an Ambaſſador hath repreſented the perſon of a King, and his ſpeech by vertue of a Commiſſion from the King is in the Kings ſtead, but the Ambaſſador is not in the Kings perſon, though he repreſents the Kings perſon, the Kings perſon is at a great diſtance from his Meſſenger.</p>
               <p>So it is with Chriſts Ambaſſadors, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors in Chriſts ſtead, beſeeching you to be reconciled unto Chriſt by our doctrine.</hi> Now <hi>Pauls</hi> perſon, and Chriſts perſon were at a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance one from the other; for Chriſts perſon was in heaven above the ſtars, and <hi>Pauls</hi> perſon was here upon earth, ſo that <hi>Paul</hi> did not ſpeak in the perſon of Chriſt, that being at ſuch a diſtance, as I ſaid before; but <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles by vertue of their Commiſſion given from Chriſt, were Ambaſſadors of him, and ſo ſtood in Chriſts ſtead, but Chriſts perſon was far enough off from them, as a Kings perſon is far off when his Ambaſſador is in a ſtrange Land, who repreſents the Kings perſon, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>But the Quakers they will get into Chriſts perſon, and ſpeak there, or elſe they will get Chriſts perſon into them, and ſo Chriſt muſt ſpeak there in their perſons, ſo as I ſaid before, the Quakers will not be ſeparated from Chriſt, nor ſuffer him to ſeparate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from them, though I know they never were in union together, neither was Chriſt ever in them that I have damned, nor never will be, neither were they ever in Chriſt, nor never ſhall be.</p>
               <p>Neither doth <hi>Fox</hi> own indeed that perſon of Chriſt of fleſh and bone that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be now living in heaven above the ſtars, but <hi>Fox</hi> and the Quakers Chriſt they ſo much talk of, is a meer Allegory without ſubſtance, a Chriſt that may be blown away with the word of a true Prophets mouth, as I ſaid in <hi>The Neck of the Quakers broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Solomons Books are good Scripture,</hi> though I ſay they are not, being not in the ſpirit of <hi>Solomon</hi> that gave them forth.</p>
               <p>Here I perceive that <hi>Fox</hi> and the Quakers are got into <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpirit, juſt as they did get into Chriſts perſon. I ſee <hi>Fox</hi> can get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſpirits as he doth into perſons: but I perceive <hi>Fox</hi> is got into <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpirit, and he blames me becauſe I am not in <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: I do ſeriouſly confeſs that I am not in <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpirit, and I am glad I never was in his ſpirit; for who ever is in <hi>Solomons</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:192297:37"/>
ſpirit, doth not know the true God, nor the right devil, for <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> knew neither of them, though he was a wiſe man in things of nature, but ignorant of ſpiritual and heavenly wiſdom; for <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> wiſdom hath the Ground-work of much luſt of the fleſh and idolatry; for the Ranters practice was grounded upon <hi>Solomons</hi> practice, who knew ſo many women, ſo the Ranters thought they might have the ſame liberty, ſeeing wiſe <hi>Solomons</hi> Writings were owned for Scripture-record; thus they continued many of them in their practice of luſt, till many of them were weary of it, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was when he was old, and then they left off that practice, and turned Quakers, and ſo fell to be the greateſt idolaters of any, as <hi>Solomon</hi> did to his Heatheniſh-Wives, drew his heart away from the worſhip of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to worſhip idols.</p>
               <p>So is it with thoſe Ranters that are turned Quakers, they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come abſolute Heathen idolaters, for when they, were <hi>Puritanes,</hi> ſo called, they were zealous for the letter of the Scriptures, and did practice a good life as near as they could to the letter, but after they fell to the practice of luſt, being encouraged by <hi>Solomons</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, they left that legal Worſhip and civil practice the Law tied them unto, and followed <hi>Solomons</hi> practice of luſt.</p>
               <p>And now they being turned Quakers, are fallen to heathen ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, that is to ſay, the Quakers they worſhip an unknown God, a Spirit without a body; they adore a Chriſt within them, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mindes a body of Chriſt without them at a diſtance; they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve their own ſpirits to be immortal, and cannot die; they believe their ſpirits go to God, or into God again, according to <hi>Solomons</hi> words; they believe Gods Spirit being an infinite Being without a body, and that this infinite bodileſs Spirit taketh all things into it ſelf, and ſo their ſpirits being immortal, they go into God when they die; they will not acknowledge that life or ſoul doth die, but departs out of the body they know not where, notwithſtanding the Scriptures are ſo full to prove the ſoul that ſins ſhall die, and experience ſhews it doth die.</p>
               <p>So that the Quakers are become the greateſt ſpiritual idolaters of any, and the greateſt fighters againſt a perſonal God of any; for as <hi>Solomon</hi> did fall to worſhip the heathen womens viſible Images, or Idols, ſo do the Quakers worſhip inviſible Idols, as a Spirit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body, and that their own ſpirits may ſubſiſt without bodies,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:192297:37"/>
and that ſpirits may be capable of happineſs or miſery without bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, this is the Heathen Philoſophers opinion, they brought into the world that Principle of the Immortality of the Soul, and that Spirits might go to happineſs or miſery without bodies.</p>
               <p>And the Quakers hath got the Heathen Principle to a hair, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore become Heathen Idolaters, as <hi>Solomon</hi> was; for the Scriptures declares another thing. Where doth the Scriptures ſay that God is an Infinite Spirit without a body? The Scripture ſaith, God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and ſo he is. Alſo the Scripture ſaith, <hi>God is a Spirit, and will be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth:</hi> but it is not ſaid, God is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without a body: for this I ſay that if a man may worſhip God in ſpirit and truth in this natural body, as the diſciples of Chriſt did in their natural bodies, and as I my ſelf do in my natural body, then of neceſſity it will follow that God hath a ſpiritual body, whereby I may worſhip him, elſe I ſhall worſhip I know not what, as you Quakers do.</p>
               <p>And becauſe Gods body is a ſpiritual body, therefore Chriſt ſaid when on earth, <hi>God is a Spirit, and will be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth;</hi> he knowing that body of his that was then a pure natural body, ſhould by his death and riſing again, be made a ſpiritual bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and then all true Believers ſhould worſhip him in ſpirit and truth here in this natural body; and ſo true Believers have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped Chriſt the onely God in ſpirit and truth in the Apoſtles Commiſſion, and ſo do we now worſhip God in ſpirit and truth; for there can be no worſhipping God in ſpirit and truth without a true Preacher ſent of God, as the Apoſtles, <hi>John Reeve,</hi> and my ſelf were: and in this ſenſe God may be ſaid to be a Spirit, becauſe he is a ſpiritual body, and not a bodileſs ſpirit, as you Quakers do vainly imagine; elſe why may not God be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth without a body, as well as God to be a Spirit without a body? You Quakers do not do well, in that you do not turn your ſouls out of your bodies, they being as you conceive immortal, me thinks you might ſometimes let your immortal ſouls ſlip out of your bodies, and go into that Infinite Spirit without a body, and worſhip in ſpirit and truth, and then come into thoſe bodies again; for I ſee you have by your own words got into Chriſts perſon, and you have got into <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpirit, and why can you not get your immortal ſouls into Gods Infinite Spirit without a body?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:192297:38"/>By this the Reader may ſee that the Quakers Principle is built upon the Heathen Philoſophers, and not upon the faith of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles who writ the Scriptures, for Heathen men were the firſt broachers of the Immortality of the Soul, and of God being an Infinite Spirit without a body, and ſo the greateſt Idolaters; for thoſe that writ the Scriptures never intended any ſuch thing, but altogether the contrary: but the Quakers do cleave to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then principles, as God being a Spirit without a body, and the Immortality of the Soul, and ſo they become with the Heathen the greateſt ſpiritual Idolaters of any people under the Sun; for I am quite out of <hi>Solomons</hi> ſpirit indeed, and am glad I never was in it.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Page 27. <hi>Muggleton</hi> thou condemneſt our Chriſt and light: and <hi>Muggleton</hi> ſaith, the Quakers think to have eternal life in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, our eternal life is in Chriſt before Scriptures were. And</hi> Fox ſaith pag. 29. <hi>thou exalteſt thy ſelf above Chriſt, for he is a man,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>the man Chriſt Jeſus will bruiſe me to pieces, which is manifeſt in his people,</hi> meaning the Quakers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS for my words, they are more largely opened in <hi>The Quakers Neck broken;</hi> Alſo this ſaying of <hi>Fox, that the Quakers had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life in Chriſt before Scriptures were,</hi> to this I ſay, How comes it to paſs that Chriſt hath turned <hi>George Fox</hi> Quaker, and many more of them out of him now the world is? Nay, Chriſt hath turned them over to be judged and condemned by me to eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: certainly if <hi>Fox</hi> had eternal life in Chriſt before Scriptures were, Chriſt would have revealed it unto me now the Scriptures are in the world; for the Scriptures are given into my hands, and I finde by the Scriptures that <hi>George Fox</hi> and many other Quakers were never in Chriſt at all, neither before Scriptures were, nor now the Scriptures are in being.</p>
               <p>But I finde in the Book of the Scriptures, that <hi>George Fox</hi> and other Quakers were in the Serpent that beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> and had eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death in their ſeed before Scripture were, but it was not viſibly known till now; for this I certainly know that you, <hi>Fox,</hi> and many
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:192297:38"/>
more of you came out of the Serpents loins, which was <hi>Cains</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you being the children of <hi>Cain,</hi> may be ſaid to be in the Serpent-devil before the Scriptures were: and as ſure as <hi>Cain</hi> the father of all the damned ſhall die an eternal death, ſo I am certain that you <hi>George Fox,</hi> with many other of your Quakers people ſhall be eternally damned, deliver your ſelves from it if you can.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith page 29. <hi>That thou exalteſt thy ſelf above Chriſt, for he is a man: and ſaith, the man Chriſt Jeſus will bruiſe me to pieces, which is manifeſt in his people,</hi> meaning the Quakers.</p>
               <p>I cannot get <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker and the man Chriſt Jeſus to part, for whereſoever <hi>Fox</hi> doth own Chriſt Jeſus to be a man, then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently this manhood of Chriſt gets into the Quakers bodies, and ſo Chriſt is manifeſt in them. Now I would very fain have Chriſts manhood by it ſelf, and the Quakers by themſelves, but <hi>Fox</hi> will by no means part with Chriſt that he might be ſpoken with alone, but Chriſt being ſo much manifeſt in the <hi>Quakers</hi> bodies, ſo that no Quaker can finde any Chriſt to be a man, but what is manifeſt in their bodies.</p>
               <p>And this Chriſt that is manifeſt in them, I ſuppoſe is he that will bruiſe me in pieces, but that man Chriſt Jeſus that I believe in, hath given me power to condemn and judge that man Chriſt Jeſus that is manifeſt in the Quakers people, for I know that Chriſt Jeſus that is manifeſt in them is nothing elſe but the ſeed of Reaſon the devil that is manifeſt in them; for I know they have no faith in the true Chriſt, but the motions of reaſon working in their mindes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king occaſion by the Law written in their hearts, it doth cleanſe them from the outward pollutions of the world, and from the breach of ſome outward Laws, and this is that Chriſt they ſo much talk of within them, and this is that man Chriſt Jeſus manifeſt within them. This is a true deſcription of the Quakers Chriſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt within them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the moſt conſiderable things for the Reader to take notice of in <hi>George Fox</hi> his Book, ſo that the Reader may mind the Anſwer and the Interpretation I have given to thoſe Scriptures which <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker brings againſt me; but he leaves the words
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:192297:39"/>
of the Scriptures more dark to the Reader than they were in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but I have given the Interpretation of thoſe Scripture words which <hi>Fox</hi> could not do, and what I have written in this Treatiſe is for the moſt part left out in <hi>The Neck of the Quakers broken,</hi> becauſe in that Book all theſe things in which <hi>Fox</hi> doth rail and revile at me in, as he calls it, <hi>An Anſwer to the Neck of the Quakers broken;</hi> but that Book of mine doth explain the Quakers Principle more plain and clear than this Treatiſe doth; for he that would have read that Book and <hi>Fox</hi> his Anſwer to it, would have ſeen all thoſe things which <hi>Fox</hi> doth alledge againſt me, more fully anſwered than he or any other Quaker could have queſtioned, ſo that had it not been for the ſake of others, and for the Ages to come, there need not have been any further diſcoveries of the Antichriſtian ſpirit of the Quakers concerning their Chriſt within them, but that Book; As alſo there is ſome things in this Treatiſe for the Information of the Reader, which was never printed before.</p>
               <p>There is many other ſayings in <hi>Fox</hi> his Pamphlet which doth rail and revile, both againſt my Commiſſion of the Spirit, and that Sentence I have paſſed upon many of the Quakers people: As firſt, <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>He believes that my Sentence will return back upon my ſelf,</hi> as in pag. 6. 2. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>That thoſe I have curſed are clear over my ſpirit,</hi> as in pag. 12. 3. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Had the Quakers nevar ſeen letter of Scripture, or any man, yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Quakers could have ſpoken in the power, and ſpirit, and in the divine light of Chriſt, had he never ſeen letter of Scripture, nor man,</hi> as in pag. 18. 4. <hi>Fox gives glory to his God and Chriſt within him, who hath,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>ſet him and other Quakers above that Curſe and Sentence I have paſſed upon them,</hi> as in pag. 20. 5. <hi>Fox</hi> blames me for ſaying God hath made me Judge of the Quakers ſpiritual eſtate, <hi>and yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou owns thy ſelf to be but a mortal man.</hi> Oh how <hi>Fox</hi> deſpiſeth that a mortal man ſhould be the Quakers Judge of their immortal ſouls, as they imagine! <hi>for,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, the ſpiritual man judgeth all things,</hi> as in pag. 21. 6. <hi>Fox</hi> blames me for ſaying that the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil; and <hi>Fox</hi> ſeems to juſtifie the Magiſtrates that perſecuted me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay they were reaſonable men. And <hi>Fox</hi> further blames me for fleeing from the devils malice, yet he judgeth that if thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates devils had inflicted more corporal puniſhment upon me than Impriſonment, it had been but reaſon the devil ſtill; <hi>for,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192297:39"/>
                  <hi>Fox, thou canſt no ſay it was unreaſonableneſs in them, according to thy own ſaying,</hi> as in Page 23. 7. <hi>Fox calls me a laying ſpirit,</hi> becauſe I ſay it doth not belong to Chriſt now being in Heaven, to interpret Scripture. <hi>For,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, doth not the Scripture ſay all ſhall be taught of God, and that he opens, and no man ſhuts? and doth not John ſay, no man was found worthy to open the Book but the Lion of the Tribe of Judah, and was not Chriſt anointed to preach?</hi> as in page 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> ANSWER.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, as for that ſentence that I have paſſed upon the Quakers people and others, it is irrevocable, and will be as ſure upon you as if God had ſaid it with his own mouth; for as I ſaid in that book, we are as true Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, as <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, and Apoſtles were; and if they were ſent of God we are ſent of God; and if there were any power in their Sentence and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe people in their time, ſo ſure will the Sentence and Judgement of us the Witneſſes of the Spirit be upon you; and as many of the Quakers people as hath, or ſhall fall under it: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall that curſe I have paſſed upon you deſpiſing Quakers, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon my ſelf no more then the curſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> which open'd the ground to ſwallow up wicked rebellous men alive, for deſiring the Prieſts office; So wil it be with you <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker, in that you have rebell'd againſt the Meſſengers of Chriſt, and ſtrove for to be a Miniſter of Chriſt, when as he never choſe nor ſent you, yet you will proudly contend with thoſe that God hath choſen, anointed, and ſeal'd to declare the higheſt myſteries that ever was declared by man, yet you look upon your ſelf to be better able to preach the Goſpel then we, you who knoweth not the true God, nor what the devil is, nor that your ſoul muſt die, nor any one true principle of Faith, yet you are taken by the people to be a man of knowledge, and ſo you encourage your ſelf to be a Miniſter of Chriſt, and yet knows not what the true Chriſt is, nor where he is, and do you think that Hell ſhall not open its mouth and ſwallow you up alive? Yea, I ſay it will, and you ſhall not eſcape, for I know and ſee it will be ſo, and you ſhall find my words to be true to your eternal pain and ſhame, as <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> did by <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:192297:40"/>2. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, thoſe I have curſed are clear over my ſpirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> ANSWER.</head>
               <p>IT is a marvellous thing that damned men ſhould be over his ſpirit that hath a commiſſion from God, to condemn deſpiſers of the Holy Ghoſt; it is as if a priſoner that is condemned by the Judge for his breach of the Law, ſhould have that curſe he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upon the man over his own head: By <hi>Fox</hi> his conceit the man is in a better caſe then the Judge, for the man may as truely ſay that the ſentence and curſe the Judge hath paſſed upon him is clear over the Judges ſpirit; as if the condemned man were in a better condition then the Judge, yet the one goeth to be hanged, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Judges ſentence, and the Judge goeth to his Palace; So is it with you <hi>George Fox,</hi> and many other of you Quakers, you muſt go to the damnation of eternal death, according to my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and I ſhall enter into everlaſting life that condemned you, ſo that you ſhall never clear your ſelves from that curſe I have paſſed upon you, but it ſhall be over your ſpirits and upon your ſpirits to eternity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>had the Quakers never ſeen letter of Scriptures, or any man, yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Quakers could have ſpoken in the power, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and in the Divine light of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre <hi>Fox</hi> ſheweth plainly that the Quakers light of Chriſt within them is nothing elſe but the Law written in their hearts, their thoughts accuſing and excuſing, as the Heathen have, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, and no divine faith of Chriſt at all. Mind! the Scripture ſaith, <hi>by faith we know the world was made, and by faith Abraham offered up his ſon Iſaac, and faith is the evidence of things not ſeen:</hi> and the Apoſtles preached the word of faith, and this I ſay, no heavenly, ſpiritual, or divine light can be truely underſtood but by faith.</p>
               <p>And this I ſay further, that the letter of the Scriptures were
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:192297:40"/>
ſpoken by the word of Faith, and by faithful men; for there is no writings under Heaven that are the ground of Faith, nor doth give ſatisfaction to the mind of man, as to his eternal ſalvation, as the letter of the Scripture doth, if underſtood and believed by man; how could man have known the creation of the world, and how God appeared to <hi>Noah</hi> before and after the Flood? or whether there were any Flood or no, but by faith? Or how can any man know that God appeared to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and gave them to propheſie ſo many hundred years before of God become<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fleſh, and that he ſhould ſave men from ſin by his death, even as many as ſhould believe in his name, with great and mighty things that hath been done by the power of faith, which the letter of the Scriptures doth relate which no man could comprehend nor know but thoſe that have faith in the letter of the Scriptures; yet <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker he could have ſpoken in the power and ſpirit of the Divine light of Chriſt, though the Quakers had never ſeen letter of Scripture nor man. Here the Reader may plainly ſee that the Quakers Chriſt within them, is no other but the Law written in their hearts, as the Heathen had as aforeſaid; their thoughts accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and excuſing, this is that Chriſt within them they ſo much talk of, and this is that power and ſpirit, and divine light of Chriſt the Quakers could have ſpoken in, had they never ſeen letter of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor man; this is the ſame the Heathen had in them, and this I ſay had the Quakers never ſeen letter of Scripture, nor man that profeſſed the letter of the Scripture, I ſay the Quakers would have talked nor ſpoke no more of a Chriſt within them, then curſed <hi>Cain</hi> and his poſterity did, or the old world that was drowned, or <hi>Sodom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe wicked people never ſaw no letter of Scripture, nor man, that had faith not as they knew, yet they had the ſame Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them as the Quakers have by the Law written in their hearts, and might have ſpoken in the power and ſpirit of the divine light of Chriſt as the Quakers do, had they ſeen the letter of the Scripture and men that believes them, as the Quakers do. So that it may be cleer to thoſe that have the true light of Faith, and of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the letter of the Scripture, that the Quakers principle of the light of Chriſt within them, is no other but the light of the Law written in their hearts, as the Heathen had before any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were written, and by this Law are they judged in themſelves;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:192297:41"/>
and this is their Chriſt within them, and this is that power and ſpirit, and divine light of Chriſt they could have ſpoken in, had they never ſeen letter of Scripture, nor man that profeſſeth Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that they do ſpeak now they have ſeen letter of Scripture, and men that profeſs it, and believe it, I ſay is the very ſame, for the Quakers have no more faith in the true Chriſt, then if they had never ſeen letter of Scripture, nor any man that believes them, what they have is meer traditional, even the faith of devils; for the Law written in their hearts is the onely and alone Chriſt the Quakers have to ſave them, and this Chriſt is indeed within them, and will never go out of them, but torment them to eternity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fox <hi>gives glory to his God and Chriſt within him, who hath as he ſaith, ſet him and other Quakers above that curſe and ſentence I have paſſed upon them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur glory to your God and Chriſt within you will fail you in the day of trouble, neither will, nor can deliver you from that curſe and ſentence I have paſſed upon you, and others of your brethren; neither will you ever be ſet above it, but ſhall be kept under it to eternity: flatter your ſelf as much as you can, you ſhall not be delivered, neither by your Chriſt within you, nor by the true Chriſt without you, this I know.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fox <hi>blames me for ſaying God hath made me Judge of the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſpiritual eſtate, and yet,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou owneſt thy ſelf but a mortal man; For,</hi> ſaith Fox, <hi>the ſpiritual man judgeth all things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Did you <hi>Fox</hi> ever ſee any man condemned to die, either natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral death, or eternal death by a ſpiritual man without a body? are not all men condemned both natural and ſpiritual by mortal men like themſelves? Was not <hi>Moſes</hi> a mortal man, did not he condemn and judge many to die? he ſaid but the word, and it was done: and did not <hi>Eliah</hi> call for fire from Heaven and deſtroy two
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:192297:41"/>
Captains and their fifties? with many other ſtrange things he did whereby many were judged by him and killed, yet he was but a mortal man and ſubject to infirmity as mortal men are, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith. Again was not <hi>Peter</hi> a mortal men, and was put to death himſelf, yet he judged <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphirah</hi> his wife to death, yet a mortal man; ſo is it with every true Prophet and Meſſenger of Chriſt, he hath power to ſet life and death before men, and power to judge and condemne thoſe that rebel againſt his commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to juſtifie thoſe that yield obedience unto it; yet all Gods Meſſengers they were mortal men, now theſe mortal men had great power being commiſſionated of God, and they all acted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the tenor of their commiſſion, and ſome of them deſtroyed life preſently.</p>
               <p>And I am ſure if you <hi>Fox</hi> had lived in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, you would have been conſumed by him in the gainſaying of <hi>Corah,</hi> for you would have rebelled againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron,</hi> as you do now againſt <hi>John Reeve</hi> and me: but becauſe my Commiſſion is not to conſume you immediately by a natural deſtruction, you proudly vaunt your ſelf againſt the Commiſſion of the Spirit, thinking you and your Chriſt within you ſhall be able to encounter with me and my Chriſt without me: but I muſt judge according to my Commiſſion of the Spirit, and not as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Apoſtles did, to deſtroy the natural life immediately, but our commiſſion is with relation to the ſpiritual eſtate of men and women after death, and accordingly we judge, yet but mortal men, and muſt die our ſelves; this power hath God given unto me, and by vertue of this am I made Judge of the Quakers ſpiritual and eternal eſtate, what will become of many of you after death.</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying, <hi>The ſpiritual man judgeth all things,</hi> this is to be minded, that every true Meſſenger and Miniſter of Chriſt may be called a <hi>ſpiritual man,</hi> and he is ſo, becauſe he teacheth ſuch doctrine that doth comfort the ſpirits of ſome, and torment the ſpirits of others, in that it divides between the joynts and the marrow: Alſo thoſe that truly believe, may be called <hi>ſpiritual men,</hi> and can judge the ſpirits of unbelievers, becauſe they know by faith in the doctrine of the true God, that others that have not the ſame faith cannot have that peace as they have; for they know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in themſelves when they were unbelievers, they were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:192297:42"/>
God in the world, and ſo were not able to judge who were happy, and who were not; but being juſtified by faith in the true God, they have peace with God, and ſo can diſcern and judge the ſpirits of others, by what they were themſelves who were ſome time in darkneſs, but now in the light of heaven; and who ever hath this true faith in the doctrine of the true God, may be ſaid to be a <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual man,</hi> and able to judge all things that is naught in himſelf, and all the unbelief and deſpiſings of others.</p>
               <p>And ſo he judgeth all things by his faith in the true God, and in the Meſſenger God hath ſent, yet Miniſter and People are but mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal men, and muſt die, yet called by the Seed of Faith <hi>the ſpiritual man that judgeth all things, and is judged of no man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore you <hi>Fox</hi> ſhall never have any ſpiritual man to judge you to eternal damnation, but me that am but a mortal man, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall you ſee any other God or Judge, but that ſentence that I have given upon you in this life, do you ſee if you can get over it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Fox</hi> blames me for ſaying the ſpirit of reaſon in man is the devil, and ſeems to juſtifie the Magiſtrates that perſecuted me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſay they were reaſonable men. And further he blames me, becauſe I fled from the devils malice; yet <hi>Fox</hi> judgeth that if thoſe Magiſtrates had inflicted more puniſhment than Impriſonment upon me, it had bin but reaſon the devil ſtill; <hi>for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou canſt not ſay it was unreaſonableneſs in them, according to thy own ſaying.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIV. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO this I do confeſs, that thoſe Magiſtrates that perſecuted me in <hi>Darby-ſhire,</hi> and did impriſon me in <hi>Darby</hi> Goal, they were reaſonable men, and no unreaſonableneſs was found in them; for unreaſonable men are not fit to be Mayors, Aldermen, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables of Corporation-Towns; and did you ever know unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or diſtracted men, to be Miniſters of a Pariſh? Nay, they were all reaſonable men that were my enemies, and their reaſon would have led them to have puniſhed me with a greater corporal puniſhment than Impriſonment, if the Law could have done it.</p>
               <p>Nay, becauſe they were reaſonable men, they could not go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their own Law, for their malice would have reached unto death, had the Law of the Land reached unto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:192297:42"/>And that would have pleaſed you Quakers very well, for I know ſome at that time were ſorry I eſcaped ſo well, and ſo ſoon out of priſon: and I finde by the writings of <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> and yours alſo, that you are ſorry in your hearts that I eſcaped without any further puniſhment, as whipping, and the like; and this I ſay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had reaſon the devil acted in the Magiſtrates and the Prieſt ſo far in puniſhment upon me, as would have ſatisfied the deſire of you Quakers, and their own malice, yet it had been but reaſon the devil ſtill, and it would have been but the malice of the devil exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and the deſire of the devil ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>So that I do juſtifie that my perſecutors were reaſonable men, and did nothing unto me but what reaſon the devil led them unto, and I do expect no other favour from reaſonable men than what their Law will bear them out in: But this I muſt tell you, that when reaſonable men do judge rightly between man and man in things temporal, this is highly eſteemed of by me, and warrantable in the ſight of God; but for reaſonable men to meddle with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men that breaketh no temporal Law, this is altogether condemned by me, and of God alſo. But <hi>Farnſworth</hi> and <hi>Fox</hi> the Quakers reviles againſt me, becauſe I fled away from the devils malice. Indeed the firſt time I was in <hi>Darby-ſhire</hi> I did go to <hi>Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</hi> but I did not know there was any await laid for me till after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: but however, I ſhould have been glad if I could have fled away from the devils malice this ſecond time alſo; but I have open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this more large in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Neck of the Quakers broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for thoſe Magiſtrates devils that perſecuted me, I knew it was reaſon the devil in them: alſo I knew they were urged on by the Prieſt of the Pariſh, for the Prieſt did ride upon the Mayors ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit he being but low in reaſon, and ignorant of the law of reaſon, therefore it was that I paſſed the Sentence of eternal damnation upon none of my enemies in that matter, but upon the Prieſt only. His name is <hi>John Cupp,</hi> I have named him here, becauſe he is bound in that bundle of Tares amongſt the damned ſort, ſo that the Age to come may ſee him recorded amongſt the damned, as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> are in the Scriptures, by good and righteous men.</p>
               <p>But I ſee by the writings of you Quakers, that your hearts are ſorry that the Powers of the Nation doth nor puniſh me more, yet this I ſhall tell you, that I have more enemies againſt me than any
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:192297:43"/>
Quakers whatſoever; for you Quakers need ſuffer nothing by the Powers of the Nation for your doctrine, for they and you are all one in that: but you out of a voluntary will, will worſhip and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice your ſelves in meetings, contrary to the Law made by the Powers of the Nation, when as you have no Authority from God for any ſuch practice, you having no true Miniſtery no more than the Nation, ſo you bring perſecution upon your own heads through a voluntary, groundleſs ſuffering for Chriſt, when as Chriſt owns not your meetings, nor the Powers of the Nation owns them not.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould you ſuffer ſo much for a Lie? I know you will take me for your enemy to ſpeak thus; yet this I ſay, I always loved the perſecuted better than I did the perſecuter; for though men ſuffer for a Lie, yet I thought it was in the innocency of the minde, and I always had compaſſion upon the afflicted for conſcience ſake, as I have known ſome that have loſt their lives for conſcience ſake, which I have been ſorry for, though I know they ſuffered for a meer Lie, as all you Quakers do; for there is none of you doth ſuffer for truth, yet I ſay whoever doth perſecute you for conſcience in meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and worſhipping an unknown God, as you Quakers do, yet I ſay thoſe men that do perſecute you willingly, they will be every man of them damned to eternity; for that which knoweth the true God, and the true Worſhip, will never perſecute any.</p>
               <p>Though we know their worſhip to be falſe, but men that are falſe worſhippers themſelves, will perſecute both the falſe worſhippers and the true; this I do know by experience, in that men have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted me onely for going upon the account of a Prophet, but glad would they have been if they could have catcht me under any Law the Powers of the nation had made, but they could not; therfore the Judge ſaid to my Accuſers, that Bill of Accuſation it did not belong to the Law, ſo the Judge could not determine no Sentence upon me; likewiſe the Judge cleared me himſelf in his own Chamber, likewiſe I juſtified the ſame things I was accuſed of to the Judges face. The Judge was hot at firſt, he not knowing I was the man, ſaid to my friend that was with me, <hi>it was not fit ſuch a man as I ſhould live.</hi> With that I asked the Judge why he ſaid ſo? Do not you read in the writing what you are accuſed of? I ſaid, I read what I am accuſed of, but what is it ſay you, that I am not fit to live? Why, ſaith the Judge, are you the man? I ſaid Yes. So the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:192297:43"/>
Judge took the Paper out of my hand, and read the Articles of my Accuſation: what ſay you to this, ſaith he? So one by one he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me: ſo I anſwered him to every one diſtinct of it ſelf; ſo when the Judge had heard my anſwer, he ſaid it was well, and freed me from going to <hi>Darby</hi> Goal any more.</p>
               <p>But this is that I would have the Reader minde, that if I had been taken in a Meeting, as the Quakers are, then the Judge would have had the Law on his ſide; and all other things I was accuſed of, as blaſphemy, and how I had power to damn and to ſave, and that I was one of the two Witneſſes ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and that their believing the Scriptures now they were damn'd by me, would do them no good; theſe, with ſuch like things, were given in againſt me, I ſay all things would have been ſwallowed up in one meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the Judge would have took up that Law, and would have given Judgement and Sentence upon me, as he did to Baptiſts and Quakers in my ſight, onely for meeting contrary to the Act.</p>
               <p>Therefore if you Quakers would forbear meeting, you need not ſuffer for your faith at all, and if you would be ruled by me, or take my adviſe not to meet at all, for I am ſorry that many innocent, harmleſs people ſhould waſte their eſtates, ſuffer Impriſonment, and impoveriſh their health, and ſuffer baniſhment, and ſo bring their lives to an end before their time, for that which is not truth.</p>
               <p>For you do but imitate other mens Commiſſion and practice, ſo that you are traditional people as all other Churches are; for if you do not meet contrary to the Law, you need not ſuffer the loſs of a groat for your Faith, nor your Chriſt within you; for the Powers of the Nation are of your minde as to your doctrine, the Pope will agree with you as to that, but all the ſtrife amongſt you is about Diſcipline, this I am very ſenſible of.</p>
               <p>Therefore I never rejoyced, nor deſired the ſufferings of the Quakers for their meetings, though I knew they ſuffered for a Lie, yet I always pittied them when they were impriſoned and baniſhed for meeting, though I know they rejoyced at my Impriſonment, and were ſorry there was not worſe puniſhment inflicted upon me; the truth of this is clear by the writings of <hi>Richard Farnſworth</hi> and <hi>George Fox,</hi> and other Quakers that I know, who juſtified the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in what they did unto me, and thinks the Magiſtrates might have puniſhed me worſe if they would; but I know they would
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:192297:44"/>
not have ſpared me ſo much as they do the Quaker, had they had the Law on their ſide as they have againſt the Quakers. But no more of that here</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Fox</hi> calls me a lying ſpirit becauſe I ſay it doth not belong to Chriſt now being in heaven, to interpret Scripture; <hi>Yet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, doth not the Scripture ſay all ſhall be taught of God? and that he opens, and no man ſhuts? And doth not</hi> John <hi>ſay, No man was found worthy to open the Book but the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Judah? <hi>And was not Chriſt anointed to preach?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> ANSWER.</head>
               <p>HEre the Reader may ſee the ignorance of <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker, and all the reſt of them, of the true meaning of the Scriptures; alſo I ſhall make it appear to thoſe that have any true light in them, that the interpretation of Scripture doth not belong unto Chriſt now, nor never did, but it belongs onely unto ſuch men as he ſends, and hath given them the gift, as thus:</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> was a man, and did not he interpret unto his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Iſraelites in <hi>Egypt,</hi> the ſayings of God unto him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their deliverance out of that bondage? Did not <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> interpret, and ſhew ſigns and wonders in <hi>Egypt</hi> of thoſe things God had revealed and made known unto them? Was not theſe men that did this?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Was not <hi>Joſeph</hi> a man, that did interpret his own dreams, and the dreams of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler and Baker, and <hi>Pharaohs</hi> own dream? Will you, <hi>Fox,</hi> ſay it was God that did interpret <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dream? was it not <hi>Joſeph</hi> a man like himſelf, therefore promoted to great honor?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Was not <hi>Daniel</hi> a man, that did interpret the King of <hi>Babylons</hi> dreams? Did God interpret the Kings dreams, or <hi>Daniel</hi> that was a man? did not thoſe Kings of <hi>Babylon</hi> promote <hi>Daniel</hi> to honor, in that the Spirit of the Holy Gods had given a man ſuch wiſdom and underſtanding to interpret Dreams, Viſions, and hard Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences? all this was done by a mortal man, and not by God himſelf.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Was not the Prophets mortal men, and not God? yet they did interpret to the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> the councel of the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> what he would do if they would not forſake their ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:192297:44"/>
and turn unto the worſhip of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he would make them deſolate? yet theſe Prophets were but men, and not God. Though <hi>Eliah</hi> did call for fire from heaven, and deſtroyed two Captains and their fifties, and fire to burn up the Sacrifice in the ſight of the people, and deſtroyed four hundred of <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts, and ſhut the heavens that it rained not, yet he was but a man, it was not God himſelf that the King would, or did ſeek after to kill him, it was a man like himſelf.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> when he unfolded and interpreted the Councel of God, that other Prophets had foretold of concerning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Zedekiah?</hi> was it God himſelf that did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret it to the King, or was it <hi>Jeremiah</hi> a mortal man, or no?</p>
               <p>So all the Prophets little or much, gave interpretations of the Councel of God concerning <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they were all but men, and were not the people of the Jews bound to believe thoſe men whom God ſent, except God would come himſelf? Why then doth the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſay, <hi>Who hath believed our report? or to whom is the arm of the Lord revealed?</hi> His meaning is this, whoſoever doth believe we that are Prophets ſent of God: believe but our report, and you ſhall know the true God, the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the ſtrength of his arm, to ſave and deliver you from your ſins: but except ye believe our report who are men like your ſelves, the arm of Gods ſaving health will never be revealed unto you, for God will not do it by himſelf, but by us his Meſſengers, who are men, will his arm of ſalvation be revealed unto, if you believe our report.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Was not <hi>Philip</hi> a man that did interpret that ſaying in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet, which the Eunuch read <hi>Act.</hi> 8.32. <hi>He was led as a ſheep to the ſlaughter, and like a lamb dumb before the ſhearer, ſo opened he not his mouth.</hi> Here <hi>Philip</hi> ran to the Charret, and asked the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandeſt thou what thou readeſt?</hi> as verſe 30 mark: Said the Eunuch, <hi>How can I, except ſome man guide me?</hi> Here you may ſee that the Eunuch did not expect that God himſelf ſhould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture unto him: but, ſaith he, how ſhall I know the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scripture, except ſome man guide me? that is, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome man interpret it to me, as the words doth imply; for <hi>Philip</hi> opened thoſe ſayings unto him which made the Eunuch to underſtand, and believe, and be baptiſed.</p>
               <p>Now will you <hi>Fox</hi> ſay that Chriſt himſelf did interpret this
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:192297:45"/>
Scripture to the Eunuch, or did it belong to a mortal man? I think you will not be ſo groſly ignorant, to ſay that Chriſt himſelf went into the Eunuchs Charret, and interpreted thoſe Scriptures to him; Surely if the interpretation of Scripture had belonged onely unto Chriſt, and not unto man, as <hi>Fox</hi> doth aſſert, then Chriſt muſt have come from heaven, and have went into the Charret in <hi>Philips</hi> ſtead, becauſe <hi>Philip</hi> was a man, and interpretation of Scripture doth not belong to man, as <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker ſaith.</p>
               <p>May not any man that hath but the light of ſenſe and reaſon in his underſtanding, ſee the groſs darkneſs of theſe Quakers, which pretends to be in the cleareſt light of all the ſeven Churches, but to my knowledge the darkeſt of all in point of doctrine.</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying of Scripture, <hi>We ſhall be all taught of God,</hi> it is not meant that God will teach every particular man and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man himſelf; do you <hi>Fox</hi> believe ſo? why then do you prattle to the people when you meet, as if you would interpret the meaning of Scripture, and teach the people the knowledge of Chriſt, for you are but a man? why do not you let Chriſt teach the people himſelf, ſeeing you will have all taught of God, and allow no man to interpret Scripture, nor teach the people? For if you ſay Chriſt doth interpret Scripture, and not <hi>Muggleton,</hi> becauſe <hi>Muggleton</hi> is a man, and the interpretation of Scripture you ſay belongs to Chriſt, and not to <hi>Muggleton,</hi> for <hi>Muggleton</hi> is but a man, ſo Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers are all taught of God, and not by man.</p>
               <p>I marvel why there is ſo many Men-teachers amongſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, ſeeing teaching knowledge of heavenly things, and the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of Scripture belongeth to God and Chriſt, and not to man! If I were of your faith, I would give over teaching and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Scriptures, and leave it to God and Chriſt to whom it doth, and it would be well for you Speakers of the Quakers, if you had done ſo before you took upon you to preach Chriſt within you; you have undertook to teach that which you ſay God will do, and to interpret Scripture, which you ſay doth belong unto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But I ſee all thoſe people that will be taught of God, and have the Scriptures interpreted unto them by Chriſt himſelf, and will not receive the interpretation from man, I ſay thoſe people are more ignorant and dark in their mindes, than thoſe that are taught by man.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:192297:45"/>And I am ſure the Quakers people would have known more truth if they had been taught by man that hath a Commiſſion from God, as <hi>Reeve</hi> and <hi>Muggleton</hi> hath, than they do by all that God ever taught them in their lives.</p>
               <p>And the Interpretation of Scripture we have given, if under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, would have informed their Judgements more than all the Interpretation of Scripture that Chriſt ever did interpret unto the Quakers people ſince the name of Quakers was put upon them, yet we are but mortal men, and muſt die.</p>
               <p>But to clear the ſcruple that may ariſe in mens mindes, becauſe I ſpeak thus, I ſhall ſhew in a few words how men may be ſaid to be taught of God, and how the Interpretation of Scripture may be ſaid to belong unto Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when God chuſeth any one man, or more, to be his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Prophet, Meſſenger, or Miniſter, God doth furniſh ſuch with wiſdom, and underſtanding, and revelation, to declare the minde of God to the people, what God would have the people do, and look how many people, or who ever doth believe this Meſſenger ſent of God, they may be ſaid to be taught of God, and are taught of God.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe he that hath the gift of Interpretation of Scripture, as Prophets, Apoſtles, and we the Witneſſes of the Spirit hath, our Interpretation of Scripture may be ſaid to belong unto Chriſt, and that it is the true Interpretation of Chriſt himſelf, becauſe we had our Commiſſion from him to teach the people, and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Scripture to as many as believe us, to their great peace and ſatisfaction of their ſouls: And in this ſenſe people may truely ſay they are all taught of God, and that Chriſt hath given the true interpretation of Scripture by his ſervants the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Witneſſes of the Spirit, to our everlaſting peace and comfort, yet all this is declared by men, yea by mortal men, and not by Chriſt himſelf, as the Quakers do vainly imagine.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Alſo <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt opens and no man ſhuts:</hi> and ſaith, <hi>Doth not</hi> John <hi>ſay, No man was found worthy to open the Book, but the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Judah? And ſaith, <hi>Was not Chriſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed to preach?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:192297:46"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVI. <hi>ANSWER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis beareth the ſame ſence as the other, whatſoever the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Apoſtles and Witneſſes of the Spirit doth, it may be ſaid Chriſt doth it, as the Prophets they preached of Balm in <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> and of Eye-ſalve to anoynt the peoples eyes, that they might ſee what did belong to their peace, and where they might have ſalve to heal the wound in conſcience, which ſin had made in their ſouls, this is called the preaching of Chriſt by his Prophets.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Apoſtles had power given them by Chriſt to open the eyes of the blinde, and to give light unto them that were in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in the ſhadow of death, and brought thoſe that believed their doctrine into the light of life eternal. Alſo they had the Keys of Heaven and of Hell, to bind ſin upon the conſciences of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers never to be forgiven, and to looſe the ſins of thoſe that did truely believe their doctrine of Chriſt; and thus they did open the Book of conſcience in the believer, and no man could ſhut up that conſcience which the Apoſtles doctrine opened; neither could any man open that conſcience the Apoſtles ſhut up in unbelief: This alſo is called the preaching of Chriſt, and opening and ſhutting the Book of Conſcience by Chriſt, yet this was done by men and not by Chriſt himſelf; But in regard they did preach the Goſpel by vertue of Authority from Chriſt, and they were anointed by him to preach the everlaſting Goſpel, and had power given them to open the Book of Conſcience in ſome, whereby they did believe in Chriſt, and ſhut the conſcience of others up in unbelief; and thus that ſaying of the Scripture is fulfilled, that Chriſt was anoynted to preach the Goſpel of glad tidings of ſalvation; for what his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers doth, it is as if he did it himſelf.</p>
               <p>Again, we the Witneſſes of the Spirit are anoynted and choſen of Chriſt to preach the everlaſting Goſpel, and Chriſt hath given us power to ſet life and death before men, and we have power to binde and looſe, and to open and ſhut the Book of Conſcience, and no man can ſhut that conſcience we have opened, neither can any man open that conſcience we have ſhut up in darkneſs as to any ſpiritual knowledge or true peace: this many can witneſs on
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:192297:46"/>
both ſides, if they would, but our other writings doth ſpeak more large of this point; ſo I ſhall ſay no more as to this.</p>
               <p>Onely this, that this power we the Witneſſes of the Spirit have is the power of Chriſt, as the Prophets and Apoſtles power was in their time, therefore ſaid to be done by Chriſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>But I know <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker is willing to believe that dead Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles were Meſſengers of Chriſt, but he doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there is any ſent of Chriſt not alive, but what is within them, but he ſhall find that we the Witneſſes of the Spirit were ſent of God, and have as great power given us, as any Prophet or Apoſtle whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And as for that ſaying of <hi>John, Revelation</hi> 5. <hi>That no man in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor in Earth, nor under the Earth, was able to open the Book, but the Lion of the Tribe of Judah.</hi> This I would have the Reader to minde, for it is a vain thing to talk to Quakers of interpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by man, that is alive; but <hi>John</hi> that ſpake theſe words being dead, the Quakers believe his words, though they know nothing what he meant, nor what that Book was that none could open but Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This let the Reader minde, that there is three Books that are to be opened by Chriſt, as you may ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.20. <hi>And the Books were opened, and another book was opened, which is the Book of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to give the Reader to underſtand theſe three Books, the firſt Book is the Law written in mans heart, this Book are all the Heathen are to be judged by, when it is opened at the great day of the Lord. The ſecond Book is the Conſcience of people who hath heard the preaching of Faith in Chriſt, yet did not believe, when this Book is opened they ſhall be judged at that great day in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for their unbelief. The third Book is the Book of Life, wherein all true believers Faith is written, and according to their works of faith they are judged, and ſo according to the works of unbelief, are judged, and according to the works of reaſon, their thoughts accuſing, ſhall the Heathen be judged according to what is written.</p>
               <p>In theſe Books ſhall all people be judged both ſmall and great.</p>
               <p>Mind and look what judgement Gods Meſſengers hath given unto men in this life, the ſame will Chriſt give when he doth raiſe them again at the laſt day, as I have ſaid before, therefore this Book
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:192297:47"/>
which no man in Heaven nor in Earth could open, it was the Book of Life, and none was found worthy to open the Book of Life but Chriſt, he being the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah.</hi> This Book of Life muſt needs belong to Chriſt to open, and to no man elſe; for he is God the firſt and the laſt, the beginning and the end of all mankind; but what is this to interpret Scripture? Chriſt hath given that to man: but I have opened theſe things more large in <hi>the Interpretation of the whole Book of the Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the laſt place I ſhall ſay ſomething as to the Quakers principle &amp; practice: <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith in the end of his Pamphlet againſt me, <hi>that I am judged with the Spirit of Truth; and over me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fox, is the true and Faithful witneſs Chriſt Jeſus the Corner-ſtone, which will grind me to powder.</hi> Further <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>in Chriſt is his people, meaning the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, that reign over my head, that can raiſe and reign over the head of the curſer: and Fox</hi> ſaith, <hi>Edward Bourn whom thou haſt curſt and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who is far above thee and thy Father, in him that redeems out of the curſe, and deſtroys thee and thy Father both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do acknowledge that Chriſt Jeſus the Faithful Witneſs, the Corner-ſtone, ſhould grinde me to powder if he doth not own me to be ſent of him; if I do curſe any without a commiſſion from him, or if I ſhould curſe any of the true Chriſts people, then let that curſe be upon my own head, as <hi>Fox</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>Alſo I was always willing that thoſe people that were ingrafted into Chriſt by Faith, ſhould be above me; for there is no people in Chriſt but ſuch as are ingrafted into him by faith, which I am ſure no Quaker is as in that ſtate, neither can any man be a member of Chriſt but by the hearing of Faith, <hi>and faith comes by hearing, how can any preach the word of faith except he be ſent?</hi> as I am ſure no Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker never was ſent of Chriſt to preach, therefore no Quakers peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But that Chriſt the Quakers people are in, I that am a man hath power over ſome, I have ſeparated their Chriſt from them one from the other, and hath ſhewed them the true Chriſt to their great ſatisfaction, and they have bin glad they were rid of the Quakers Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Others again hath bin condemned by me, both them and their Chriſt, neither would I let them and their Chriſt part one from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, but torment each other; for this Chriſt the Quakers hath
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:192297:47"/>
in them, is the Law written in their hearts, and the Chriſt the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker people are in, is the motions of this Law, and ſometimes they do well, then the Law is quiet in them, and their Chriſt giveth peace to them; ſo I knowing this Chriſt was born with man, and man born with it, as the Apoſtle ſaith, being under the Law then free from grace.</p>
               <p>But being born again, we are not under the Law but under Grace, but the Quakers people are under the Law, though not the outward letter, as the people of the Jews were, yet they are under the Law written in their hearts, as the Heathen were before any Law was given; and this is the Quakers Chriſt within them, and that Chriſt they are in; ſo that Chriſt the only God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen me, and hath given me power over the Quakers Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them and themſelves alſo, to keep them together, ſo that the one ſhall not part from the other; for though they ſhall deſire that this Chriſt within them might part from them, but it will not, but torment their ſouls to eternity; This will be <hi>Fox</hi> the Quakers por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and many more Quakers beſides, and if you <hi>Edward Bourn</hi> and others of the Quakers, whom I have curſed, do get over, or above that curſe and ſentence I have paſſed upon you, let your righteouſneſs be what it will, I ſay then <hi>Cain</hi> ſhall get above, and over that curſe God himſelf pronounced upon him, and ſo ſhall <hi>Judas</hi> get above that curſe Chriſt pronounced upon him.</p>
               <p>Furthermore; if you Quakers were not wilfully ignorant and blinde, you might ſee that this commiſſion of the Spirit given to <hi>John Reeve</hi> and <hi>Muggleton</hi> hath had great power over the Ranters and Quakers, it hath broken the Ranters principle all to pieces, ſo that none dares hold up an argument to defend it, you Quakers alſo are very much ſhattered, you are not like the people ye were 16 years ago, this ſome that had a love for you have ſeen &amp; confeſt.</p>
               <p>The Ranters when we came out firſt ſixten years ago, were very high in their elevations, in ſeeing of viſions, and going forth as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Propheteſſes, and ſtripping themſelves naked for ſigns, as you Quakers have done, I can make it appear in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, that this commiſſion hath had great power over Ranters and Quakers; for the heads of theſe two were <hi>John Robins</hi> and <hi>John Taney; Robins</hi> was the head of all falſe Chriſts, falſe Prophets, Propheteſſes, Shakers, and Quakers, and you Quakers are but the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:192297:48"/>
ſpawn of <hi>John Robins,</hi> and that Chriſt you own within you being a falſe Chriſt, <hi>John Robins</hi> was the head of that principle alſo; his believers had thoſe witchcraft-fits upon them, as you Quakers had very ſtrongly at that time, when <hi>John Robins</hi> was in power; alſo <hi>John Taney</hi> was the head of the Atheiſtical Ranters, &amp; thoſe Ranters were very high in their language, and vile in their practiſe as to oppreſſe one another, deflower Virgins, commit whoredome with mens wives, and counted all the wickedneſs they did to be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, theſe things and much more did thoſe people do, and theſe two heads were in great power when we came firſt out; and the firſt man that was curſed by us after we had power, was <hi>John Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins,</hi> after that divers of his Prophets were curſt, and in two months time after <hi>John Rob'ins</hi> power fell, and all his Prophets and Propheteſſes fel with him, ſo he and they moultered away like dirt, and none durſt acknowledge any faith in <hi>John Robins,</hi> neither could they attain any Witchcraft-fits any more, ſo that <hi>John Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins,</hi> and his Prophets and people are layd aſide as if they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been.</p>
               <p>Afterwards it came to paſs, that <hi>John Taney</hi> was damned by us, becauſe he would not lay down the Prieſt-hood, and his <hi>Jeruſalem Journey,</hi> he had witchcraft-fits alſo, and would ſhut up himſelf nine days to produce them, but could not after he was curſt, ſo after few years he fell, and all his great matters to nothing, ſo that not one of his hearers can tell what became of him. Likewiſe we did paſſe Sentence on ſeveral of the Ranters Miniſters, as of them themſelves, ſo that they all tumbled down headlong, and could not riſe again to this day.</p>
               <p>Now do you <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker call to minde, and ſee whether this curſe <hi>Reeve</hi> and <hi>Muggleton</hi> hath not been over the Quakers people, nor touched them? there hath a many Quakers been curſt by us, but eſpecially of late years by me; have you your ſelf <hi>Edward Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, Francis Hougal,</hi> you three were the firſt Quakers <hi>John Reeve</hi> damned? have you three had any witchcraft-fits ſince? have you foamed at the mouth, &amp; ſwollen in your belly with the workings of the ſpirit? and as you think as if you had the Falling-ſickneſs? have you had any new viſion, or new revelation in thoſe witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft-fits ſince, yea or nay?</p>
               <p>I am ſure it hath great power over you Quakers; and hath put
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:192297:48"/>
a ſtop to thoſe witchcraft-fits; for I do not hear of any Quaker of late that hath any, though they were never curſt by me: this curſe hath run in the line of the heads of the Quakers, ſo that it doth put a ſtop to the whole body; ſo that none of the members can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a witchcraft-fit; nay, the Quakers are bereft of all revelation now, and Meſſages to the Magiſtrates; they have left off ſtripping themſelves naked, and imitating the Prophets of old.</p>
               <p>Do you <hi>Fox</hi> own that practiſe of <hi>Solomon Ecle</hi> the Quaker? I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by a paſſage in your book you do, becauſe <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did ſo, as a ſign to the Jews, but your Prophet <hi>Solomon Ecle</hi> went in a more ſhameleſs manner, being ſent by the ſpirit of witchcraft, then <hi>Iſaiah</hi> did that was ſent of God; for <hi>Ecle</hi> went ſtark naked, as is reported at <hi>Aldermanbury</hi> Church, and not onely ſo but he was ſhamleſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhit, ſo that none could lay hands on him, onely the Coachmans whip gave him a jerk or two: this is he that went with fire upon his head in <hi>Bartholomew-fair,</hi> alſo he ſowed his linings upon the peoples Communion-table to prophane it at <hi>Aldermary</hi> Church; theſe things were very brief formerly with the Ranters and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers people, they were much for ſigns, though ſome of them were very beaſty ſigns; yet the Ranters and Quakers were well pleaſed with them, being moved thereunto by the ſpirit of witchcraft, to imitate Prophets of old in a more ſhameleſs manner.</p>
               <p>As I could tell you ſome things of the Ranters practiſe, who would go forth as ſigns: there was one his name was <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> he was the Ranters ſign, yet pretended to be a ſign of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Miniſtery, that as he did ſtink in the noſtrils of people, ſo ſhould they; for he went always beſhit, ſo he was called <hi>Shitten Nat;</hi> he eat his own dung, and ſtank that none would come nigh him; nay miſtreſs <hi>Cook</hi> a Ranter would lye with him in the fields and make cakes of his dung for him to eat, and he did eat his own dung; but whether ſhe did eat any with him, I cannot tell; but it was ſaid ſhe did: now this ſign goeth beyond the Quaker <hi>Solomon Ecle.</hi> Alſo this miſtreſs <hi>Cook</hi> ſhe went to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Church to ſhew the Miniſter a ſign, ſhe ſtript her ſelf ſtark naked, and went into the Church; ſo ſome threw a cloak over her to cover her nakedneſs, and ſhe was committed to <hi>Bride-well,</hi> and there ſhe was clothed all in white linnen like the Queen of Heaven; theſe were Ranting ſigns now for you Quakers to imitate; many ſuch things were acted
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:192297:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by that ſort of people; as that <hi>John Thomas</hi> who danced naked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir <hi>Richard Brown</hi> as he went to the Church, and being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by him, was extreamly whipped, and when he had ſuffered, and was out of priſon poyſoned himſelf, <hi>Richard Ruſel</hi> the Quakers wife can witneſs the truth of his nakedneſs before Sir <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> for ſhe went on one ſide, and another woman on the other, they were both impriſoned with him; many more of thoſe Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters came to a ſad end, for moſt of them fell to nothing after their head <hi>John Taney</hi> did fall, and their principle doth ſtink in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of all civil people, even as he did that was the true ſign to that ſort of people, for he ſtank in the noſtrils of all that came neer him, he could hot endure himſelf, nay he killed himſelf with the wyer of a candleſtick, thruſt it into his belly, and ſo died: do you <hi>George Fox</hi> approve of ſuch ſhitten ſhameleſs Prophets, and ſtinking ſigns as theſe? how much difference is there in <hi>Solomon Ecle</hi> his ſign being a Quaker, then in the Ranters? are not you Quakers almoſt aſhamed of your Prophets ſigns? theſe things hath bin pretty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon amongſt Quakers heretofore, when the ſpirit of witchcraft reigned in them; but now the power of witchcraft-fits is ſubdued by <hi>Reeve</hi> and <hi>Muggletons</hi> commiſſion, neither ſhall you Quakers whom I have curſed get above, nor over that curſe I have paſſed upon you, for it ſhall be upon your perſons and over the heads of your ſouls to eternity, and none ſhall deliver you from it.</p>
               <p>Thus much in anſwer to <hi>George Fox</hi> his printed Pamphlet.</p>
            </div>
            <byline>
               <hi>By</hi> Lodwick Muggleton.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:192297:49"/>
            <head>Here followeth the Copy of a LETTER ſent to <hi>SARAH COPPIN,</hi> Quaker.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sarah Coppin,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu may remember about fourteen years ago, in the year 1653. that you did ſeem to receive <hi>John Reeve</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton</hi> as Meſſengers and Prophets of the Lord, or as Witneſſes of the Spirit; and further you did ſhew much kindneſs unto us upon that account, for there could be no other inducement in us at that time to invite any to ſhew kindneſs unto us, but that doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by us concerning the true God, as our writings did declare, which you did ſeem to own. Alſo you may remember your great zeal you had for us when we were priſoners in <hi>Old-Bridewel,</hi> your zeal carried you out ſo far for us to deliver a Writing of ours unto <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> who was then choſen Lord Protector; this you did your ſelf in zeal and love to this Commſſiion of the Spirit, as we the Witneſſes of the Spirit thought, and I ſuppoſe your ſelf did think what you did in that kinde, it was in ſincerity of heart alſo, and we took it ſo, and had a love for you as to your eternal happineſs; but your faith was not truely grounded, neither upon the doctrine of the true God, nor the Commiſſion of the Spirit, as it is manifeſt ſince. Alſo you may remember one <hi>Joan Biſhop</hi> a maid, that was the occaſion of bringing you acquainted with us; and that you had been very religiouſly given before you met with us, even ſo much that you were almoſt diſtracted about your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, in that none of the Preachers of the Nation could ſhew you the way to reſt for your ſoul, they having no true reſt themſelves; yet you may remember your receiving us upon that account as Prophets of the Lord, who had put down <hi>John Taney, John Robins,</hi> and many others that went as prophets and propheteſſes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended great revelations and viſions from the Lord, and yet knew not what God is: theſe all have been brought down by us the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Spirit, theſe things you know in part.</p>
            <p>Alſo your acquaintance with us, it cured you of that diſtracted condition you were in before you knew us, and you were clothed
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:192297:50"/>
in your right minde, and was able to give a ſenſible Anſwer to any that did oppoſe you: but I know you cannot do ſo now you are turned to the Quakers, though you are become a Speaker amongſt them. I know your pride, and ambition of your heart that loveth to be eſteemed of people: what, a Woman-preacher! you think this to be a great glory to you, but the greateſt ſhame that poſſible may be will be the effects of it; for it is not your many ſenſleſs ſpeeches without form or order produced by a witchcraft ſpirit within you, which you call the light of Chriſt; I ſay this you have gloried in will be your endleſs ſhame, for your latter end will be worſe than your beginning, for you are become an abſolute Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, who hath back-ſlided and fallen from the truth, and turned to the Quakers, the moſt Antichriſtian Principle of all the ſeven Churches, and the greateſt fighters againſt a perſonal God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out man, of any, ſo that you are an abſolute Apoſtate, and impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be renewed by repentance; for you are fallen from truth to a lie, for you are as ſome were in the Apoſtles time, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 3 6. who were enlightened, and had taſted of the good word of God, and the powers of the life to come, that is, they were enlightened by the Commiſſion of the Goſpel committed to them to preach, they taſted that good word of God, even the doctrine of Chriſt, which was life and ſalvation to them that truly believed: But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming believers taſted of this good word of God which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles preached and rejoyced in it for a ſeaſon, as <hi>Herod</hi> did; and as for the powers of the life to come, they had peace in their minds and hope of eternal life by the Apoſtles doctrine, ſo long as they ſtood by faith, but when they fell away from that faith they once profeſt, they could not be renewed again by repentance, ſo that all that light and word of God they taſted of, and peace, and hope, which is the powers of the life to come, it all withered and dyed within them, ſo that they were not ſenſible of the light of heaven, nor any goodneſs of Gods word they preacht, nor any peace, or hope they ever found by owning the Apoſtles doctrine; ſo it is with you as it was with thoſe apoſtates that did fall away from the Apoſtles Commiſſion after they had made a profeſſion to own and believe it, and had received many refreſhments in their mindes, and had taſted of the Joys of Heaven, but in that they did fall from it to ſome other opinion, as to the worſhip of the Law, as the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:192297:50"/>
did who were bewitched, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, ſo that their latter end was worſe than their beginning. For before a man joyn with truth, though he doth not believe it for the preſent, yet it is poſſible he may be renewed in his minde, and come afterwards to believe and be ſaved; but if any ſhall profeſs truth, and rejoyce in it for a ſeaſon, and afterwards fall away, it is impoſſible for ſuch an one to be renewed by repentance, as aforeſaid; And this is your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for you rejoyced in this Commiſſion of the Spirit for a ſeaſon, and did many good acts for us, which did manifeſt that you had a love for this Declaration of <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf, and yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to fall away from the belief of it, and not onely ſo, but to ſpeak evil of us the Witneſſes of the Spirit, In that you ſaid you knew <hi>John Reeve,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> very well, and that we were the greateſt Deceivers that ever was, and that as ſoon as ever you met with Truth, meaning the Quakers, then you forſook us; theſe, with ſuch like words, and more than I mention here, did you ſay, which is clear to me that you are not onely fallen from grace, but you have trampled the blood of the Covenant under foot, and counted it an unholy thing, even that whereby you ſhould have been ſanctified by faith; had you held out to the end, you ſhould have been ſaved by this Commiſſion of the Spirit; for there is no ſalvation under heaven to be found in theſe days, but in the belief of this Commiſſion of the Spirit given of God to <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf: for our Commiſſion is as true as the Apoſtles Commiſſion was at that time, and we as true Prophets as they were Apoſtles; ſo that whoever ſhall make a profeſſion of this, and fall away after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and ſpeak evil of that they once owned, I ſay they trample the blood of the Covenant under foot now, as they did in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, and do count that an unholy thing that ſhould have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them the aſſurance of everlaſting life; but it is impoſſible for ſuch to return to the truth again. And this I muſt tell you, a man cannot properly be ſaid to fall away, but when men and women fall from a Commiſſion; for we ſee many people fall oft from one profeſsion of Religion to another, as from Baptiſts to Quakers, and Independents to Baptiſts, and Quakers fall from that Principle to others, and ſome to Atheiſm, yet this is not properly a falling away, becauſe there is no true Prophet or Miniſtery amongſt them all, not in the whole world; ſo that to my knowledge many hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:192297:51"/>
from one thing to another, and at laſt have come to be ſaved by this Commiſsion of the Spirit, and have had aſſurance of eternal life in themſelves, notwithſtanding their falling from ſeveral forms of worſhip; but who ever falls from the Commiſsion of God, there can be no return again, neither can they poſsibly be ſaved; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought it convenient to let you know what will be the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of your fall. I have been in this Commiſsion theſe ſixteen years, and I never knew but four perſons that did fall which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to own us, your ſelf is one, and a Scotch woman, <hi>Alexander Hails</hi> his wife, ſhe fell to the Quakers as ſoon as we were put in <hi>Newgate,</hi> for indeed ſhe was very poor, and we being in priſon could not ſupply her with loaves no longer, there being but very few that did believe at that time, ſo ſhe did fall to the Quakers and forſook us; for I ſuppoſe the Quakers had more loaves amongſt them, for they were many; for a loaf of bread was the greateſt religion ſhe had in her, for ſhe was for <hi>John Robins</hi> his people ſo long as he could maintain them with the ſtock he got from them, but when that was ſpent, ſhe did fall from him and his people alſo. The third perſon was Miſtreſs <hi>Langley,</hi> the fourth was <hi>John Hide</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller; theſe all ſeemed to own the doctrine of this Commiſsion of the Spirit, and pleaded much for it, and rejoyced for a ſeaſon in it. This Miſtreſs <hi>Langley</hi> did fall to the Quakers as you have done, but a woful effect did follow upon it, even diſtractedneſs of brain, a waſting of her eſtate, an endeavor to kill her ſelf, a fugitive, and vagabond condition in this world, beſides her damnation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Now I have ſhewed you what a dangerous thing it is to fall from commiſſionated men to non-commiſſionated men, and what a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing it is for men or women to exerciſe the offices of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching without a Commiſſion from God, or from him whom God ſends; therefore I ſhall ſay theſe words as followeth, I have heard of your being a Quaker theſe many years, ſo I let you alone as to that, but of late I hear that you are a Speaker among the Quakers meetings, and that you knew <hi>John Reeve</hi> and my ſelf, and did keep company with us, until you met with Truth, the Quakers princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you call Truth; Alſo you ſaid we were the greateſt Deceivers that ever was; and you ſaid rather than you would return again unto us, you would go to the publick, and hear the Prieſts of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:192297:51"/>
Nation; theſe things I have weighed and conſidered, firſt your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting and back-ſliding from that you once rejoyced in: and ſeI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>condly, in that you have ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt, and have contemptuouſly ſpoken evil of the Commiſſion of the Spirit, in calling it the greateſt Deceit that ever was, in this you have tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled the pureſt Truth that ever was, under your feet as an unholy thing, and as a ſcorn; Therefore for theſe things aforeſaid, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to my Commiſſion from God, I do pronounce <hi>Sarah Coppin</hi> Quaker, curſed and damned both in ſoul and body from the preſence of God, elect men, and Angels to eternity, and it will be a marvellous thing if you eſcape a fugitive and vagabond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in this life, beſides your damnation hereafter; for ſins of this nature hath commonly a double curſe follow, as it did with Miſtreſs <hi>Langley:</hi> I had no hatred in my heart to you at all in this thing, but in obedience to my Commiſſion I have done this, that you might not go to hell in a ſleep, but that you may know what it is to deſpiſe the laſt Meſſengers of the Spirit of God, and that the Age to come may ſee and read this Letter, and may fear to do as you have done.</p>
            <trailer>I was informed of ſome of theſe things by one <hi>John Clark</hi> a Tanner, <date>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 14. 1667.</date>
            </trailer>
            <byline>Written by <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> one of the two laſt Prophets and Witneſſes of the Spirit, unto the high and mighty God, the Man Chriſt Jeſus in glory.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:192297:52"/>
            <head>Another <hi>LETTER</hi> ſent to <hi>RICHARD CHAIR</hi> Quaker, as followeth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Richard Chair,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am informed by one <hi>Francis Newel</hi> that you have reported very baſe lies of me in the temporal; and not only ſo, but you have blaſphemed againſt the Holy Ghoſt, as moſt of you Quakers do, and that without a cauſe, for I do not remember I ever had any diſcourſe with you, nor no dealings with you, neither temporal, nor ſpiritual; neither do I know you if I ſhould ſee you, and it is very like you do not know me if you ſhould ſee me, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you have reported that you knew me in <hi>Trinity-lane,</hi> and that I was a very cruel man to my ſervants, and would abuſe my Prentices, and further you will not believe but that I lived in <hi>Half-moon</hi> Court in <hi>Bow-lane,</hi> which things are all falſe; for I never lived in <hi>Half-moon</hi> Court in my life, neither was I ever cruel to my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; cruelty was always contrary to my natural temper, therefore the neighbors that lived by me &amp; in my houſe will ſay I was one of the patienteſt men to my children and ſervants upon the earth, though none of thoſe neighbors, nor thoſe that lived in my houſe, did love my principle, or Religion, nor my commiſſion they could not abide; neither did any of them believe <hi>John Reeve</hi> nor me, yet as to that you accuſe me of, they will juſtifie it to be falſe. I underſtand you was prentice with Maſter <hi>Farmer</hi> the Smith, I knew your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter very well, his ſervants did things for me ſometimes, it may be you being his ſervant you might do it, and I not know you, but you might know me in that regard; but I ſuppoſe you miſtook the man, to ſay I was cruel to my ſervants: it was one <hi>Richard Drew</hi> one of the ſeed of the ſerpent as your ſelf is, that was cruel to his prentices, he would beat and abuſe one boy he had moſt ſadly to my knowledge, for this <hi>Richard Drew</hi> lived in my houſe at that time, when that boy was abuſed, and afterwards this ſaid <hi>Richard Drew</hi> lived in <hi>Half-moon</hi> Court ever ſince till the fire in <hi>London,</hi> and this is about twenty years ago ſince he lived in my houſe, and if this will not ſtop your lying tongue, nor convince you of your lies as to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:192297:52"/>
that, you may go on with it ſtill, for your ſlanders are not the firſt, nor the greateſt that hath bin laid upon me by you Quakers: but knowing my own innocency, I am never moved at ſuch ſlanders in the temporal; for if one man tells a lye of me, another man, though he be my enemie, yet he will juſtifie the truth on my ſide in things that are moral, for ſuch things are eaſily decided and made manifeſt here in this world, ſo that I am not offended with you for your lies and ſlanders you have reported of me in theſe things as aforeſaid: but I have a greater charge againſt you then this, even the ſin again the Holy Ghoſt, that unpardonable ſin, I can bear with any ſlanders and lies in the temporal, but with blaſphemy againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent me I cannot, nor ſhall not bear with it; for it is reported to me by the party aforeſaid, that you <hi>Richard Chair</hi> hath bin very wrath and angry with me a long time, in ſo much that you have called me a blaſphemer, and the doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by me blaſphemy, you have called me a Decever, a Lier, theſe things you have done ſeveral times, with many other wicked envious ſpeeches; alſo you have in a ſcoffing manner asked the party aforeſaid, if I did damn folks apace, and lately you asked the ſame party how many <hi>Muggleton</hi> had damned this week? doth not all theſe things ſhew unto me clearly that you are of the ſeed of the Serpent, and of the reprobat ſeed appointed to be damned, and is it not great pitty that ſuch a blaſpheming devil ſhould eſcape the Sentence of damnation ſo long as you have? for you have reigned in your blaſphemy againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent me a great while; but as the ſaying is, when your ſin is at the height then you muſt be damned, juſt as the Judges doe with thieves that have eſcaped hanging ſeveral times, yet the thief continuing ſtill in the ſame practice, the Judge ſaith, you had as good hang this man out of the way, for he will never be better, ſo the man is hanged; and when he is condemned to be hanged his ſins may be ſaid to be at the full, or at the height, ſo is it with you <hi>Richard Chair,</hi> your ſin of blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt is at the full, for you have committed that ſin very oft, ſo that it is high time to give the ſentence of eternal damnation upon you, for you will never be good; for you being the ſeed of the Serpent you cannot bring forth better fruits then blaſpemy, lies, and ſlanders againſt the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the moſt high God, the man Chriſt Jeſus in glory.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:192297:53"/>Theſe things aforeſaid conſidered, by vertue of my commiſſion from God, I do for theſe blaſphemies againſt the Holy Ghoſt I do pronounce <hi>Richard Chair</hi> Quaker curſed and damned both in ſoul and body from the preſence of God, elect men, and Angels, to eternity, and do you now ſee if you can ſcoffe this ſentence off you again; no it ſhall cleave as cloſe to you as your skin to your fleſh, and you ſhall know that the moſt High hath given power unto a mortal man like your ſelf to give ſentence of eternal damnation upon you both body and ſoul; and now you may apply your ſelf to <hi>George Fox</hi> the Quaker, and ſee if he or the light within you, can deliver you from what I have ſaid; for when I do write an anſwer to <hi>Fox</hi> his ignorant Pamphlet againſt me, I ſhall record you and he, and others in that anſwer for a company of damned Quakers; for this Sentence of yours ſhall be recorded to remain from genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to generation, ſo long as the Sun and Moon indureth.</p>
            <trailer>The Copy of a Letter ſent to <hi>Richard Chair</hi> Quaker, a Smith by trade in <hi>Shoreditch.</hi> 
               <date>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> the 26. 1667.</date>
            </trailer>
            <byline>Written by <hi>Lodwick Muggleton,</hi> one of the two laſt Prophets and Witneſſes of the Spirit unto the high and mighty God the Man Chriſt Jeſus in Glory.</byline>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:192297:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
